<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: film theory | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/film-theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-09T21:23:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Layers, the Inner Film, and Reality]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/08/layers/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-08T18:09:24-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/08/layers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Life’s but a walking shadow, a poor player that struts and frets his hour upon the stage, and then is heard no more. It is a tale told by an idiot, full of sound and fury, signifying nothing. - <em>Macbeth</em>, Shakespeare</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’ve become accustomed to viewing film, whether consciously or subconsciously, as a separate world with its own <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">intrinsic epistemology</a>. It represents a false world constructed within our own world – much like a play or other piece of narrative fiction.</p>

<p>Certain films exhibit a layering of realities – a “film within a film”, or “mise en abyme” – which can be used as a powerful narrative tool or as a metaphor for some larger concept. By interweaving stories within stories, a more complex tale can emerge which can be more intricate than the stories would be if told separately.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="stories-within-stories-flashbacks-and-narration">Stories within Stories: Flashbacks and Narration</h2>

<p>Layered stories don’t have to represent a separate reality or epistemology ; they can also be used as an expository tool. In Spielberg’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0109830/">Forrest Gump</a>, the vast majority of the story is told as a series of flashbacks – which we can view as being self-contained short films, even though they exist within the epistemological domain of the film. We believe the stories that we are being told are objective reality, even through the denouement, because we are given no reason to doubt the sincerity and authenticity of our venerable narrator at any point during the film.</p>

<p>The concept of “narrator as liar”, which I have explored, along with the layered story concept, in my original piece on <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">film epistemology</a>, shows that the concept of a sincere and authentic narrator can be subverted to use flashback sequences and narration as both a narrative tool <em>and</em> a plot device. The examples I had given included Verbal Kint in Singer’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114814/">The Usual Suspects</a> and the narrator in Fincher’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0137523/">Fight Club</a>.</p>

<p>There is an additional aspect, along with a component of ambiguity present in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0144084/">American Psycho</a>, in that that Bateman’s “inner story” continues with the “narrator as liar” concept during the natural time-flow of the film, without resorting to flashback sequences to tell the ambiguous portions of the story. It should be noted that, while there are non-temporal flow portions of the story told through flashbacks, they are not a majority of the device used to tell the story. We’re treated to the ambiguity of a narrator who <em>doesn’t know that he is a liar</em>, much like the narrator in <em>Fight Club</em> – but <em>Fight Club</em> is told, almost entirely, as a series of flashback sequences.</p>

<p>Putting aside “narrator as liar” examples, however, shows that many Hollywood films rely heavily on flashback-style authentic exposition to tell their stories within their epistemological system; so much that we don’t view those flashbacks as a potentially separate epistemological system or inner story, but as an adjunct to the primary story. In this way, we are told stories within stories without them actually <em>being</em> a logically separate story.</p>

<h2 id="stories-within-stories-stages-films-and-an-inner-story">Stories within Stories: Stages, Films, and an Inner Story</h2>

<p>Inner stories can be represented by actual film, theater, or book productions or materials. In this way, the inner story can be physically separated from the outer story – even if some ambiguity is potentially introduced in the story about that separation.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/stills/sherlockjr11.jpg" width="300" height="200" title="‘Keaton inhabiting the inner story in “Sherlock Jr”’" ></p>

<p>Keaton’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0015324/">Sherlock Jr</a> tells the majority of the narrative through the dream of the protagonist, who works as a film projectionist. This, by itself, isn’t anything special, but Keaton’s character walks through film audience present in the outer story, who are implicitly watching the inner story, and physically injects himself into the film by walking through the invisible “fourth wall” to be come a part of the inner story.</p>

<p>Weir’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120382/">The Truman Show</a> treats us to an unwitting participant in a television show, in what appears to be an allegory about man’s relationship to his creator as he discovers the true nature of his existence. Where it was a bit heavy-handed in some places (Harris’s character being named “Christof”, or the line “I am the creator … (pregnant pause) … of a television show”), the “real world” and outer story exist outside of the inner story while the denizens of the outer story are shown voyeuristically watching the predominant inner story as it slowly is shown to recede into the outer story as the metaphoric curtain is pulled back. Our protagonist <em>literally</em> bows before leaving the not-so-metaphoric stage, giving us a curtain call for the inner story moments before the outer story ends. There is also a certain implication that Truman is experiencing a widening of his perceptions and metaphorically (as well as physically) escaping the epistemological confinement in which he lived his entire life – quite possibly a not-so-subtle poke at religion.</p>

<p>I refer back to one of my favorite Gilliam films, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096764/">The Adventures of Baron Munchausen</a> for an example of an inner theatre-stage-set story, as well as to Iñárritu’s now critically-acclaimed <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2562232/">Birdman</a>. Both have an inner theater production which relates (to one degree or another) to the outer story. I’m not going to even <em>attempt</em> to do a better <a href="http://www.avclub.com/article/how-reality-becomes-function-film-technique-birdma-215503">technical analysis of the film</a> than SEK did, but I would like to note that both the inner stage play and the meta-discussion in the outer story regarding that inner play relate back to the outer plot and outer reality, even as the protagonist appears to be losing his grip on it. Theater has been used in other popular films, more recently <em>Moulin Rouge</em> and both versions of <em>To Be or Not To Be</em>, although it does not inherently contain the same implications about the nature of reality that <em>Munchausen</em> does; the concept of mise en abysme is, instead, used as a simple narrative device to drive the story forward.</p>

<p>As for a literature-based inner story, Goldman and Reiner’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779/">The Princess Bride</a> qualifies as an example of an inner story told as an outer story narrator relating the contents of an outer story work of fiction containing the inner story. A far more nuanced example of this would be Kaufmann and Jonze’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0268126/">Adaptation</a> because it defies that simple categorization. Even though Hollywood films’ authors have become increasingly self-referential – possibly due to the old adage about writing “what you know” (which is, appropriately, lampshaded in <em>Adaptation</em> through Brian Cox’s character) – most of the stories are banal tales of narcissism and self indulgence, as the author almost invariably makes him or herself the infallible protagonist.</p>

<h2 id="ambiguity-between-inner-and-outer-story">Ambiguity Between Inner and Outer Story</h2>

<p>In <em>Adaptation</em>, Kaufmann’s inner story starts by intentionally confusing the real world with the outer story. This trend continues throughout the course of the film, and was so successful at confusing the intended epistemology that a <em>fictional character</em>, Kaufmann’s twin brother, received a joint writing award for the screenplay for <em>Adaptation</em>. He also creates an inner story as the screenplay adaptation for “The Orchid Thief” – which is a <em>real</em> book in our reality, and which serves as the <em>real world</em> source for the story material in <em>Adaptation</em>. The outer story is an adaptation of “The Orchid Thief”, but so is the inner story. It is a masterpiece of both ambiguous epistemic domains and an interesting viewpoint regarding the entire craft behind film adaptations.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well, I really want to encourage a kind of fantasy, a kind of magic. I love the term magic realism, whoever invented it — I do actually like it because it says certain things. It’s about expanding how you see the world. I think we live in an age where we’re just hammered, hammered to think this is what the world is. Television’s saying, everything’s saying “That’s the world.” And it’s not the world. The world is a million possible things. - Terry Gilliam, <a href="http://www.believermag.com/issues/200303/?read=interview_gilliam">Salman Rushdie talks with Terry Gilliam</a> <sup>(<a href="http://www.webcitation.org/6WsvDrr34">cite</a>)</sup></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would be doing any readers of this piece a serious disservice by failing to mention Terry Gilliam’s works in a piece regarding inner and outer story ambiguities. Most of his films have some sort of delusion, story, or narrative work which tries to transcend the barrier between imagination and reality – of inner story and outer story.</p>

<p><em>Munchausen</em> delivers this ambiguity through both filmmaking techniques, such as cross-cutting quickly between two conflicting layers of story (the bombing of the theater contrasted with the escape from the Sultan’s palace) or mixing sets in such a way to deliberately fuse the stories together (when the actor playing the Sultan is pushed out onto the stage for the reveal that he is now in the Sultan’s palace). The battle between imagination and reality is given a physical form, as well, through the characters of The Right Ordinary Horatio Jackson (Jonathan Pryce) and the Baron himself. In one of the inner stories, Jackson assassinates the Baron as he is being accepted and lauded by a world which had rejected him – but it is shown to be an inner story, and the Baron (imagination) is still able to outlive and outwit Jackson (reality).</p>

<p>A similar, yet different, scenario is set up in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114746/">Twelve Monkeys</a>. Cole has a recurring dream about seeing a man shot before he returns to the past – but is the “past” really the present, and his “present” (our future) really just a delusion? Gilliam spends a good portion of the film playing up the ambiguity of those two states against Cole’s fragile mental state. We’re given <em>some</em> sort of epistemic relief when Dr Railly finds pictures of Cole in a history book and identifies a bullet as being very old – but there’s never really any certainty, and the ambiguity can theoretically continue on. Cole’s “dream” is revealed in the final act to be his unknowing memory of his own death, completing his timeline in an out-of-sequence circle. Even though Cole is warned that he will be lost to the past (assuming that his “present” is actually reality) and told that history is immutable, he still tries to change it. We are all puppets in the grand scheme of history – from an anthropological point of view, this has already happened – but Cole can’t accept that he is not the master of his own destiny.</p>

<p>Another example of ambiguity between outer and inner story / film is Brooks’ <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0071230/">Blazing Saddles</a>. Not only do the characters seem to be periodically aware that they are part of the outer film, occasionally using frontality to speak directly to the audience a la Groucho Marx, but the outer film <em>is</em> the inner film. Much as he did in <em>Spaceballs</em>, Brooks conflates the inner and outer films while making it clear that the characters are somewhat aware that they exist within a film. <em>Spaceballs</em> does this through both dialogue (“The ship’s too big; if I walk, the movie’ll be over.”) and through entire scenes (the “instant cassettes” scene). Although this is primarily played for laughs, it intrinsically changes our perceptions of the characters through our knowledge of their self-aware nature. <em>Blazing Saddles</em> not only juxtaposes the ending fight scene in Rock Ridge with the characters <em>literally</em> breaking the fourth wall into other sets, but has the characters simultaneously watching their film while other characters are, according to the in-universe continuity, still making that film. Continuity even carries over between the two layers, with Wilder holding his theater popcorn bucket in the scene after he is shown to be in a theater … watching the very film that he has yet to finish.</p>

<p>The last example I’d like to cite is the excellent <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0352520/">The Life and Death of Peter Sellers</a>. It follows an interwoven narrative, given with subjective exposition by the titular character, played expertly by the always-superb Geoffrey Rush. The story within story motif is clear as Sellers is shown intermittently to be playing <em>every character</em> whenever the thin curtain between the outer and inner material is pulled back. The titular character is so egotistical and full of himself that we are constantly reminded that we are seeing the world through <em>his</em> subjective gaze. We have to assume that what we are seeing somewhat resembles the objective truth, even though our narrator is a self-proclaimed liar, to one degree or another. Apart from Rush playing Sellers playing his characters as a function of narcissism, it functions as a film technique to point to Sellers’ lack of a solid sense of self or personality – much as the discontinuous editing technique of <em>Deconstructing Harry</em> points to the fractured way that its eponymous character views reality.</p>

<h2 id="reality-as-a-shared-delusion">Reality as a Shared Delusion</h2>

<p>Even though the Wachowskis’ <em>The Matrix</em> popularized this in film culture, the idea that reality as we know it is just a shared delusion has been around for a while. John Carpenter’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096256/">They Live</a> insinuated, more than ten years before <em>The Matrix</em>, that most people live in a shared delusion, unable to see the reality that exists around them. The inner story and the outer story share not only diagetic space, but also epistemological space. They live in the same world, even if the shared delusion of some make it appear to be a different world. The campy pastiche film <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086856/">The Adventures of Buckaroo Bonzai Across the 8th Dimension</a> (which predated <em>They Live</em> by four years) uses a similar separation between inner and outer story. It does use a different differentiation mechanism: a spark of energy rather than a pair of sunglasses.</p>

<p><em>The Matrix</em> physically separated the denizens of the shared delusion by embedding the inner story in the container of a computer simulation, which the outer story characters, once aware, could jump in and out of. It played very heavily off of the concept of awareness, in that some people in the inner story could jump to the outer story by having knowledge that they were essentially characters in a fiction. There are a lot of philosophical overtones present, and I’m sure others have done far more justice to analyzing them than I would have done.</p>

<p>Proyas’s <em>Dark City</em> is an interesting hybrid between the type of shared delusions in <em>They Live</em> and <em>The Matrix</em>. Like <em>They Live</em>, the characters experiencing the shared delusion of the inner story share the same space as the characters experiencing the outer story, and much like <em>The Matrix</em>, they are unwitting test subjects, whose gruesome reality is not apparent to them until they are willing to take a leap of faith, of sorts (the red pill/blue pill test in <em>The Matrix</em> and trying to find Shell Beach in <em>Dark City</em>). In <em>Dark City</em>, no one questions why there is never any sun, nor why they never have any desire to leave the city, nor why they only have dim, distant memories; they accept the reality with which they are presented.</p>

<p>Nolan’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/">Inception</a> not only has a inner story, but <em>three more</em> story layers beneath. One of the criticisms I’ve heard about <em>Inception</em> was that, due to the varying story layers, it was difficult to follow; I didn’t agree with that assessment, but felt compelled to include it here. Depending on whether or not you agree that the “real world” shown as the outer story layer is, indeed, the outer story layer or not, there may be an unseen layer between the further visible story layer and our reality. To further complicate matters, the characters are all meant to represent different functions of filmmakers – there is a “meta-meaning” on top of the already convoluted layered-reality story line. One of the most important epistemological constants in all of the realities is that the inhabitants of any of these stories are, much like the characters in most films, unaware that they are living in a story, or a story within a story, or a story within a story within …</p>

<p>Much like <em>Dark City</em>’s theme of the Strangers trying to steal our souls / humanity through our memories, Jeunet’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0112682/">La cité des enfants perdus</a> centers around the theme of a mad scientist, Krank, trying to take youth / life from children by stealing their dreams. The film is rife with shared delusions and obsessions, from the clones’ attempt to prove which is “l’originale”, to Krank’s obsession with living through the dreams of others, to One’s need for family to live out his dystopian existence.</p>

<h2 id="why-does-this-technique-resonate-with-us">Why does this technique resonate with us?</h2>

<p>I don’t think I can put forth a concrete answer to that, mostly due to the way that eisegesis trumps exegesis in the majority of film viewers.</p>

<p>My working theory is that layered stories resonate because they tap into some subconscious desire for us to see this world as as dream – or at the very least, a part of a bigger, better world. To quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s an old joke - um… two elderly women are at a Catskill mountain resort, and one of ‘em says, “Boy, the food at this place is really terrible.” The other one says, “Yeah, I know; and such small portions.” Well, that’s essentially how I feel about life - full of loneliness, and misery, and suffering, and unhappiness, and it’s all over much too quickly.” - <em>Annie Hall</em>, Woody Allen</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This desire for more – of something – generally is accompanied with the idea that the something we seek is <em>better</em> than what we have here and now. Film is, to one extent or another, escapism. It could be argued that one of the pushes for epistemic closure in film stems from our desire not to let the comforting delusion of the film universe, which we love, abruptly end with a credit roll.</p>

<p>There are some films where the story breaks out of an inner world into an outer one, and the outer world is far more horrifying and bleak than the inner world. This subverts our desires for a better outer world, as exploited masterfully in Proyas’s <em>Dark City</em> and the Wachowskis’ <em>The Matrix</em>. It is also implied in <em>The Truman Show</em> that the outer world is a terrible place, by Christof.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Epistemology II]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/06/film-epistemology-ii/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T09:12:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/06/film-epistemology-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This continues the analysis from my <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">previous article on epistemology in film</a>. It makes more sense in the context of the first part.</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="known-unknowns-and-unknown-unknowns">Known unknowns and unknown unknowns</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say we know there are some things we do not know. But there are also unknown unknowns – the ones we don’t know we don’t know. And if one looks throughout the history of our country and other free countries, it is the latter category that tend to be the difficult ones. - Donald Rumsfeld</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m not a big fan of Donald Rumsfeld, but his attempt to weasel out of a bad PR situation by echoing the sentiments of Nassim Taleb’s “Fooled by Randomness” does have a silver lining of real value in epistemological evaluation – as well as in the analysis of the effects of intentionally incomplete epistemology on film viewing.</p>

<p>There are certain things that are going to fall outside the realm of narrative exposition – our “unknown unknowns”. These can manifest as plot twists, or may simply contain areas of knowledge which are tangential, to a certain degree, to our principal characters or plot.</p>

<p>The “known unknowns” are the principal fodder for epistemic expansion. For example, in the context of Nolan’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0468569/">The Dark Knight</a>, we are treated to a series of false-lead backstories for the Joker, but we’re always aware that we have <em>no idea</em> where he comes from, or anything outside of the explicitly available information in the film epistemology.</p>

<p>The oddest quadrant of the known/unknown delineation is the “unknown known”. In the system of information that we <em>don’t know that we know</em>, there are plenty of subtle hints and pieces of subliminal information which we ingest during the course of viewing the first acts of a film before the potential payoff in the last act. We may not be conscious that we know these things until they are brought to our attention, and the information moves to become a “known known”.</p>

<h2 id="epistemology-as-part-of-a-larger-canon">Epistemology as part of a larger canon</h2>

<p>As part of a response to the first part of this analysis, a friend pointed me to an <a href="http://kotaku.com/why-people-get-so-worked-up-about-canon-1688856413">examination of how we view canon</a> <sup>(<a href="http://www.webcitation.org/6WrSMmtox">cite</a>)</sup>. There are a number of different aspects to the relationship between epistemology and canon.</p>

<p>A television series presents an interesting situation; it poses the question of how to deal with a single work, generally under the care of multiple auteurs, in the form of multiple directors over the course of a single season/series. In traditional multiple episode television works, the story arc writers function as primary auteurs, using a “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible_%28writing%29">bible</a>” to attempt to keep epistemic consistency across works. Deviances can (and have been) introduced when interpreted by individual episode directors.</p>

<p>With multi-medium canon, spanning graphic novels, television, film, et al, the potential problems maintaining a single definitive canon multiply. It’s difficult enough to maintain canon between films or television episodes in the same medium, but, as each storytelling medium has its own caveats and rules, there are differences in the way that information is conveyed – not to mention that the presence of multiple auteurs (specific to each medium) would provide a potentially corrupting influence on the epistemology specific to the canon.</p>

<p>An example of this could be seen to be the interactions between large canon works, such as some of the DC comics universe works (i.e. Batman, Superman) and the television and film adaptations of those same works.</p>

<h2 id="altering-canon----and-the-burden-of-appeasing-fandom">Altering canon – and the burden of appeasing fandom</h2>

<p>The auteurs involved in the adaptations will sometimes drastically alter canon – <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0279600/">Smallville</a> and Singer’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0348150/">Superman Returns</a> in the case of the Superman franchise, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3749900/">Gotham</a> and Burton’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096895/">Batman</a> as examples in the case of the Batman franchise. Some of these works override / ignore existing canon, while some of them provide prequel and sequel material; for the moment, the question I’d like to pose is “what does a prequel or sequel <em>owe</em> canonical epistemology?”</p>

<p>There are a few things which I believe should be taken into account when trying to determine the answer to that question.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Intent</strong>. What is the intention of the prequel/sequel? Putting aside the general overriding motive of monetary gain, motivations can generally be split between a primary financial motivation to profit off of the material or an intention to either “re-imagine” the canon (assuming that the auteur can produce a superior outcome) or augment the canon. A primarily financial motive will most likely result in the canonical epistemology being set aside for the sake of increasing or pleasing the target demographic.</li>
  <li><strong>Integrity</strong>. It seems as thought the vast majority of epistemic extension and exploration is done without much consideration for the impact on both the integrity and the closure of the film’s epistemology. Considerate works which are considering attaching themselves to existing epistemology of a larger canon should be considering these factors before altering the epistemology. Any addition to canonical epistemology changes both the perception of prior works and potentially their emotional impact in retrospect.</li>
</ul>

<p>Fandom have devoted time and/or money to a “franchise”, presumably because they identify or sympathize with something espoused in the larger canon. Because of this largely emotional attachment to the larger body of work, fandom can place a great emphasis on preserving the present state of canon and keeping the epistemology intact – or perhaps as close to the state in which they originally found it when they became attached to the canonical works. This temporal attachment goes toward explaining why, for example, fans of <a href="http://tardis.wikia.com/wiki/Doctor_Who">Doctor Who</a> generally tend to view the incarnation of the Doctor which was their first introduction to the series as the subjectively “best” incarnation of that character.</p>

<p>There is another possibility inherent in the relationship between fandom and epistemology, which is that the viewer will (almost obsessively) attempt to seek out any epistemic closure or extension which is offered to them. I posit that it is the result of a deep emotional attachment to the characters and situations present in the canon which cause the viewer to attempt to create the most vivid knowledge-set of the canon and attempt to achieve epistemic closure.</p>

<h2 id="expectations--the-burden-of-context">Expectations ; the burden of context</h2>

<p>The context in which we view the epistemic system of a film, or the subjective epistemology, is almost as important as the objective epistemology given by the subject film.</p>

<p>The emotional and subjective knowledge baggage we bring into a film don’t necessarily have to have been introduced by other works in a canon. They could have come from other films in the same genre, adaptations of written works with similar subject material, earlier attempts at adapting the source material from the film, or even subjective life experiences of the viewer.</p>

<h2 id="reboot----uncorrupting-the-epistemology">Reboot – uncorrupting the epistemology?</h2>

<p>Over time, epistemology of a canon can become corrupted, self-contradictory, or suffer an overall loss in quality. One of the accepted methods for uncorrupting the epistemology of a larger work has been the <em>reboot</em>, another is retroactive continuity, or “retconning”, which has been used extensively in graphic novel and comic works as well as <a href="https://matthewkirshenblatt.wordpress.com/2013/12/24/time-travel-and-retconning-revisionism-and-reconstructionism-in-doctor-who/">television and film</a> <sup>(<a href="http://www.webcitation.org/6WrTwHOTQ">cite</a>)</sup>. There are a number of different successful methodologies which have been used for epistemic resets through reboots:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Complete epistemic do-over</strong>. This involves a disregarding of the entire literal epistemology, perhaps keeping some of the more commonly regarded portions of the canon, most likely to appease the target demographic’s past connection with prior incarnations. Examples of this would include the multiple Batman series reboots (Burton, Nolan), as well as the recent Spiderman reboots.</li>
  <li><strong>Time Travel Adjustment</strong>. This is when a series simply invents a <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/CosmicRetcon">time-travel type retcon or reset</a> in order to change basic principals of the epistemology. This differs from complete epistemic reconfigurations because the original continuity and epistemology is respected and then explained away or altered through the use of a time-travel narrative device. Popular examples of this include Abrams’ <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0796366/">Star Trek</a> reboot, and the <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1340138/">Terminator: Genisys</a> film. Zemeckis’s <a href="">Back to the Future</a> franchise worked almost entirely by turning this concept into a plot device – a concept mirrored by the recent <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3148266/">12 Monkeys</a> television series, but ironically not from its source material, the Gilliam <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114746/">Twelve Monkeys</a> film.</li>
  <li><strong>Hand Wave</strong>. Quite possibly the <em>laziest</em> form of epistemic reset. It generally involves simply ignoring certain aspects of previous epistemology in the canon or offering a glib explanation – usually prior films within a designated series. A general example of this would be the <em>Highlander</em> sequels, although it has also been part of a fairly well known <em>Doctor Who</em> trope for the majority of the run of the show.</li>
  <li><strong>Revisionist Adjustment</strong>. Adjusting portions of an already established epistemology for the purpose of correcting perceived mistakes or inadequacies. An example of this would be the introduction of Darth Vader as Luke Skywalker’s father in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080684/">Empire Strikes Back</a> after it was explained through explicit narrative exposition in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0076759/">A New Hope</a> that Vader had <em>murdered</em> Luke’s father; it was <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/Retcon">retconned</a> during <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086190/">Return of the Jedi</a> through a particularly clumsy dialogue-based hand wave. (This is only one of many, many examples of retroactive continuity in the Star Wars universe.)</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Narrative Exposition in Film]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/02/narrative-exposition-in-film/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-02T18:30:19-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/02/narrative-exposition-in-film</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Narrative exposition</strong>, or simply <strong>exposition</strong>, is the insertion of important background information within a story; for example, information about the setting, characters’ back-stories, prior plot events, historical context, etc. (from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposition_%28narrative%29">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Within the confines of the skeleton of a film work (the script), there are many ways to impart information which would not otherwise be assumed by the viewer or implied by the filmmaker. I posit that the way in which expository information is imparted to a viewer via the medium of film is as important <em>if not more important</em> than the information which is being imparted.</p>

<p>As with any other aspect of film as an art form and medium, there isn’t a single “correct” way of doing anything. There isn’t one particular correct framing which needs to be used for a shot, not only a single focal length lens or camera brand which would have to be used to get the only valid shot possible – and in much the same vein, there are many different more-or-less-equally-correct methods of imparting that information. I’d like to explore the mechanisms and caveats of each of them.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="objectivity-and-subjectivity">Objectivity and Subjectivity</h2>

<p>It’s an interesting concept – there is no real delineation between objectivity and subjectivity as far as narration goes, if we consider that any narration is part of the <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">artificially separate epistemic system of a film</a>, and therefore could have a level of objectivity or subjectivity within the confines of a certain character, but which presents the same objective face to the viewing audience as a whole (in that they all will see the same footage), which will be subjectively interpreted by each viewer (since even though they physically see the same footage, each person subjectively interprets what they see differently).</p>

<p>If we view the epistemology of the film as a system which we mentally “enter” during the course of film viewing, we can attempt to assign a level of subjectivity or objectivity <em>within those parameters</em> to determine how objective exposition appears to be <em>within that system</em>. This is the virtual vantage point which I will be using during the remainder of my analysis of different forms of exposition, so as not to overly confuse the concepts.</p>

<h2 id="narrative-exposition--through-narration">Narrative exposition … through narration</h2>

<p>One of the most popular methods for imparting information to the audience of a film (or other visual work) is by simply having either a character (through a monologue or soliloquy) tell the audience the pieces of the story or other details which the auteurs wish to impart, directly speak to the audience through a voiceover, or espouse the information through a conversation between characters – or even a character who exists <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MrExposition">only to spout expository information</a>.</p>

<p>Out of all of these methodologies, I tend to look down on voiceover narration as the most egregious, because it comes across as an indicator of either laziness or over-complexity, as the auteurs did not believe that the information could be imparted in any way <em>other than essentially having the film universe speak through a disembodied voice directly to the viewer</em>, even if it comes by way of a character. (I make the distinction between a voiceover of a diary being written or read and this type of narration, simply because a diary-type voiceover would otherwise fall under being categorized as a soliloquy.)</p>

<h2 id="captioncrawl-exposition">Caption/crawl exposition</h2>

<p>Popularized in modern cinema by George Lucas’s Star Wars intro crawl but dating back to silent movie title cards, crawl exposition is more or less a written form of voiceover narration, presented in a slightly varied form. It could be argued that caption/crawl titles actually present a perceptually higher level of objectivity to the viewer, as they speak with an omniscient deity-like authority rather than speaking through an anonymous narrator or using a character as a puppet of sorts.</p>

<h2 id="mise-en-scne-exposition">Mise-en-scène exposition</h2>

<p>This is where my cinematography sensibilities come in. There are many methods of using the camera as a virtual narrator, and it is a very powerful tool to use, since the camera’s recorded mise-en-scène is the lens by which the viewer perceives the whole of the film universe. This gives the filmmaker great latitude in deciding how much or how little information can be imparted from the framing and composition alone, before the actors’ dialogue or motions are considered at all.</p>

<p>Some even consider the camera to be its own character, and though this is fairly specific to directors and cinematographers, being</p>

<p>In the interests of space and time, I’ll just briefly overview some of the more successful methods.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Frame Composition</strong>. I’ll refer to <a href="https://vimeo.com/118078262">Tony Zhou’s breakdown of Kurosawa’s The Bad Sleep Well</a> for a more in-depth analysis of how the way elements dance in and out of frame and are arranged <em>in a single shot</em> can tell us more about the characters than pages of dialogue or a flurry of quick cuts.</li>
  <li><a href="http://acephalous.typepad.com/acephalous/2011/01/fight-club.html">Frontality</a>. The way a character can be looking directly at the viewer (although, to be fair, we only <em>perceive</em> that they’re looking directly at us, and for the most part, the camera is taking the place of another character) can subconsciously impart a wealth of information. It allows us to put ourselves in the place of one of the characters, and the way we perceive them can shift.</li>
  <li><strong>Lighting</strong>. Even though particular film idioms like film noir are specifically known for using lighting for exposition, neo-noir films have brought this technique back into the mainstream. Using visual idioms like casting bars of shadow across a character’s face to indicate that they feel trapped or cornered, for example.</li>
  <li><strong>Objectivity/Subjectivity</strong> can be implied by the type of shot used, and even the level of stabilization employed. If we need to get into a character’s head to imply thought, many cinematographers have used dolly-in closeup shots to imply figuratively going into the character’s head (or in the case of the intro to <strong>Fight Club</strong>, literally coming out of it).</li>
  <li><strong>3D Forced Perspective</strong>. I don’t particularly like “3D” films, especially as they generally come off like large pop-up books to me, but the ability to force certain objects to be more apparent, and therefore more important, by using 3D manipulation is another fairly effective tool. If a sword appears to be a few inches from your nose in a movie theater, you’re going to be paying attention to it.</li>
  <li><strong>Montage theory</strong>. Exposition introduced through the process of editing is another method, more firmly in the realm of post-production – and iterated in most texts on the Soviet theory of montage – which allows the juxtaposition of images and sounds to imply certain narrative exposition or foreshadowing. Cutting to reaction shots can coerce the viewer into associating those reactions directly with the content of the prior shot. This form is quite prevalent in many visual mediums, including film, television, and graphic novels.</li>
</ul>

<p>These can be used in conjunction with one another, or, as in the case of De Palma’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0117060/">Mission Impossible</a>, they can be used to deliver contradictory viewpoints. In <em>Mission Impossible</em>’s first reveal sequence, Voight’s character allows Cruise’s character to use dialogue to confirm his intended exposition – which is false – but De Palma shows a series of flashback sequences from slightly different angles, revealing the true nature of the exposition, even as Cruise’s voiceover contradicts it. Cruise is lying to Voight, but telling <em>us</em> the truth.</p>

<h2 id="holistic-exposition">Holistic exposition</h2>

<p>Holistic exposition is the dissemination of information through observed character movements, actions, and observed and inferred intents. An auteur can impart vast amounts of information through the situations and non-discrete expositional phrasing. (I make the distinction between “holistic exposition” and “mise-en-scène exposition”, even though the latter is a subset of the former, for the sake of dividing between camera-based exposition and all other types of holistic exposition.)</p>

<p>For example, if a character is lonely, the character does not have to state “I am lonely” for the viewer to understand the character’s loneliness. It is just as effective, if not more so, to allow situations to unfold where the character is allowed to <em>imply</em> that same loneliness by actions, or even in non-explicit dialogue.</p>

<p>There are a number of caveats to holistic exposition.</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Intellectual Laziness</em>. There’s a certain percentage of any viewing demographic that does not want to have to <em>think</em> about how information is presented – they just want the characters to come out and say whatever they’re thinking.</li>
  <li><em>Ambiguity</em> can be introduced unintentionally if there is more than one potential cause or source for the holistic expositional element. Is the character picking up a knife because they’re scared, hungry, or angry?</li>
  <li><em>Actors</em> make or break this style of exposition. If the actors lack subtlety or under- (or over-) act their part, it can destroy carefully planned exposition.</li>
  <li><em>Planning</em>. It requires much more subtlety to reveal information through holistic means than to simply tell the viewer what you want them to know, which requires a greater level of planning from the writing on down to the director in the chain of auteurship.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="respecting-holistic-epistemology-or-only-tell-what-you-need-to-survive">Respecting holistic epistemology (or “Only tell what you need to survive”)</h2>

<p>Not everything has to be explicitly told or known for a story or universe to be complete. As I had mentioned in my first piece of film epistemology, epistemic closure isn’t a necessary thing; the lack of it can has the ability to change the perception of a film by the viewers.</p>

<p>It should be noted that some of the wave of independent filmmakers starting in the 1990s seemed to rely on over-telling stories by introducing potentially irrelevant information to the plot through over-loquacious characters who buried their narrative exposition in paragraphs of misleading dialogue. Kevin Smith and Quentin Tarantino are two examples of this school of narrative over-exposition, but there have been many who have attempted the same techniques with varying levels of success. (It takes a certain level of craft to create dialogue which works this way but does not come off as cloyingly banal or irritatingly uninteresting.)</p>

<h2 id="dark-city-an-exercise-in-comparison">“Dark City”, an exercise in comparison</h2>

<p>Alex Proyas’ gothic neo-noir/horror/sci-fi classic <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0118929/">Dark City</a> offers a very apparent dichotomic illustration of the differences in narrative exposition choices. The theatrical cut begins with a paragraph of indulgent voice-over narration provided by Kiefer Sutherland’s character (spoilers, of course):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>First, there was darkness. Then came the Strangers. They were a race as old as time itself. They had mastered the ultimate technology – ability to alter physical reality by will alone. They called this ability “Tuning.” But they were dying. Their civilization was in decline, and so they abandoned their world, seeking a cure for their own mortality. Their endless journey brought them to a small, blue world… in the farthest corner of the galaxy. Our world. Here, they thought they had finally found… what they had been searching for. My name is Dr. Daniel Poe Schreber. I am just a man. I help the Strangers conduct their experiments. I have betrayed my own kind. <em>(courtesy of <a href="http://www.script-o-rama.com/movie_scripts/d/dark-city-script-transcript-proyas.html">script-o-rama</a>)</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The narration sets up the basics of the plot, and now the viewer knows far more than any of the principal characters other than <em>Dr. Shreber</em>. The other principals spend the majority (at least two thirds) of the film coming up to speed with this information, while we watch along – textbook objective viewing.</p>

<p>The director’s cut, however cuts out the narration entirely, as well as extending some scenes to add additional dialogue and action to help round out certain parts of the plot. The major change which this has on the perceptual quality of the film is that we don’t know what the characters know (unknown knowns), and we don’t know what the characters don’t know (unknown unknowns). This, at least in theory, gives us greater subjectivity in our relationship to the perceptions and situations of the principal characters. <em>We don’t even know the name for the villains until the third act.</em> It also creates the potential for a fair amount of confusion in the first act, as we don’t know <em>anything</em> outside of what we holistically learn – John Murdock wakes up in a bathtub near a corpse, and someone is chasing him.</p>

<p>I found that while viewing the director’s cut of Dark City, the “larger truth” (or the “bigger lie”, depending on your perception) behind the city seemed to come as more of a revelation. I say “seemed to come” as I’m incapable of watching a second version of the film in a totally objective light ; my context has been clouded by my previous viewings. For example, it’s less noticeable that there is never any sunlight, as the characters seem blissfully unaware of that detail.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Epistemology]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T12:08:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to take a brief look at film epistemology. In order for that to work, I’m going to be positing that for our purposes, each film is its own self-contained universe with its own rules and knowledge both known and unknown.</p>

<p><em>(As a disclaimer, I’m no Scott Eric Kaufmann; I’m not going to be using visual illustrations, and precious few (if any) citations. There are also bound to be spoilers of every variety, so if a film is mentioned, avert your gaze if you don’t want to learn important truths about its ending.)</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="film-as-philosophy-and-self-contained-world">Film as philosophy and self contained world</h2>

<p>As I’ve just mentioned, a singular film can be seen as its own self-contained universe – a universe populated with rules and knowledge which are specific to that universe. Sometimes that world looks much like our own and shares many similar traits, sometimes it shares many visual similarities but a different history, and sometimes it bears little resemblance to the world and universe we know and try to understand.</p>

<p>The important similarity is that there’s a philosophical system underlying each of these film universes, built on the philosophies and mores of the auteurs of each film (writer, director, et al). Some popular films and film franchises have generated series of philosophical works – Star Wars, in particular, comes to mind – as well as compendiums of knowledge and in-universe canon of all varieties. Within the confines of these films, the epistemology has been grown in such a way as to allow a more immersive universe (according to the optimist), and/or wring more money from dedicated fans (according to the pessimist).</p>

<p>One of the things that has tended to irritate my own film sensibilities have been when films violate their own rules. Film is a suspension of disbelief, but there are certain rules explicitly or implicitly set out during the course of the film, which define the epistemology in which I have to be immersed while watching. A film shouldn’t violate its own rules, otherwise I end up setting aside my suspension of disbelief and become very aware that I’m watching a film.</p>

<p>To elaborate, I quote <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/WillingSuspensionOfDisbelief">TV Tropes’ excellent page on this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Any creative endeavor, certainly any written creative endeavor, is only successful to the extent that the audience offers this willing suspension as they read, listen, or watch. It’s part of an unspoken contract: The writer provides the reader/viewer/player with a good story, and in return, they accept the reality of the story as presented, and accept that characters in the fictional universe act on their own accord.
An author’s work, in other words, does not have to be realistic, only believable and internally consistent (see <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MagicAIsMagicA">Magic A Is Magic A</a>). When the author pushes an audience beyond what they’re willing to accept, the work fails in the eyes of that particular audience. As far as science fiction is concerned, viewers are usually willing to go along with <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TechnoBabble">creative explanations</a> which is why <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/PhysicsGoof">people don’t criticize your wormhole travel system</a> or <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AppliedPhlebotinum">how a shrinking potion doesn’t violate the laws of matter conservation</a>, but even in the more fantastical genres, suspension of disbelief can be broken when a work breaks its own established laws or asks the audience to put up with too many things that come off as contrived.
A common way of putting this is “You can ask an audience to believe the impossible, but not the improbable.” For example, people will accept that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AWizardDidIt">the Grand Mage can teleport across the world</a>, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/StealthInSpace">the spaceship has technology that makes it completely invisible</a> without rendering its own sensors blind, but they won’t accept that the ferocious carnivore <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AssPull">just happened to have a heart attack and die</a> right before it attacked the main character, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/HollywoodHacking">the hacker guessed his enemy’s password on the first try just by typing random letters</a>, at least without <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/JustifiedTrope">some prior detail justifying it</a> or one of the Rules listed below coming into play. What is in <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/RealLife">Real Life</a> impossible just has to be made the norm in the setting and kept consistent.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="epistemological-overlap-and-suspension-of-disbelief">Epistemological overlap and suspension of disbelief</h2>

<p>As much as there is a suspension of disbelief inherent in any viewing of film (it is, after all, a series of quickly presented still frames in an artificial viewing environment), we require a certain epistemological overlap with our own universe / reality.</p>

<p>There is a certain range of deviation from reality which is acceptable in the majority of film. I believe this is because film has to balance a sense of relatability, which is produced by overlapping epistemology with reality, with its own deviations and rules. If a film is <em>too close</em> to reality without matching it exactly, we end up encountering something similar to the “<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mori_Uncanny_Valley.svg">uncanny valley</a>”, where we become disenfranchised from the reality with which we are presented because it becomes very clear to us that it isn’t real, and suspension of disbelief falls apart.</p>

<p>I believe that resources like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/CinemaSins">CinemaSins</a> are a combination of relevance and irrelevance. In regards to that resource in particular, it shows irrelevance when it posits that film should obey all of the rules of the real world in most of its critiques, but shows relevance when it acknowledges a film’s epistemological separateness and shows how that film breaks its own rules.</p>

<h2 id="narrator-as-deity--narrator-as-liar">Narrator as deity / narrator as liar</h2>

<p>Many films employ an explicit narrator, whether by title scroll (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0076759/">Star Wars: A New Hope</a>), voice-over (Princess Irulan and Paul Atreides’ voiceovers in David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0087182/">Dune</a>), by a narrator telling an inner story (Verbal Kint in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114814/">The Usual Suspects</a>), by physically narrating a written inner story (The Grandfather in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779/">The Princess Bride</a>), or even a character’s internal soliloquy (the narrator in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0137523/">Fight Club</a>). This is generally done to augment what could otherwise be clumsy and/or ineffectual exposition through other means in the film – or even to give a certain amount of backstory in order to produce enough in-universe knowledge to allow viewers to be sufficiently immersed in the universe which they are presented.</p>

<p>The narrator has a particular type of power and hold over the viewer ; they are the lens with which the fabricated universe of the film is viewed. Even though we are presented with visual and auditory information through picture and sound, the narrator is the <strong>voice of god</strong> (or at least some sort of prophetic voice, if we’re going with the religious metaphor) as far as this universe is concerned. But what if this omnipresent narrator isn’t telling the truth about this universe?</p>

<p>Two extremely visible cases of this occur in David Fincher’s “Fight Club” and Bryan Singer’s “The Usual Suspects”.</p>

<p>In “Fight Club”, we’re led down a paraprosdokian storyline by a nameless author, who not only tells us a story in his droning monotone, but also shows us his misadventures with a character we know as Tyler Durden. Only at the end of the second act do we learn that our author has been lying to us, much as he has been lying to himself. What we have seen as a fully realistic and discernibly physical part of this universe is a figment of the narrator’s imagination. We’re forced to change our view of this film universe as part of an unsettling experience which helps define a major part of the attraction to that film.</p>

<p>In “The Usual Suspects”, we confront a similar situation – except that the narrator (Verbal Kint) is very much aware that he’s misleading both us and Agent Kujan. Our realization comes right after the perceived climax of the film, as Verbal allows Agent Kujan to apparently convince both himself and the audience that the elusive Keyser Soze is really Dean Keaton. Mere moments later, Kujan comes to the realization at which we are meant to arrive ; he has been lied to. This is shocking to the audience because we implicitly trust the narrator to guide us to the truths of the film universe which he inhabits, yet he betrays us, breaking our knowledge of his universe. Even more troubling is that we’re not sure how much of the last few hours has been real (according to the film universe), and how much was made up by the narrator. A false world, inhabited by a virtual deity who hides the nature of that false world with yet another representation.</p>

<p>Yet another power that on-screen narration (in particular) has is that it can provide the film equivalent to the literary “aside” or footnote. Groucho Marx was known for pioneering this form of soliloquy, which came to be known colloquially as “breaking the fourth wall”. It allows the author to speak through his/her characters directly to the audience without the need for voiceover – but it shows the universe <em>stop</em> around the narrator. What they’re saying is so important that their universe <em>literally stops</em> so that you, the captive audience, can bear witness to it. In Woody Allen’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0075686/">Annie Hall</a>, the narrator’s diatribe (aimed directly at the viewing audience, in spite of the people around him) appears to be breaking the fourth wall – but the subject of his anger is revealed to be able to actually <em>hear what he is saying</em>, in contravention of Groucho Marx’s tradition of film asides. Allen then proceeds to almost literally pull a rabbit out of a hat by magically pulling Marshall McLuhan seemingly out of thin air to make his point for him, then resumes his narrative aside. To Allen, the narrative aside is just another platform on which to base a joke, but it speaks to the unspoken acknowledgement that the narrator is aware at some level that he is part of a film universe; he just bends the rules a little.</p>

<h2 id="epistemic-closure-vs-incomplete-epistemology">Epistemic closure vs incomplete epistemology</h2>

<p>Another supposition I’d like to put forward is that epistemic closure in a film universe essentially eliminates a very specific source of tension. “Settling films” (films which leave the viewer with a feeling of completion) tend not to leave unanswered questions, and if it does leave unanswered questions, they’re generally fairly benign or immaterial to substantial portions of the central plot.</p>

<p>On the other hand, we can look at some of the films of Christopher Nolan as examples of intentionally incomplete epistemology. A number of his films employ missing information or information which can be interpreted in a number of different ways to provide differing conclusions or philosophies to his films.</p>

<p>“Inception”, for example, famously ends with a shot of a spinning top which either will or will not fall down to indicate whether the principal character is trapped within a never-ending dream. Depending on whether you believe that he is awake or asleep, it changes the interpretation of the ending. (Nolan had actually said that fixating on the top essentially missed the point of the ending, as Cobb is happy, which is the important part of the conclusion.)</p>

<p>“The Prestige” offers a number of events which can be interpreted in more than one way. The last shot shows a room full of water tanks full of dead clones – or does it? We see that because we <em>want</em> to see it; we want to believe in the magic of Tesla’s invention, no matter how horrifying the potential consequences. The narrator, being Angier for the expositional sequence about Tesla’s machine, may or may not be telling the truth – he is, after all, a magician who would hide his secrets from everyone including the invisible audience. If there is only one body, it could easily have been Angier’s double. We could puzzle over this at length, which gives us a sense of unsettling non-completion.</p>

<p>Perhaps in a “search for more money” (as a certain purveyor of The Schwartz had been known to say), prequels and origin stories for most major film universes have been veritably exploding into existence. <em>(For the sake of some form of brevity, I’m leaving out film reboots and re-imaginings.)</em> The question which should be asked about these expansions and attempts to bring about some form of epistemic closure should not be “is it good?” but rather “is it necessary or right?”</p>

<p>Sometimes prequel films end up completely destroying a venerable mythology (Star Wars Episodes 1-3), and sometimes prequel works add backstory which is more or less completely unnecessary for the comprehension of a character (the “Gotham” and “Hannibal” television series, for example). I posit that incomplete epistemology inherent in film universes provides a tension which underscores certain themes, and this tension and uncertainty dissolves as soon as every important mystery is taken away by subsequent works. You have to know when to explain and when not to explain.</p>

<h2 id="layered-realities-in-film">Layered realities in film</h2>

<p>A popular motif in film has been the story within a story – from <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0015324/">Sherlock Jr</a>’s cameraman dreaming in the booth to Inception’s dreams within dreams, and many more in between. My supposition is that the popularity of this motif, which stems from sentiments like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All the world’s a stage, and all the men and women merely players - “As You Like It”, William Shakespeare</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are many transpositions of external epistemological ideas in non-“story within a story” contexts as well. Examples of this are films like David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0166924/">Mulholland Drive</a>, which uses knowledge about the internal workings of Hollywood to inform and shape the story.</p>

<p>A combination of those methods for transposing epistemology into film are also possible; Inception not only has dreams within dreams, but also has characters who <a href="http://www.theawl.com/2010/07/the-key-to-inception-its-a-movie-about-making-movies">mirror the jobs of the people who make film</a>. David Mamet’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120202/">State and Main</a> tells a story-within-a-story (the film which is being made), but also pulls from the reality of filmmaking and Hollywood politics.</p>

<p>One of my favorite auteurs in the realm of mixing epistemologies and conflating fantasy with reality is Terry Gilliam. As an example, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096764/">The Adventures of Baron Munchausen</a> has a series of overlapping and interweaving stories within stories. The Baron’s life and adventures (which may be pure fantasy, and almost surely represent fantasy and imagination in the context of the larger story) are presented as a matter-of-fact stage play which is being used as a diversion from a larger, terrible reality. As the film progresses, we begin to descend into layers of transitions between what we believe is the “real world” of the film and stories-within-stories. The transitions between them are usually not the typical dream sequence transitions; one of the most genius transitions in the film occurs when the Baron begins narrating his own life, and the stage actor playing the Sultan is pushed out onto the stage, to discover that it is no longer the stage, but rather the Sultan’s palace. Gilliam doesn’t really want there to be a solid delineation between reality and imagination, and it shows. By the end of the film, we’re aware that (at least, within the confines of the film’s epistemology) some of the stories must have been somewhat real, but we don’t know which ones or how much of them. Gilliam denies us epistemological closure, and it does not detract from the film – quite the opposite – it defines the nature of the film.</p>

<h2 id="documentary-and-narrative-fallacies-and-truths">Documentary and narrative fallacies and truths</h2>

<p>Documentary filmmaking is another odd case ; it presents itself as a sort of objective narrative truth, whereas in reality documentarians rely on their own subjective narrative truths and fallacies to underscore themes which they believe to be present in reality. The power of documentary film comes from its ability to expose an external epistemology in the guise of objective observation. The majority of documentary films also possess the omnipresent narrator, using him/her as the lens with which to see the universe of the film – but that universe is <em>our</em> universe.</p>

<p>Rather than creating an artificial world and filling it with narrative and knowledge, documentarians use the real world as the substrate to build their own artificial world, but sell it back to us as being the “real world”. It’s much easier to consume documentary film works when we are aware that they are someone’s subjective view of reality, with all of the epistemological baggage that carries.</p>

<h2 id="the-big-lie">The Big Lie</h2>

<p>The Big Lie is that it’s all fake; documentaries and flights of fantasy alike.</p>

<p>We enter into an unspoken and unwritten agreement with the filmmakers to suspend our ability to differentiate the 24 still frames flying past our eyes as individual discrete images, and instead peek into another world with its own laws, knowledge, and history. We all know, somewhere inside us, that it’s all a Big Lie, but we agree to leave our sense of reality, suspend our disbelief, and share in a small piece of something unlike what we’re used to seeing.</p>

<p>The problems with ignoring the separate epistemology of a film is that it can limit our ability to enjoy that film by removing lingering doubts or questions, or possibly coming a little too close or far away from what we understand to be reasonable deviations from our own local experiences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fine Line Between Confidence and Hubris]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T15:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to make sense of two necessarily contrary positions in regard to skill, art, and aesthetics. This is something of which I’ve been trying to make sense for quite some time.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="aesthetics-technique-and-intent">Aesthetics, Technique, and Intent</h2>

<p>The fundamental balance of aesthetics in any art-form is, in my supposition, the balance between the personal sense and the general public sense. This is somewhat necessitated by a very strange mechanism – that of our inherent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">inability to accurately self-assess</a> our own skills and works. I would secondarily posit that art is effectively a combination of <strong>technique</strong> (skill) and <strong>intent</strong>. (Some have additionally added <strong>context</strong> to that, but I’m going to put that aside as an adjunct of intent for now.)</p>

<p>Technique is teachable. Technique is learnable (depending on the amount of time put in, internal aptitudes, etc). Technique is something which, to one degree or another, is somewhat quantifiable. A great deal of education in the arts is devoted to attempting to teach classical techniques, if only for the sake of eventually learning which ones can be accepted and which ones can be disregarded.</p>

<p>Intent, on the other hand, is a really hairy beast. It is <strong>not</strong> able to be deterministically divined from a work in a vacuum. Even more frustrating is that it can be broken into <strong>perceived intent</strong> (how we internalize what we’ve seen, heard, and experienced), and <strong>original intent</strong> (how the artist actually originally intended the art to be consumed). But wait – the original intent can further be broken into <strong>original intent</strong> and <strong>revisionist intent</strong>, where the artist retro-fits an original intent onto a piece for one reason or another – even though it was not originally present in the design and execution phases. (My personal belief is that this is done primary for reasons dealing with popularity, but I don’t have any data to back this up.)</p>

<p>If art is a combination of these two things, how can art be “judged” by others if the original artist’s intent cannot be accurately determined? Should it be consumed and rated based on the perceived intent, which is completely subjective based on the person consuming it?</p>

<h2 id="coming-back-to-confidence-and-hubris">Coming back to Confidence and Hubris</h2>

<p>The next logical question in the context of this reading would be “what does this have to do with the difference between confidence and hubris?”</p>

<p>Confidence is somewhat necessary in the artistic process, as it helps shape the intent of the work. If we have no belief or confidence in what we are doing, it is very difficult to move forward with doing it.</p>

<p>Technique, however, requires a certain amount of humble nature to learn and master. If we believe that we have nothing else to learn, we stop learning. As the source material from Dunning-Kruger concludes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the miscalibration of the incompetent stems from an error about the self, whereas the miscalibration of the highly competent stems from an error about others</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, hubris is a base requirement for successful intent, as we need to believe that what we are doing has some sort of artistic merit, both to ourselves and for the external validation provided by others. We would need to be able to weather the concerns of others to forge our own artistic path.</p>

<p>But technique requires a humility which contradicts that hubris, for if we do not know our place in the grand spectrum of abilities, how can we ever hope to know when we can improve, or how to improve?</p>

<h2 id="societal-homogenization">Societal Homogenization</h2>

<p>To a degree, all artists who come in contact with other art or other artists will experience a level of homogenization of their work. The Millenial generation, replete with Instagram pictures, <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/doge">Doge-level memes</a>, and an inflated sense of self (unencumbered by a history of perceived failures) seem to experience this effect at a greater magnitude than seen before. I’m not sure if this is due to the replicating effect of social networking, an increased population size (similar to the compounding effect of scientific discoveries with larger populations), or some other ancillary effect with which I’m unfamiliar.</p>

<p>I mention societal homogenization of art-forms because it leads me to the next question…</p>

<h2 id="is-it-me-or-is-it-the-world">Is it me, or is it the world?</h2>

<p>The question that I ask is “Is it me, or is it the world?”</p>

<p>If my aesthetic is different than the vast popular aesthetic, am I wrong, or does society at large just have bad taste? I can’t answer that question. If aesthetics are the domain of popular opinion, I’m wrong, and confidence needs to be cut back in favor of humility and a level of homogenization. If original intent is the important part of the equation, I should be forging ahead, allowing confidence (and eventually hubris) to shape the end-products of artistic labor.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do">What do you do?</h2>

<p>I’ve struggled with this – and due to the paradoxical nature of the problem, the only solution I can offer is to make the decision about how to proceed with your art based on <em>your</em> intent. If you’re trying to make a living from your art, primarily, go for the homogenization – you will see better returns from a more commercially viable product. If you’re trying to make “better art”, go your own way – either you will create something which will transcend you or you won’t, but at least you will have made art which is yours.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
