<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: film theory | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/film-theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-02T18:31:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Narrative Exposition in Film]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/02/narrative-exposition-in-film/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-02T18:30:19-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/02/narrative-exposition-in-film</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Narrative exposition</strong>, or simply <strong>exposition</strong>, is the insertion of important background information within a story; for example, information about the setting, characters’ back-stories, prior plot events, historical context, etc. (from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exposition_%28narrative%29">Wikipedia</a>)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Within the confines of the skeleton of a film work (the script), there are many ways to impart information which would not otherwise be assumed by the viewer or implied by the filmmaker. I posit that the way in which expository information is imparted to a viewer via the medium of film is as important <em>if not more important</em> than the information which is being imparted.</p>

<p>As with any other aspect of film as an art form and medium, there isn’t a single “correct” way of doing anything. There isn’t one particular correct framing which needs to be used for a shot, not only a single focal length lens or camera brand which would have to be used to get the only valid shot possible – and in much the same vein, there are many different more-or-less-equally-correct methods of imparting that information. I’d like to explore the mechanisms and caveats of each of them.</p>

<h2 id="objectivity-and-subjectivity">Objectivity and Subjectivity</h2>

<p>It’s an interesting concept – there is no real delineation between objectivity and subjectivity as far as narration goes, if we consider that any narration is part of the <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">artificially separate epistemic system of a film</a>, and therefore could have a level of objectivity or subjectivity within the confines of a certain character, but which presents the same objective face to the viewing audience as a whole (in that they all will see the same footage), which will be subjectively interpreted by each viewer (since even though they physically see the same footage, each person subjectively interprets what they see differently).</p>

<p>If we view the epistemology of the film as a system which we mentally “enter” during the course of film viewing, we can attempt to assign a level of subjectivity or objectivity <em>within those parameters</em> to determine how objective exposition appears to be <em>within that system</em>. This is the virtual vantage point which I will be using during the remainder of my analysis of different forms of exposition, so as not to overly confuse the concepts.</p>

<h2 id="narrative-exposition--through-narration">Narrative exposition … through narration</h2>

<p>One of the most popular methods for imparting information to the audience of a film (or other visual work) is by simply having either a character (through a monologue or soliloquy) tell the audience the pieces of the story or other details which the auteurs wish to impart, directly speak to the audience through a voiceover, or espouse the information through a conversation between characters – or even a character who exists <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MrExposition">only to spout expository information</a>. </p>

<p>Out of all of these methodologies, I tend to look down on voiceover narration as the most egregious, because it comes across as an indicator of either laziness or over-complexity, as the auteurs did not believe that the information could be imparted in any way <em>other than essentially having the film universe speak through a disembodied voice directly to the viewer</em>, even if it comes by way of a character. (I make the distinction between a voiceover of a diary being written or read and this type of narration, simply because a diary-type voiceover would otherwise fall under being categorized as a soliloquy.)</p>

<h2 id="captioncrawl-exposition">Caption/crawl exposition</h2>

<p>Popularized in modern cinema by George Lucas’s Star Wars intro crawl but dating back to silent movie title cards, crawl exposition is more or less a written form of voiceover narration, presented in a slightly varied form. It could be argued that caption/crawl titles actually present a perceptually higher level of objectivity to the viewer, as they speak with an omniscient deity-like authority rather than speaking through an anonymous narrator or using a character as a puppet of sorts.</p>

<h2 id="mise-en-scne-exposition">Mise-en-scène exposition</h2>

<p>This is where my cinematography sensibilities come in. There are many methods of using the camera as a virtual narrator, and it is a very powerful tool to use, since the camera’s recorded mise-en-scène is the lens by which the viewer perceives the whole of the film universe. This gives the filmmaker great latitude in deciding how much or how little information can be imparted from the framing and composition alone, before the actors’ dialogue or motions are considered at all.</p>

<p>Some even consider the camera to be its own character, and though this is fairly specific to directors and cinematographers, being</p>

<p>In the interests of space and time, I’ll just briefly overview some of the more successful methods.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Frame Composition</strong>. I’ll refer to <a href="https://vimeo.com/118078262">Tony Zhou’s breakdown of Kurosawa’s The Bad Sleep Well</a> for a more in-depth analysis of how the way elements dance in and out of frame and are arranged <em>in a single shot</em> can tell us more about the characters than pages of dialogue or a flurry of quick cuts.</li>
  <li><a href="http://acephalous.typepad.com/acephalous/2011/01/fight-club.html">Frontality</a>. The way a character can be looking directly at the viewer (although, to be fair, we only <em>perceive</em> that they’re looking directly at us, and for the most part, the camera is taking the place of another character) can subconsciously impart a wealth of information. It allows us to put ourselves in the place of one of the characters, and the way we perceive them can shift.  </li>
  <li><strong>Lighting</strong>. Even though particular film idioms like film noir are specifically known for using lighting for exposition, neo-noir films have brought this technique back into the mainstream. Using visual idioms like casting bars of shadow across a character’s face to indicate that they feel trapped or cornered, for example.</li>
  <li><strong>Objectivity/Subjectivity</strong> can be implied by the type of shot used, and even the level of stabilization employed. If we need to get into a character’s head to imply thought, many cinematographers have used dolly-in closeup shots to imply figuratively going into the character’s head (or in the case of the intro to <strong>Fight Club</strong>, literally coming out of it).</li>
  <li><strong>3D Forced Perspective</strong>. I don’t particularly like “3D” films, especially as they generally come off like large pop-up books to me, but the ability to force certain objects to be more apparent, and therefore more important, by using 3D manipulation is another fairly effective tool. If a sword appears to be a few inches from your nose in a movie theater, you’re going to be paying attention to it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="holistic-exposition">Holistic exposition</h2>

<p>Holistic exposition is the dissemination of information through observed character movements, actions, and observed and inferred intents. An auteur can impart vast amounts of information through the situations and non-discrete expositional phrasing. (I make the distinction between “holistic exposition” and “mise-en-scène exposition”, even though the latter is a subset of the former, for the sake of dividing between camera-based exposition and all other types of holistic exposition.)</p>

<p>For example, if a character is lonely, the character does not have to state “I am lonely” for the viewer to understand the character’s loneliness. It is just as effective, if not more so, to allow situations to unfold where the character is allowed to <em>imply</em> that same loneliness by actions, or even in non-explicit dialogue.</p>

<p>There are a number of caveats to holistic exposition.</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Intellectual Laziness</em>. There’s a certain percentage of any viewing demographic that does not want to have to <em>think</em> about how information is presented – they just want the characters to come out and say whatever they’re thinking.</li>
  <li><em>Ambiguity</em> can be introduced unintentionally if there is more than one potential cause or source for the holistic expositional element. Is the character picking up a knife because they’re scared, hungry, or angry?</li>
  <li><em>Actors</em> make or break this style of exposition. If the actors lack subtlety or under- (or over-) act their part, it can destroy carefully planned exposition.</li>
  <li><em>Planning</em>. It requires much more subtlety to reveal information through holistic means than to simply tell the viewer what you want them to know, which requires a greater level of planning from the writing on down to the director in the chain of auteurship.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="respecting-holistic-epistemology-or-only-tell-what-you-need-to-survive">Respecting holistic epistemology (or “Only tell what you need to survive”)</h2>

<p>Not everything has to be explicitly told or known for a story or universe to be complete. As I had mentioned in my first piece of film epistemology, epistemic closure isn’t a necessary thing; the lack of it can has the ability to change the perception of a film by the viewers.</p>

<p>It should be noted that some of the wave of independent filmmakers starting in the 1990s seemed to rely on over-telling stories by introducing potentially irrelevant information to the plot through over-loquacious characters who buried their narrative exposition in paragraphs of misleading dialogue. Kevin Smith and Quentin Tarantino are two examples of this school of narrative over-exposition, but there have been many who have attempted the same techniques with varying levels of success. (It takes a certain level of craft to create dialogue which works this way but does not come off as cloyingly banal or irritatingly uninteresting.)</p>

<h2 id="dark-city-an-exercise-in-comparison">“Dark City”, an exercise in comparison</h2>

<p>Alex Proyas’ gothic neo-noir/horror/sci-fi classic <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0118929/">Dark City</a> offers a very apparent dichotomic illustration of the differences in narrative exposition choices. The theatrical cut begins with a paragraph of indulgent voice-over narration provided by Kiefer Sutherland’s character (spoilers, of course):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>First, there was darkness. Then came the Strangers. They were a race as old as time itself. They had mastered the ultimate technology – ability to alter physical reality by will alone. They called this ability “Tuning.” But they were dying. Their civilization was in decline, and so they abandoned their world, seeking a cure for their own mortality. Their endless journey brought them to a small, blue world… in the farthest corner of the galaxy. Our world. Here, they thought they had finally found… what they had been searching for. My name is Dr. Daniel Poe Schreber. I am just a man. I help the Strangers conduct their experiments. I have betrayed my own kind. <em>(courtesy of <a href="http://www.script-o-rama.com/movie_scripts/d/dark-city-script-transcript-proyas.html">script-o-rama</a>)</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The narration sets up the basics of the plot, and now the viewer knows far more than any of the principal characters other than <em>Dr. Shreber</em>. The other principals spend the majority (at least two thirds) of the film coming up to speed with this information, while we watch along – textbook objective viewing.</p>

<p>The director’s cut, however cuts out the narration entirely, as well as extending some scenes to add additional dialogue and action to help round out certain parts of the plot. The major change which this has on the perceptual quality of the film is that we don’t know what the characters know (unknown knowns), and we don’t know what the characters don’t know (unknown unknowns). This, at least in theory, gives us greater subjectivity in our relationship to the perceptions and situations of the principal characters. <em>We don’t even know the name for the villains until the third act.</em> It also creates the potential for a fair amount of confusion in the first act, as we don’t know <em>anything</em> outside of what we holistically learn – John Murdock wakes up in a bathtub near a corpse, and someone is chasing him.</p>

<p>I found that while viewing the director’s cut of Dark City, the “larger truth” (or the “bigger lie”, depending on your perception) behind the city seemed to come as more of a revelation. I say “seemed to come” as I’m incapable of watching a second version of the film in a totally objective light ; my context has been clouded by my previous viewings. For example, it’s less noticeable that there is never any sunlight, as the characters seem blissfully unaware of that detail.  </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Epistemology]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T12:08:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to take a brief look at film epistemology. In order for that to work, I’m going to be positing that for our purposes, each film is its own self-contained universe with its own rules and knowledge both known and unknown.</p>

<p><em>(As a disclaimer, I’m no Scott Eric Kaufmann; I’m not going to be using visual illustrations, and precious few (if any) citations. There are also bound to be spoilers of every variety, so if a film is mentioned, avert your gaze if you don’t want to learn important truths about its ending.)</em></p>

<h2 id="film-as-philosophy-and-self-contained-world">Film as philosophy and self contained world</h2>

<p>As I’ve just mentioned, a singular film can be seen as its own self-contained universe – a universe populated with rules and knowledge which are specific to that universe. Sometimes that world looks much like our own and shares many similar traits, sometimes it shares many visual similarities but a different history, and sometimes it bears little resemblance to the world and universe we know and try to understand.</p>

<p>The important similarity is that there’s a philosophical system underlying each of these film universes, built on the philosophies and mores of the auteurs of each film (writer, director, et al). Some popular films and film franchises have generated series of philosophical works – Star Wars, in particular, comes to mind – as well as compendiums of knowledge and in-universe canon of all varieties. Within the confines of these films, the epistemology has been grown in such a way as to allow a more immersive universe (according to the optimist), and/or wring more money from dedicated fans (according to the pessimist).</p>

<p>One of the things that has tended to irritate my own film sensibilities have been when films violate their own rules. Film is a suspension of disbelief, but there are certain rules explicitly or implicitly set out during the course of the film, which define the epistemology in which I have to be immersed while watching. A film shouldn’t violate its own rules, otherwise I end up setting aside my suspension of disbelief and become very aware that I’m watching a film.</p>

<p>To elaborate, I quote <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/WillingSuspensionOfDisbelief">TV Tropes’ excellent page on this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Any creative endeavor, certainly any written creative endeavor, is only successful to the extent that the audience offers this willing suspension as they read, listen, or watch. It’s part of an unspoken contract: The writer provides the reader/viewer/player with a good story, and in return, they accept the reality of the story as presented, and accept that characters in the fictional universe act on their own accord.
An author’s work, in other words, does not have to be realistic, only believable and internally consistent (see <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MagicAIsMagicA">Magic A Is Magic A</a>). When the author pushes an audience beyond what they’re willing to accept, the work fails in the eyes of that particular audience. As far as science fiction is concerned, viewers are usually willing to go along with <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TechnoBabble">creative explanations</a> which is why <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/PhysicsGoof">people don’t criticize your wormhole travel system</a> or <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AppliedPhlebotinum">how a shrinking potion doesn’t violate the laws of matter conservation</a>, but even in the more fantastical genres, suspension of disbelief can be broken when a work breaks its own established laws or asks the audience to put up with too many things that come off as contrived.
A common way of putting this is “You can ask an audience to believe the impossible, but not the improbable.” For example, people will accept that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AWizardDidIt">the Grand Mage can teleport across the world</a>, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/StealthInSpace">the spaceship has technology that makes it completely invisible</a> without rendering its own sensors blind, but they won’t accept that the ferocious carnivore <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AssPull">just happened to have a heart attack and die</a> right before it attacked the main character, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/HollywoodHacking">the hacker guessed his enemy’s password on the first try just by typing random letters</a>, at least without <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/JustifiedTrope">some prior detail justifying it</a> or one of the Rules listed below coming into play. What is in <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/RealLife">Real Life</a> impossible just has to be made the norm in the setting and kept consistent.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="epistemological-overlap-and-suspension-of-disbelief">Epistemological overlap and suspension of disbelief</h2>

<p>As much as there is a suspension of disbelief inherent in any viewing of film (it is, after all, a series of quickly presented still frames in an artificial viewing environment), we require a certain epistemological overlap with our own universe / reality.</p>

<p>There is a certain range of deviation from reality which is acceptable in the majority of film. I believe this is because film has to balance a sense of relatability, which is produced by overlapping epistemology with reality, with its own deviations and rules. If a film is <em>too close</em> to reality without matching it exactly, we end up encountering something similar to the “<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mori_Uncanny_Valley.svg">uncanny valley</a>”, where we become disenfranchised from the reality with which we are presented because it becomes very clear to us that it isn’t real, and suspension of disbelief falls apart.</p>

<p>I believe that resources like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/CinemaSins">CinemaSins</a> are a combination of relevance and irrelevance. In regards to that resource in particular, it shows irrelevance when it posits that film should obey all of the rules of the real world in most of its critiques, but shows relevance when it acknowledges a film’s epistemological separateness and shows how that film breaks its own rules.</p>

<h2 id="narrator-as-deity--narrator-as-liar">Narrator as deity / narrator as liar</h2>

<p>Many films employ an explicit narrator, whether by title scroll (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0076759/">Star Wars: A New Hope</a>), voice-over (Princess Irulan and Paul Atreides’ voiceovers in David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0087182/">Dune</a>), by a narrator telling an inner story (Verbal Kint in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114814/">The Usual Suspects</a>), by physically narrating a written inner story (The Grandfather in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779/">The Princess Bride</a>), or even a character’s internal soliloquy (the narrator in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0137523/">Fight Club</a>). This is generally done to augment what could otherwise be clumsy and/or ineffectual exposition through other means in the film – or even to give a certain amount of backstory in order to produce enough in-universe knowledge to allow viewers to be sufficiently immersed in the universe which they are presented.</p>

<p>The narrator has a particular type of power and hold over the viewer ; they are the lens with which the fabricated universe of the film is viewed. Even though we are presented with visual and auditory information through picture and sound, the narrator is the <strong>voice of god</strong> (or at least some sort of prophetic voice, if we’re going with the religious metaphor) as far as this universe is concerned. But what if this omnipresent narrator isn’t telling the truth about this universe?</p>

<p>Two extremely visible cases of this occur in David Fincher’s “Fight Club” and Bryan Singer’s “The Usual Suspects”.</p>

<p>In “Fight Club”, we’re led down a paraprosdokian storyline by a nameless author, who not only tells us a story in his droning monotone, but also shows us his misadventures with a character we know as Tyler Durden. Only at the end of the second act do we learn that our author has been lying to us, much as he has been lying to himself. What we have seen as a fully realistic and discernibly physical part of this universe is a figment of the narrator’s imagination. We’re forced to change our view of this film universe as part of an unsettling experience which helps define a major part of the attraction to that film.</p>

<p>In “The Usual Suspects”, we confront a similar situation – except that the narrator (Verbal Kint) is very much aware that he’s misleading both us and Agent Kujan. Our realization comes right after the perceived climax of the film, as Verbal allows Agent Kujan to apparently convince both himself and the audience that the elusive Keyser Soze is really Dean Keaton. Mere moments later, Kujan comes to the realization at which we are meant to arrive ; he has been lied to. This is shocking to the audience because we implicitly trust the narrator to guide us to the truths of the film universe which he inhabits, yet he betrays us, breaking our knowledge of his universe. Even more troubling is that we’re not sure how much of the last few hours has been real (according to the film universe), and how much was made up by the narrator. A false world, inhabited by a virtual deity who hides the nature of that false world with yet another representation.</p>

<p>Yet another power that on-screen narration (in particular) has is that it can provide the film equivalent to the literary “aside” or footnote. Groucho Marx was known for pioneering this form of soliloquy, which came to be known colloquially as “breaking the fourth wall”. It allows the author to speak through his/her characters directly to the audience without the need for voiceover – but it shows the universe <em>stop</em> around the narrator. What they’re saying is so important that their universe <em>literally stops</em> so that you, the captive audience, can bear witness to it. In Woody Allen’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0075686/">Annie Hall</a>, the narrator’s diatribe (aimed directly at the viewing audience, in spite of the people around him) appears to be breaking the fourth wall – but the subject of his anger is revealed to be able to actually <em>hear what he is saying</em>, in contravention of Groucho Marx’s tradition of film asides. Allen then proceeds to almost literally pull a rabbit out of a hat by magically pulling Marshall McLuhan seemingly out of thin air to make his point for him, then resumes his narrative aside. To Allen, the narrative aside is just another platform on which to base a joke, but it speaks to the unspoken acknowledgement that the narrator is aware at some level that he is part of a film universe; he just bends the rules a little. </p>

<h2 id="epistemic-closure-vs-incomplete-epistemology">Epistemic closure vs incomplete epistemology</h2>

<p>Another supposition I’d like to put forward is that epistemic closure in a film universe essentially eliminates a very specific source of tension. “Settling films” (films which leave the viewer with a feeling of completion) tend not to leave unanswered questions, and if it does leave unanswered questions, they’re generally fairly benign or immaterial to substantial portions of the central plot.</p>

<p>On the other hand, we can look at some of the films of Christopher Nolan as examples of intentionally incomplete epistemology. A number of his films employ missing information or information which can be interpreted in a number of different ways to provide differing conclusions or philosophies to his films.</p>

<p>“Inception”, for example, famously ends with a shot of a spinning top which either will or will not fall down to indicate whether the principal character is trapped within a never-ending dream. Depending on whether you believe that he is awake or asleep, it changes the interpretation of the ending. (Nolan had actually said that fixating on the top essentially missed the point of the ending, as Cobb is happy, which is the important part of the conclusion.)</p>

<p>“The Prestige” offers a number of events which can be interpreted in more than one way. The last shot shows a room full of water tanks full of dead clones – or does it? We see that because we <em>want</em> to see it; we want to believe in the magic of Tesla’s invention, no matter how horrifying the potential consequences. The narrator, being Angier for the expositional sequence about Tesla’s machine, may or may not be telling the truth – he is, after all, a magician who would hide his secrets from everyone including the invisible audience. If there is only one body, it could easily have been Angier’s double. We could puzzle over this at length, which gives us a sense of unsettling non-completion.</p>

<p>Perhaps in a “search for more money” (as a certain purveyor of The Schwartz had been known to say), prequels and origin stories for most major film universes have been veritably exploding into existence. <em>(For the sake of some form of brevity, I’m leaving out film reboots and re-imaginings.)</em> The question which should be asked about these expansions and attempts to bring about some form of epistemic closure should not be “is it good?” but rather “is it necessary or right?”</p>

<p>Sometimes prequel films end up completely destroying a venerable mythology (Star Wars Episodes 1-3), and sometimes prequel works add backstory which is more or less completely unnecessary for the comprehension of a character (the “Gotham” and “Hannibal” television series, for example). I posit that incomplete epistemology inherent in film universes provides a tension which underscores certain themes, and this tension and uncertainty dissolves as soon as every important mystery is taken away by subsequent works. You have to know when to explain and when not to explain.</p>

<h2 id="layered-realities-in-film">Layered realities in film</h2>

<p>A popular motif in film has been the story within a story – from <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0015324/">Sherlock Jr</a>’s cameraman dreaming in the booth to Inception’s dreams within dreams, and many more in between. My supposition is that the popularity of this motif, which stems from sentiments like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All the world’s a stage, and all the men and women merely players - “As You Like It”, William Shakespeare</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are many transpositions of external epistemological ideas in non-“story within a story” contexts as well. Examples of this are films like David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0166924/">Mulholland Drive</a>, which uses knowledge about the internal workings of Hollywood to inform and shape the story.</p>

<p>A combination of those methods for transposing epistemology into film are also possible; Inception not only has dreams within dreams, but also has characters who <a href="http://www.theawl.com/2010/07/the-key-to-inception-its-a-movie-about-making-movies">mirror the jobs of the people who make film</a>. David Mamet’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120202/">State and Main</a> tells a story-within-a-story (the film which is being made), but also pulls from the reality of filmmaking and Hollywood politics.</p>

<p>One of my favorite auteurs in the realm of mixing epistemologies and conflating fantasy with reality is Terry Gilliam. As an example, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096764/">The Adventures of Baron Munchausen</a> has a series of overlapping and interweaving stories within stories. The Baron’s life and adventures (which may be pure fantasy, and almost surely represent fantasy and imagination in the context of the larger story) are presented as a matter-of-fact stage play which is being used as a diversion from a larger, terrible reality. As the film progresses, we begin to descend into layers of transitions between what we believe is the “real world” of the film and stories-within-stories. The transitions between them are usually not the typical dream sequence transitions; one of the most genius transitions in the film occurs when the Baron begins narrating his own life, and the stage actor playing the Sultan is pushed out onto the stage, to discover that it is no longer the stage, but rather the Sultan’s palace. Gilliam doesn’t really want there to be a solid delineation between reality and imagination, and it shows. By the end of the film, we’re aware that (at least, within the confines of the film’s epistemology) some of the stories must have been somewhat real, but we don’t know which ones or how much of them. Gilliam denies us epistemological closure, and it does not detract from the film – quite the opposite – it defines the nature of the film.</p>

<h2 id="documentary-and-narrative-fallacies-and-truths">Documentary and narrative fallacies and truths</h2>

<p>Documentary filmmaking is another odd case ; it presents itself as a sort of objective narrative truth, whereas in reality documentarians rely on their own subjective narrative truths and fallacies to underscore themes which they believe to be present in reality. The power of documentary film comes from its ability to expose an external epistemology in the guise of objective observation. The majority of documentary films also possess the omnipresent narrator, using him/her as the lens with which to see the universe of the film – but that universe is <em>our</em> universe. </p>

<p>Rather than creating an artificial world and filling it with narrative and knowledge, documentarians use the real world as the substrate to build their own artificial world, but sell it back to us as being the “real world”. It’s much easier to consume documentary film works when we are aware that they are someone’s subjective view of reality, with all of the epistemological baggage that carries.</p>

<h2 id="the-big-lie">The Big Lie</h2>

<p>The Big Lie is that it’s all fake; documentaries and flights of fantasy alike.</p>

<p>We enter into an unspoken and unwritten agreement with the filmmakers to suspend our ability to differentiate the 24 still frames flying past our eyes as individual discrete images, and instead peek into another world with its own laws, knowledge, and history. We all know, somewhere inside us, that it’s all a Big Lie, but we agree to leave our sense of reality, suspend our disbelief, and share in a small piece of something unlike what we’re used to seeing.</p>

<p>The problems with ignoring the separate epistemology of a film is that it can limit our ability to enjoy that film by removing lingering doubts or questions, or possibly coming a little too close or far away from what we understand to be reasonable deviations from our own local experiences.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fine Line Between Confidence and Hubris]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T15:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to make sense of two necessarily contrary positions in regard to skill, art, and aesthetics. This is something of which I’ve been trying to make sense for quite some time.</p>

<h2 id="aesthetics-technique-and-intent">Aesthetics, Technique, and Intent</h2>

<p>The fundamental balance of aesthetics in any art-form is, in my supposition, the balance between the personal sense and the general public sense. This is somewhat necessitated by a very strange mechanism – that of our inherent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">inability to accurately self-assess</a> our own skills and works. I would secondarily posit that art is effectively a combination of <strong>technique</strong> (skill) and <strong>intent</strong>. (Some have additionally added <strong>context</strong> to that, but I’m going to put that aside as an adjunct of intent for now.)</p>

<p>Technique is teachable. Technique is learnable (depending on the amount of time put in, internal aptitudes, etc). Technique is something which, to one degree or another, is somewhat quantifiable. A great deal of education in the arts is devoted to attempting to teach classical techniques, if only for the sake of eventually learning which ones can be accepted and which ones can be disregarded.</p>

<p>Intent, on the other hand, is a really hairy beast. It is <strong>not</strong> able to be deterministically divined from a work in a vacuum. Even more frustrating is that it can be broken into <strong>perceived intent</strong> (how we internalize what we’ve seen, heard, and experienced), and <strong>original intent</strong> (how the artist actually originally intended the art to be consumed). But wait – the original intent can further be broken into <strong>original intent</strong> and <strong>revisionist intent</strong>, where the artist retro-fits an original intent onto a piece for one reason or another – even though it was not originally present in the design and execution phases. (My personal belief is that this is done primary for reasons dealing with popularity, but I don’t have any data to back this up.)</p>

<p>If art is a combination of these two things, how can art be “judged” by others if the original artist’s intent cannot be accurately determined? Should it be consumed and rated based on the perceived intent, which is completely subjective based on the person consuming it?</p>

<h2 id="coming-back-to-confidence-and-hubris">Coming back to Confidence and Hubris</h2>

<p>The next logical question in the context of this reading would be “what does this have to do with the difference between confidence and hubris?”</p>

<p>Confidence is somewhat necessary in the artistic process, as it helps shape the intent of the work. If we have no belief or confidence in what we are doing, it is very difficult to move forward with doing it.</p>

<p>Technique, however, requires a certain amount of humble nature to learn and master. If we believe that we have nothing else to learn, we stop learning. As the source material from Dunning-Kruger concludes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the miscalibration of the incompetent stems from an error about the self, whereas the miscalibration of the highly competent stems from an error about others</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, hubris is a base requirement for successful intent, as we need to believe that what we are doing has some sort of artistic merit, both to ourselves and for the external validation provided by others. We would need to be able to weather the concerns of others to forge our own artistic path.</p>

<p>But technique requires a humility which contradicts that hubris, for if we do not know our place in the grand spectrum of abilities, how can we ever hope to know when we can improve, or how to improve?</p>

<h2 id="societal-homogenization">Societal Homogenization</h2>

<p>To a degree, all artists who come in contact with other art or other artists will experience a level of homogenization of their work. The Millenial generation, replete with Instagram pictures, <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/doge">Doge-level memes</a>, and an inflated sense of self (unencumbered by a history of perceived failures) seem to experience this effect at a greater magnitude than seen before. I’m not sure if this is due to the replicating effect of social networking, an increased population size (similar to the compounding effect of scientific discoveries with larger populations), or some other ancillary effect with which I’m unfamiliar.</p>

<p>I mention societal homogenization of art-forms because it leads me to the next question…</p>

<h2 id="is-it-me-or-is-it-the-world">Is it me, or is it the world?</h2>

<p>The question that I ask is “Is it me, or is it the world?”</p>

<p>If my aesthetic is different than the vast popular aesthetic, am I wrong, or does society at large just have bad taste? I can’t answer that question. If aesthetics are the domain of popular opinion, I’m wrong, and confidence needs to be cut back in favor of humility and a level of homogenization. If original intent is the important part of the equation, I should be forging ahead, allowing confidence (and eventually hubris) to shape the end-products of artistic labor.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do">What do you do?</h2>

<p>I’ve struggled with this – and due to the paradoxical nature of the problem, the only solution I can offer is to make the decision about how to proceed with your art based on <em>your</em> intent. If you’re trying to make a living from your art, primarily, go for the homogenization – you will see better returns from a more commercially viable product. If you’re trying to make “better art”, go your own way – either you will create something which will transcend you or you won’t, but at least you will have made art which is yours.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
