<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[/home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-05T13:36:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winning a 48 Hour Film Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T15:37:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My team, <a href="http://www.shootthemoonfilms.com/">Shoot the Moon Films</a>, won the
2014 Providence Horror Film Project’s “Best Picture” award, as well as scoring
a “Best Actor” award for <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">Nicholas Magrey</a>, a “Best Writing” award for
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm5720821/">Natasha Darius</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">Nicholas Magrey</a>, and a “Best Sound Design” award for
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854894/">Aaron Theodore Berton</a> for our short film
“<a href="http://www.facebook.com/TheCarving">The Carving</a>” (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4131910/">IMDb</a>).</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/l4OQm1J0F0w "></iframe></div>

<p>I’m used to doing post-mortem analyses on failures, so this is a fairly
unusual task ; why did “The Carving” win against other films – especially
against some very strong contenders?</p>

<h2 id="its-all-about-the-story">It’s all about the story.</h2>

<p>As usual, we didn’t base our story off of any pre-existing concepts, scripts,
etc. Although it is expressly forbidden in the rules of the 48 hour film
projects, it is common knowledge that many teams engage in this practice,
presumably because of the difficulty of producing a good screenplay in the
alloted time.</p>

<p>I’m always proud of our writers, and this was no exception. When you’re
writing a story which has to come out as a four to seven minute short, you
can’t write an over-complicated concept, or take a half hour concept and
cut it down to a few minutes of film. We had used a fairly complicated
concept for our last 48 hour effort, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3713362/">Desire</a>,
and it did not fare very well.</p>

<p>It helps to have writers who know basic tenets of writing, and there are
a ton of online courses, books, and general help to improve scripts. Without
the screenwriters, we would not have won.</p>

<h2 id="sound-is-important-too">Sound is important, too.</h2>

<p>We spend an inordinate amount of post production time on ADR-ing, Foley-ing,
and otherwise enjoying the hard work of our sound engineer, which resulted
in the best <strong>sounding</strong> audio track of any of the films in the festival.
(Don’t take my word for it – it won an award specifically for that.)</p>

<p>Your boom operator has to be paying attention, and your audio setup has to
be… something. Don’t rely on a single source of audio, either. We had an
issue with a cable which resulted in having to use on-camera audio for a
closeup shot. This wouldn’t have been possible without a backup.</p>

<p>(It’s worth noting that in editing, I ended up doing as much audio replacement
as I could before handing off to our sound engineer, to cut down on the
amount of time which he’d have to burn finding the nicest audio for a certain
take.)</p>

<h2 id="take-footage-of-only-what-you-need-to-survive">Take (footage of) only what you need to survive.</h2>

<p>Overly fancy cinematography, while fun to execute (and great for winning
Cinematography awards), is nothing if it doesn’t help propel your story
forward. If you’re trying desperately to find a way to put a quadcopter
shot into your film, you may have lost already.</p>

<p>I’m a huge fan of indulgent, long, complicated shots – but they have to
fit your idiom. If you’re making a four to seven minute long short, you
probably shouldn’t do things just for the sake of doing them. A quick
example was that I had originally planned a jib/crane shot for a particular
piece of exposition, but ended up going with a snorricam rigged shot
instead. The snorricam doesn’t add as much “value” to the end product, but
it told the story <em>better</em>.</p>

<h2 id="on-the-other-hand-think-about-your-video-quality-a-bit">On the other hand, think about your video quality a bit.</h2>

<p>If you’re shooting on a handicam, why? Entry level DSLRs are cheap and
easy to come by, and with the right set of eyes behind the camera, they
can produce great footage.</p>

<p>If you’re not color correcting or grading your footage, why? The walls
behind your characters shouldn’t be changing between shots unless you
intend for them to be doing so. White balancing doesn’t cost any money.</p>

<p>If you’re not lighting your footage, why? A guy with a decent eye and
a few clamp lights can add immeasurable depth and character to your
shots. I know that “low light cinematography” is making the rounds as
the new fad, but you’re not going to get the same type of picture. It
doesn’t cost much (or anything if you already have the equipment at
home), so what’s the harm?</p>

<h2 id="if-you-cant-do-something-find-someone-who-can">If you can’t do something, find someone who can.</h2>

<p>Unless you’re a one person shop, consider finding other people to handle
tasks – especially if they’re better at something than you are. Get
someone with a good eye to handle the cinematography, someone who can
write well to pen your piece, and people who are good with audio to handle
your post production.</p>

<h2 id="dont-try-to-win-try-to-put-out-the-best-film-you-can">Don’t try to win, try to put out the best film you can.</h2>

<p>This is advice I had received right before the 48 started, and it’s some
of the best I’ve had. Because we specifically tried to make the best film
we could make in 48 hours (within the constraints outlined by the 48), we
have a film for our own promotion and uses after the festival ended.</p>

<p>Good luck to you in all of your cinematographic adventures!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another 48 Hours]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/10/19/another-48-hours/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-19T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/10/19/another-48-hours</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Almost six months after the Boston 48 Hour Film Festival, my team
(<a href="http://www.shootthemoonfilms.com/">Shoot the Moon Films</a>) is entering the
2014 <a href="http://www.48hourfilm.com/providence/horror/2014/">Providence 48 Hour Horror Festival</a>. Along
with seventeen other teams, we’re going to try to make a 4-7 minute
horror film in 48 hours.</p>

<p>This is pretty far out of my wheelhouse, as I haven’t made a practice of
making horror films, but my team and I are excited, and I’m going to keep
track of both our successes and our missteps here.</p>

<h2 id="day-one-preproduction-kickoff-and-writing">Day One: Preproduction, Kickoff, and Writing</h2>

<p>The one crazy moment I ended up having before everything got started was
the realization that I didn’t have enough space on the primary editing
workstation drive – and I ended up ameliorating that by purchasing another
drive down the road. Crisis averted, no hair lost.</p>

<p>I don’t like the roads around Providence, which proved to be a pain both
heading out to the kickoff event (horrific traffic and rubbernecking) as well
as on the way back (incorrect signage sending me to take a nasty U-turn in
Providence). As our producer couldn’t make the trip to the kickoff event,
I ended up taking his place.</p>

<p>After a two or three story jaunt up a staircase in a pretty non-descript
mill building in Pawtucket, I joined a group of mostly younger filmmakers,
eager to pick a category and get moving. As this was a “horror” themed
festival, we had a list of genres – and the writers had asked that I not
request one of the contingency genres, as they were more difficult to pull
off.</p>

<p>The guy standing behind me, after telling me how much he hated “Found Footage”
as a genre (which, by the way, I also loathe), ended up pulling that genre.
We ended up getting “Satanic/Demonic Possession”, and I messaged the
information back to the writers, so that they could get started on the
planning and writing process before I got back.</p>

<p>Both of the writers were coming from previous engagements, including one
who was starring in a theater production of “Frankenstein”, the other who
had costumed and was doing hair and prep work – but they still
managed to crank out the final version of a script before midnight. Everyone,
cast and crew, got sent copies.</p>

<p>From midnight until about 2:00 - 2:30 a.m., I wrote out a tentative shot list
and printed a huge piles of copies of the script. I got to sleep a little
before 3:00 a.m.</p>

<h2 id="day-two-production--shooting">Day Two: Production / Shooting</h2>

<p>At around 6:00 a.m., my wife and I got up, packed all of the equipment into
the car, and met the rest of the cast and crew at our shooting location at
7:00 a.m. We ended up having to scramble around to get all of the set
dressing components for the set, and got production underway around 10:30 -
11:00 a.m. Shooting with the BMPC4K camera made shooting, in most instances,
much faster since we could shoot in 4K and simply “punch in” for close up
shots without losing resolution. It was a neat trick which had been suggested
to me about two years ago by the director of “Chez Upshaw”, which a project
of mine had screened with at BIFF.</p>

<p>I got a chance to trot out a snorricam rig which hadn’t been used in almost
two years. It couldn’t handle the weight of the production camera, so we
were using a Blackmagic Pocket Cinema Camera with a modified Computar 12.5mm
f/1.3 lens stopped down to about f/4 to replace the GoPro Hero 2 we used to
use. The footage is nicely inter-cuttable with the Production Camera footage,
so I wouldn’t have to pull any rabbits out of hats in color grading.</p>

<p>We had a hard deadline for wrapping up principal photography of 5:30 p.m.,
since a number of actors and crew members had to make it back to the theater
for another performance of “Frankenstein” – including two of our actors,
our production designer <em>and</em> our makeup artist. We barely finished our last
take of our last outside shot as it started to rain heavily outside. No
equipment damaged, no shot missed.</p>

<p>We had to return props, and since my wife had taken the car, our producer
loaded up half of the equipment and my friend Chris helped me with the rest
of it, as well as helping me return some of our borrowed props. Another cup
of coffee later, and we were transferring about 280+ GB of footage off of the
two cameras and the boom rig.</p>

<p>One of the actors and the producer took turns sitting with me while I made
the bulk of the edits. We finished the rough cut at a little past 11:50 p.m.
The cast and crew members present watched the rough cut to confirm that there 
weren’t any glaring issues with the cut, then my wife and I went through all
of the audio to catalogue shot numbers and takes for easy sound replacement
referencing. I rendered out a reference copy for the musician doing the
scoring, uploaded it, and went to sleep before I passed out on my keyboard.</p>

<h2 id="day-three-post-production-and-making-the-deadline">Day Three: Post-production and Making the Deadline</h2>

<p>After a brief hour and a half or so of sleep, I ended up having to get up
to help my geriatric dog, who has periodic breathing issues. I got another
hour or so of sleep before my wife tossed me out of bed, and I stumbled down
the street to grab a cup of delicious Peruvian coffee to wake up. I’m pretty
sure my eyes weren’t open until half way back to the house.</p>

<p>From 6:30 a.m. until 10:30 a.m., I did the bulk of the sound replacement and
matching work as well as the coloring in Resolve. I dumped out an export for
Audition to take with me for ADR, and headed off to get the few lines that
we needed done.</p>

<p>Five actors met me over at our original shoot location, primarily so that my
dogs wouldn’t scuttle any of the takes. We wrapped sound collection around
1:30 p.m., and headed back to recomposite everything. I sent out the audio
to our audio engineer in Massachussetts, who recomposited everything together
and cleaned up some of our slightly dirtier boom audio, as well as leveling
out the speech. Final render time out of Premiere came right after that.</p>

<p>A last minute call to the hotline for the festival confirmed that we could
present HD 24 fps footage, rather than being limited to 30 fps footage (as
the website had indicated). A quick burn of a DVD and dropping footage on
a flash drive which felt <em>far</em> too large for the content we were putting on
it, and we were off to the races – so to speak.</p>

<p>We hauled the 45+ minute drive through Providence to the drop off point, and
were the first team in our group (the “B” group) to hand in our materials
40 minutes before the 7:30 p.m. drop-off deadline. Yahtzee!</p>

<h2 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Have an on-site audio engineer to take care of ADR duties.</strong> It’s a
serious pain to have to color <em>and</em> handle re-recording.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Get the cleanest boom audio possible.</strong> Make sure your boom operator is
getting pristine audio, as close as possible to the source, and monitoring
the levels.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make sure your audio is being catalogued on set.</strong> It was a serious time
waster to do this late at night, and put off coloring work until the next
day.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make sure someone is arranging rides.</strong> If someone needs to shuttle crew
around, make sure it’s not one of your department heads.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Screen your graded footage a few times before finalizing.</strong> I’m really
guilty of this one, as I noticed a few places where I needed to brighten
the midtones a bit, or match the color of the grass in some exterior shots
a bit better.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make sure to let everyone know how important they are.</strong> In a 48 hour
film festival, there are no “unimportant” people. Everyone is doing their
job, and without them, things wouldn’t come together properly. Our 1st AD
(who is, by trade, a stage manager) had never worked on a film set before
– but you’d never know it, since she brought her “A” game with her.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="special-thanks">Special Thanks</h2>

<p>I’d like to thank:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm5720821/">Natasha Darius</a></strong> – My
wife, co-writer, and general driving force behind everything I do. We
wouldn’t have done the 48 if it wasn’t for her talented writing and
creative spark, her tenacity in keeping everyone moving in the right
direction, and her infectious optimism. She was costuming and doing
actor prep for “Frankenstein” during this weekend, which made
everything else she was able to do (including prop shopping,
organization, writing, et cetera) that much more impressive.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">Nick Magrey</a></strong> –
Although he overbooks <em>everything</em> and wears far too
many hats, nothing would get done without him. Co-writing, acting,
production designing, wardrobe supervising… the list goes on and
on. Not to mention that he did this during the closing weekend of
his leading role in “Frankenstein” at the Bradley Playhouse.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm4840208/">Curtis Reid</a></strong> – I give
him a lot of crap about everything, but he’s the other half of the
organizational aspect of all of this, as well as running <strong>Shoot the
Moon Films</strong>. I like to tell people “you need to get a Curtis” when
they ask how I manage to get stuff done. I shouldn’t downplay his
acting, either – I just usually focus on all of his producing duties.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6562104/">Jon Demers</a></strong> – He kept me
awake, gopher’d the crap out of everything, drove me everywhere, 
<strong>and</strong> found time to act. Give that man a gold star.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854892/">Hannah Viens</a></strong> – 1st AD 
extraordinaire. She made sure that we were getting everything done,
and that’s no small task.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6562109/">Chelle Wright</a></strong> – Even
though she’s been doing MUA duties with us for a while, this was her
acting debut. Thank you for not only putting in a great performance,
but also for making everyone look so good!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Entire Verrill Clan</strong> – 
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm5220888/">Elizabeth</a> was acting and doing
sound work, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854893/">Patricia</a> was taking
still photos, and they were nice enough to lend their lovely home and
property to us to trash judiciously for filming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm4941340/">Maureen Vlaco</a></strong> – You have
one of the longest commutes to set, but you were cheery, helpful, and
even drove <em>back</em> for audio re-recording right before a funeral. You
brought that character to life – thank you!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854891/">Keith Murphy</a></strong> – I’ve never
worked with a stunt/fight guy before, but he was fantastic, in addition
to lending a double-popped-collar performance.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6562110/">Paul Magrey</a></strong> – Booming, as
well as helping with all sorts of other stuff on set. Awesome job!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong><a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6562108/">Brandi Demers</a></strong> – You’re my
right hand on set, and threw in a performance to boot, not to mention
the time you put in prepping props!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Our post-production crew</strong> – 
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854894/">Aaron</a> and
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6476893/">Garett</a>, especially. You guys
added so much production value with the precious little time we gave
you to work, and your work <em>completely</em> speaks for itself.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="screening">Screening</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4131910/">The Carving</a> is premiering on
<a href="http://horrorpvd-b.eventbrite.com/">October 29th in Providence at 9:00 p.m.</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ways To Keep Your Work From Appearing Cheap]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/09/19/ways-to-keep-your-work-from-appearing-cheap/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-19T15:16:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/09/19/ways-to-keep-your-work-from-appearing-cheap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay; so you’ve got a DSLR, a RED, a Blackmagic Cinema Camera, a GoPro – what’s
next? The internet is littered with all sorts of tutorials aimed at trying to
reproduce the “Hollywood look”, but where to begin?</p>

<p>Over my time as a cinematographer, I’ve learned quite a bit about putting
together things that don’t look terrible. Unfortunately, I’ve learned most of
these through the painful process of trial and error. If there’s an item listed
in this article, I most likely ended up screwing up in that particular way at
one time or another.</p>

<p><em>A slight disclaimer: I’m a bit of a purist. I tend not to deal with
post-production effects except when absolutely necessary. I also <strong>hate</strong>
camera shake, especially intentionally induced camera shake.</em></p>

<p>With that out of the way…</p>

<h2 id="audiophilia-dont-skimp-on-sound">1) Audiophilia: don’t skimp on sound.</h2>

<p>If your sound is terrible, your work is going to be perceived as terrible. It
doesn’t matter how artistic your shots are, how talented your actors, or how
legendary your vision. Audiences (and critics) can forgive almost anything, but
they cannot forgive terrible sound.</p>

<p>Sound makes up half of your deliverable work, so logically you should be
spending half your time working on it, but most of the indie productions I’ve
seen tend to ignore it as much as possible. Don’t skimp on a sound engineer;
if you manage to find a really good one, do <strong>not</strong> let them go.</p>

<p>Don’t let just anyone operate your boom mic. Make sure they are actually
interested in doing it. They should preferably be listening to every take and
making sure that you have good, usable audio.</p>

<p>If you really need to, get an ADR and Foley engineer. Or learn how to do it
yourself – just make sure that you give sound a reasonable amount of
attention.</p>

<h2 id="spastic-squirrel-syndrome-dont-cut-movies-like-youve-never-seen-a-movie">2) Spastic squirrel syndrome: don’t cut movies like you’ve never seen a movie.</h2>

<p>Editing is the “directorial discretion of last resort”. You can make all sorts
of changes in editing, including changing the entire mood of your film.</p>

<p>Don’t cut it like you’ve never seen a movie before. I need to reiterate that.
<strong>Don’t cut it like you’ve never seen a movie before.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Consider continuity</strong>. If one of your characters has a bag of chips in his hand
one moment and doesn’t the next, it’s possible that your discontinuous method
of cutting is making a statement about the transient nature of existence or the
fragile mental state of your protagonist – but it’s far more likely that the
person in charge of continuity fell asleep at the switch.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t cut movies like music videos</strong>. A new trend has emerged where music
video directors are being promoted to full length feature direction.
Unfortunately, their attention-deficit style of cutting has become the norm
for every type of film, even non-action ones. If you can’t keep your
audience’s attention unless you cut every 1.5 seconds, you might need to
work on your script or actors.</p>

<p><strong>Respect the 180 degree and 15 degree rules</strong>. If you don’t know what they
are, read a few articles on the basic rules of editing.</p>

<p><strong>Respect the pacing</strong> … or at least <em>consider</em> the pacing. I’ve changed
pacing in editing, but the resulting pace has to be considered before you
finalize an edit.</p>

<p><strong>Too many cooks spoil the soup</strong>. Or in this case, the film. Have one, maybe
two people at most editing your film. Everyone is going to have a different
idea of where it should go or how it should be cut together – do <strong>NOT</strong>
allow a crowd of people to make editing decisions. Especially if they aren’t
editors. (Actors can be the worst, as they tend to be concerned with how they
look on film, rather than the overall aesthetic.)</p>

<h2 id="read-the-script-make-sure-you-really-want-to-make-this-script">3) Read the script. Make sure you really want to make this script.</h2>

<p>Not every script should be made into a film. Some scripts barely have enough
content or action to cover a 10 minute short, let alone a 120 minute feature
film. Some scripts are just horribly written.</p>

<p>Think of the standard distribution curve; going by that, most scripts are
mediocre, some are terrible, some are good. You’re going to need to reject the
majority of material with which you are presented if you’re only going to make
the best scripts into films.</p>

<p>Find an uninterested party (not your close friends, family, or actors who would
be potentially involved in the production of it) and describe the plot. If it
doesn’t interest them, there’s a very good chance that you may not have a wider
audience appeal than your group of friends and family.</p>

<p>I should point out, at this part of this article, that not everyone makes films
for mass audience appeal. If you don’t, don’t worry about it. Find someone who
specializes in the niche you’re targeting, and ask them for their opinion. It
could save you quite a few weeks/months/years on a real turkey of a project.</p>

<h2 id="good-actors-are-not-easy-to-come-by-make-sure-you-find-them">4) Good actors are not easy to come by. Make sure you find them.</h2>

<p>Actors’ skill levels also follow the standard distribution curve. Be picky about
working with them, if at all possible.</p>

<p>Actors have the very unique ability to completely ruin a scene if even one of
them is out of character or “off their game”. Even non-speaking background roles
can break the illusion that is your film, so try to be selective in choosing
actors. Unless you need a character with a flat affect, don’t use an actor who
can’t produce anything other than that affect.</p>

<p>Make sure your actors get a chance to run their lines together and “block”
scenes before the day when their scenes are shot. Most actors tend to produce
better group dynamics when they’ve had a chance to prepare their material
(which is one of the reasons why the \ater actors prepare so far in advance and
practice together).</p>

<p>Speaking of theater actors – they’re a great source for acting talent. Most
communities have community theaters, and they are usually stocked with a wide
variety of talented characters actors. There are some differences between film
and theater work, but their “acting chops” are worth the extra work that needs
to be put in.</p>

<h2 id="do-not-rely-on-inserts-for-the-bulk-of-your-movie">5) Do not rely on inserts for the bulk of your movie.</h2>

<p>There’s nothing wrong with insert shots; they tend to add a bit of spice and
variety, as well as giving your editor something to cut away to if there’s some
continuity issue between takes.</p>

<p>Do <strong>not</strong> rely on them for a majority of your film. They tend not to tell much
of a story, and overuse not only gives a feeling of claustrophobia, but is one
of the telltale signs of low-budget indie films.</p>

<p>Like many other suggestions I’ve made here, this isn’t an ironclad rule. There
are many art films which make extensive use of insert shots to tell a story in
a particular way.</p>

<h2 id="there-is-a-setting-on-your-lenses-other-than-wide-open">6) There is a setting on your lenses other than “wide open”.</h2>

<p>Ever since “bokeh” made its first appearance in the photographer/cinematographer
lexicon, there has been a proliferation of extensively thin DOF shots. These can
be used to great artistic effect, and can produce beautiful images – but, much
like other tools in a cinematographer’s toolbox, it shouldn’t be the only tool
you use. All of your characters should generally be in focus when they’re having
a conversation in most circumstances. Constantly focus-pulling between two
characters because you have a tissue-thin DOF tends to give off the impression
that you have no lighting budget, or that you don’t know how to use your lenses.</p>

<p>On top of all of that, most lower-cost lenses tend to not be as sharp as higher
grade lenses when they’re used wide-open. If you’re a fan of cheap Rokinon /
Samyang glass, it performs quite well – but not necessarily across the entire
frame wide open. Stopped down to f/4, it compares favorably with high-end Zeiss
and Canon glass, so if you can stop it down a bit further, you’ll get a better
quality image.</p>

<h2 id="time-theres-never-enough-of-it-corollary-the-enemy-of-the-good-is-the-perfect">7) Time: There’s never enough of it. Corollary: The enemy of the good is the perfect.</h2>

<p>There seems to be an inverse relationship between location availability and the
time consuming nature of the shots in a scene. I have tended to find that when
I spend more time setting up a shot, I will get better results than when I
“run and gun” the shots in a scene. (Like every other concept, this has
exceptions.)</p>

<p>Try to make sure you’ve metered and scouted your location properly before
placing actors in front of the camera. You’ll avoid a lot of time-wasting
adjustment and blown takes, which will translated into better looking shots and
a better end product.</p>

<p>As far as “the enemy of the good is the perfect”: it is rarely going to be
perfect. Deciding how much time to spend on that one insert may be the thing
which keeps you from rushing through the rest of your limited time at a
location. This is as much about time management as anything.</p>

<h2 id="prepare">8) Prepare.</h2>

<p>I’ve joked that my pre-production time on a film is longer than the actual
filming time. For the most part, this is actually the case.</p>

<p>Walking onto a set with no idea of what you’re going to do or how you’re going
to do it will lead to amateur errors, rushing, and a poor end product.
Preparation, be it storyboarding, notes, location scouting, or anything else,
is going to save you from some of the easy pitfalls which produce a cheap
end product.</p>

<h2 id="listen">9) Listen.</h2>

<p>You’re one person in (presumably) a fair sized crew of people. If you’re
directing something, you’re the decision maker. You’re the one who has to decide
how something is to be done and who is going to do it, or at least delegate that
to someone else.</p>

<p>If you’re a cinematographer/DP, you’re responsible for the visual aspect of the
film. You have to make the decisions as to how the cameras are set, or at least
delegate that authority.</p>

<p>That doesn’t mean that you can’t listen to other people. Some of my favorite
shots have come from suggestions I’ve gotten from other people. The ability to
look past your own hubris and take suggestions under consideration from other
people can open up your ability to shoot or direct better – and that shines
through in the final product.</p>

<h2 id="do-not-assume-you-can-fix-it-in-post">10) Do not assume you can “fix it in post”.</h2>

<p>“Fix it in post” has been a joke amongst my crew, since I’m not a big fan of
the filmmaking ethos centered around correcting everything in editing and
post production.</p>

<p>(I’m shooting with a rig which requires a fair amount of post production to
bring the footage to its final form, and to be clear, I don’t dislike or
hate post production. I dislike the idea of relying on it for things which you
could have done on set.)</p>

<p>Blood effects are a great example. Any monkey with a licensed (or unlicensed)
copy of After Effects can make a blood spatter effect, but it’ll look like a
low budget horror movie. If you’re going to do blood, do it with practical
effects. Squibs aren’t difficult to design, even on virtually no budget. People
have made them with such inventive materials as
<a href="http://www.refocusedmedia.com/how-to-make-diy-squibs/">condoms and fishing line</a>.
Just because we’ve entered an age of digital cinematography doesn’t mean we have
to throw out practical effects.</p>

<h2 id="one-more-for-safety">11) “One more for safety.”</h2>

<p>My cast and crew have been so used to me saying this phrase that they gave me
an etched mug with it on the side. No matter how well you think you’ve gotten a
scene on film, there’s always a chance that you’re missing something. There is
no worse feeling in editing than when you realize that you’re missing something
in one of your takes and have <strong>no fall back</strong>.</p>

<p>Take the extra few minutes and get another take of that “perfect take”. You’d
be surprised at how often you can avoid embarrassing cuts and amateur looking
transitions.</p>

<h2 id="context-understand-when-youre-doing-something-just-for-the-sake-of-doing-it">12) Context: understand when you’re doing something just for the sake of doing it.</h2>

<p>“Quadracopter” is a latin word which means “I need to wow my financial
backers”. Well, not really, but it could be, judging from the way they’re used.</p>

<p>Just because you have a certain rig or piece of equipment does not mean that
you should necessarily use it for everything you do. If you’re adding a shot
specifically to impress people instead of telling a story, your film is going
to suffer.</p>

<p>Sometimes you need a crane shot. Sometimes you need an overhead shot. Sometimes
you need a snorricam shot. There are plenty of things you <strong>can</strong> do, but your
job as a filmmaker is to be able to determine <strong>when</strong> you should.</p>

<p>Film is about emotional connection and content. If you have a hollow work with
a lot of style, you’ll impress a certain crowd, but it’ll be devoid of any sort
of deeper meaning. Stick with your artistic integrity for as long as you can –
you can always make money, but once you’ve sold out your integrity, you don’t
get it back.</p>

<h2 id="equipment-hubris-never-assume-your-equipment-will-save-you-or-make-you-better">13) Equipment hubris: never assume your equipment will save you or make you better.</h2>

<p>The most important piece of equipment you have as a cinematographer is your
eyes; everything else is much, much less important. I’ve seen films shot on
RED EPIC bodies which look like a high-schooler shot them, and films shot on
DSLRs which rival anything out of Hollywood.</p>

<p>Never assume that a new equipment purchase will make you a better
cinematographer. The only thing that will do that is <strong>time</strong>.</p>

<p>“Equipment hubris”, as I call it, leads to bad and amateur shots. If you just
received a new rig, make sure to log some hours using it before you bring it
on set. Screwing up a basic setting on a camera is a very easy way to destroy
an entire day’s worth of filming … or more.</p>

<h2 id="the-low-light-disease-or-why-i-learned-to-light-and-stopped-hating-my-work">14) The low-light disease, or why I learned to light and stopped hating my work.</h2>

<p>With the rise of the Sony A7 series, with ISO sensitivities of 100k+, and other
low-light and no-light cameras, we’ve also seen the rise of the no-lighting
production.</p>

<p>Hollywood lights the hell out of their films. Despite certain films trying to
portray a low-budget look, you can bet that they have a tractor-trailer full of
lights and lighting modifiers making each shot look good.</p>

<p>Stop assuming that you need speed boosters, faster lenses, and tricks to shoot
with less light. In all but a few cases, you need to add more light, not make
your camera accept more light – and that’ll take away the “cheap” quality
which comes from not using enough light. ETTR is the way to go – as long as
you don’t blow your highlights, you can always decrease the amount of light in
coloring/post-production, if you’ve taken that into account ahead of time.</p>

<h2 id="coloring--color-grading">15) Coloring / color grading.</h2>

<p>Coloring / color grading used to be referred to as “color correction”, but now
that so much more is done with it, “coloring” or “color grading” works as well
as anything else.</p>

<p>Hollywood films go through a round of color grading with people who spend their
professional lives doing it. You can’t just “apply a LUT” or “apply a curve” to
something and have it magically look like a million dollars, any more than an
Instagram filter can make a picture look better instead of just making it look
like it was taken with a terrible camera from the 1970s.</p>

<p>Color grading / coloring is a time-consuming, iterative process. It’s awful to
do, but it’s a necessary evil. It allows you to correct lighting problems
(assuming that your base footage has enough latitude to withstand the
corrections, of course), change color temperature, punch certain colors, and
even correct moving objects or flaws in the camera. It also allows a final
look and feel to be given to your project, which can help take away that indie
low-budget feel to your film.</p>

<p>Color grading / coloring won’t <em>save</em> a terrible film, but it can take a good
film and give it a look and feel which will keep it from being dismissed as
looking amateur.</p>

<h2 id="framing-stop-cutting-off-peoples-heads">16) Framing: stop cutting off peoples’ heads.</h2>

<p>One of the things that immediately jumps out at me about low-budget film
projects, and cheap cinematography in general, is framing. If you’re not paying
attention to the framing of your subject material, the edge of the frame becomes
a knife which slices at your subjects and surroundings.</p>

<p>If you’re going to use a special aspect ratio / crop bars, make sure that you’re
framing according to those bars. I had a project on which I had DP’d where the
decision to adjust aspect ratio was made <strong>after</strong> principal photography had
concluded. This left a bunch of shots where the actors looked decapitated.
These are all things to consider before you choose your focal length, camera
position, et cetera.</p>

<h2 id="dont-ask-for-money-unless-you-really-really-need-it">17) Don’t ask for money unless you really, really need it.</h2>

<p>This is more of a personal pet-peeve. Pay your crew if that’s your
arrangement. If you’re paying one actor, you pay them all. If you’re doing a
senior thesis project, or a festival piece, or something else which isn’t
slated for distribution, please do <strong>NOT</strong> go on kickstarter, gofundme, or any
of the other funding/begging sites to ask for 10-50k$ of money. If you end up
with a chunk of bad publicity and unhappy financial backers, it’s going to
reflect poorly on your film.</p>

<p>(I’m aware that this isn’t a “look and feel” thing, but permit me my slight
digression from the topic at hand; I feel that it is important enough to
mention.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Modifying Computar 12.5mm C-mount lens for M4/3]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/08/14/modifying-computar-12-dot-5mm-c-mount-lens-for-m4-slash-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T15:21:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/08/14/modifying-computar-12-dot-5mm-c-mount-lens-for-m4-slash-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For whatever reason, there seems to be a serious dearth of information
regarding lens modification on the C-mount Computar 12.5mm f/1.3 lens. I am
going to share my experience modifying this lens, in the hope that it will
prevent other people from having the same issues which I have encountered.</p>

<p>As a quick disclaimer, you really should not blame me if you break your lens,
or if it eats your children or animals. This either will or will not work for
you. You have been warned.</p>

<p>You will need:</p>

<ul>
  <li>File or dremel</li>
  <li>Very small screwdriver (flathead)</li>
  <li>C-mount to M4/3 adapter (I used the Fotoasy one)</li>
</ul>

<p>1) <strong>File down the edges of the back mount a little.</strong> I do not think that I
   can stress “a little” enough. If you file this down too much, you will run
   into the same issue I ran into, and will break the back metal piece of
   your lens. I used a triangular file and edged it down to a nice smooth
   surface.</p>

<p>2) <strong>Unscrew the three screws at the base.</strong> This will remove the metal
   back of the lens.</p>

<p>3) <strong>Loosen the center column of the lens.</strong> You will see a small lens
   assembly protruding from the back of the rest of the lens. Loosen it a
   few turns. This is a trial-and-error thing, so be patient.</p>

<p>4) <strong>Reattach the backing with the screws.</strong> The lens assembly should be
   protruding further from the back of the C-mount to M4/3 adapter, when
   attached.</p>

<p>5) <strong>Attempt infinity focus.</strong> Attach to the camera, attempt focus.</p>

<p>If infinity focus is not attainable by step 5, repeat steps 2-5 until it is.</p>

<p>If you end up breaking or cracking the rear C-mount, you can permanently attach the lens to your C-mount to M4/3 adapter using some solder or hot-glue.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DIY $7 Film Slate]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/06/10/diy-7-dollars-film-slate/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T15:50:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/06/10/diy-7-dollars-film-slate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can’t claim credit for this one – my extremely talented and resourceful
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">production designer</a> got the idea to
use an inexpensive slate “prop” and modify it slightly to allow the use of
erasable whiteboard markers. These are usually a bit more than seven dollars,
and we didn’t have the time to wait for one to arrive in the mail for the
shoot in question.</p>

<p>There are only two pieces of “hardware” which are required to make this,
along with a few pieces of duct tape, a sharpie, a ruler, and whatever 
whiteboard markers and erasers you are planning to use on the finished
slate.</p>

<p>You will need to buy these two items from a <a href="http://www.fivebelow.com/">Five Below</a> discount shop:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Slate Prop - $5</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.fivebelow.com/8-5-x-11-neon-dry-erase-boards.html">8.5 x 11 Eraseable Whiteboard</a> - $2</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Apologies for not giving a product link for the slate prop – I had trouble finding it on the Five Below site. I assure you, it does exist…</em></p>

<h2 id="assembly-instructions">Assembly Instructions</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Break the frame of the whiteboard, and remove the cardboard backing and
the broken frame. You should now have a piece of unencumbered whiteboard.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Position the whiteboard over the slate prop’s useless slate writing. You
can’t write on the slate with chalk, so it is pretty useless as-is.
Center it as best you can, then use strips of duct or gaff tape to attach
the whiteboard surface to the clapper.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Use the ruler as a straight-edge to draw sharpie lines to denote the
different markable areas on your slate. In the best penmanship you can
muster, label them with the sharpie.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>It is a pretty simple hack, but quite effective for giving your editor a bit
of A/V sync assistance.</p>

<p><img src="http://jbuchbinder.com/images/7-dollar-slate.jpg" title="'My production designer holding the finished slate'" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boom!]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/12/boom/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-12T08:44:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/12/boom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are quite a few guides, tutorials, videos, and other resources on how to
capture usable boom audio. Most of these have a few usable sections with a
bunch of fluff or useless information accompanying them. This is my attempt to
compile a “quick guide” to capturing usable boom audio, assuming you don’t have
a competent audio engineer in your employ (which I highly recommend). Audio is
half of your deliverable product, as a cinematographer, so you should make sure
that you capture the highest quality audio possible.</p>

<h2 id="proximity-reflections-and-the-inverse-square-law">Proximity, Reflections, and the Inverse Square Law</h2>

<p>Much like light, sound decreases exponentially as you move away from the source
of the sound. One of the first things which you will realize when starting to
capture audio is that it sounds increasingly awful as you move further away –
which can be attributed to two things:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>As you move further away, relative volume decreases</strong>. The background
sounds (“noise floor”, for anyone trying to be technical), consisting of both
the present background noises and any noises introduced in the recording
process, increase when you increase the sensitivity of your recording
equipment. As the source sound becomes quieter, bringing sound up in post
production will also increase that noise. <em>(If anyone says “just record some
room tone”, ignore them; it won’t help you if your source recording is
terrible, since that’s only a solution if you can gate and isolate the
primary sounds in post.)</em> This is one of the compelling reasons why boom
operators are utilized; they allow a recording to be made from closer to
the source.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Reflections</strong>. Light bounces off of everything, as we are taught, and we
have to be careful to deal with those reflections, in terms of color,
brightness, et cetera. Sound does the same thing. It bounces off of surfaces,
but because sound travels slower than light, we <em>notice</em> when it takes a
few milliseconds longer for sound to arrive at our recording device. Even
more insidious, those reflections (which take on different properties and
sounds based on the materials on which they are reflecting) can sound
<em>louder</em> than the original sound – which will make your recording sound
terrible. The closer you are in proximity to the source, the softer the
reflections will be, in comparison to the original sound.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="polarpickup-patterns">Polar/Pickup Patterns</h2>

<p>Not all microphones, or even microphone <em>types</em> are created equal. They all have
different “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microphone#Microphone_polar_patterns">polar patterns</a>”
which describe the areas of sensitivity which the microphones use to pick up
sound. When attempting to capture dialog, for example, an omnidirectional
microphone would be a poor choice, as it picks up sound equally from all
directions, taking away the ability to create greater isolation for the primary
sound source. The most popular boom microphone type is the “shotgun” microphone,
which has a very directed polar pattern, allowing specific isolation of the
sound in question.</p>

<h2 id="levels-peaking-and-limiting">Levels, Peaking, and Limiting</h2>

<p>Getting the recording level <em>just right</em> is one of the more tricky parts of
recording external boom audio. If the audio is too high, “peaking” will occur.
Peaking is the phenomenon which can be heard when the top part of a sinusoidal
wave (which naturally recorded sounds have) becomes squared when the top of the
wave is clipped by hitting the top limit for recording signal. If the audio is
too low, the signal-to-noise ratio will be too low, and bringing the signal up
to a usable level will bring the sound floor up to an obscenely loud level –
making gating nearly impossible to perform.</p>

<p>To properly deal with this, you need to adjust the signal level so that the
loudest sound comes in under 0 dB, which is where most recorders “peak”. If
certain sounds surpass 0 dB, some audio recorders have the ability to apply a
“limiter” effect, which will push the sound level back down to a usable value
as it is recorded. It’s not a desired effect, but it can save you from
clipping.</p>

<p>As you’re adjusting audio levels, you’ll see a constantly fluctuating level of
audio when no primary sound source is active. This is the “sound floor”, and
should be as far away from the bulk of the primary sound levels as possible.</p>

<h2 id="portable-recording-devices">Portable Recording Devices</h2>

<p>I recommend avoiding the <a href="http://amzn.to/1jyOxm5">Tascam DR-40</a> unit unless
you’re <em>positive</em> that you are using a balanced microphone. It tends to have a
weird firmware issue which produces a
<a href="http://www.dvxuser.com/V6/showthread.php?268124-Tascam-Dr-40-Buzz-Clicking-noise">strange clicking sound</a>
(almost impossible to remove) every quarter of a second when presented with an
unbalanced microphone. If you’re worried about this, go for the
<a href="http://amzn.to/QAUvXD">Zoom H4n</a>. It’s a bit more expensive, but it seems to
handle less expensive microphones in a more able fashion, as well as having
signal limiting and a host of other interesting features.</p>

<h2 id="compression-and-formats">Compression and Formats</h2>

<p>Most digital recorder units will record, at a minimum MP3 and WAV formats. WAV
is an uncompressed audio format, which means that it takes up more storage space
than a compressed format, but retains all of the information captured (at the
resolution captured). MP3 is a compressed format, using a psycho-acoustic model,
which means that it drops pieces of information which it figures we aren’t going
to be able to hear. MP3 files take up a smaller amount of space compared to
the same resolution WAV files – but that comes at the cost of throwing some
of the information out. MP3 @ 192kbps or above tends to have enough information
for most uses.</p>

<h2 id="equipment">Equipment</h2>

<p>There’s no “correct” equipment which you need to purchase to be able to capture
boom audio properly. There are, however, a few piece of equipment you’re
probably going to need.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Extendable Boom Pole</strong>. It’s tempting to go with a converted painters’
pole, but trust me – it pays to go with a decent boom pole. This is mainly
due to the additional noises which can be generated by swinging around a
makeshift boom pole. I personally recommend the
<a href="http://amzn.to/1l3TQaQ">On Stage MBP7000</a> boom pole for budget operators. It
doesn’t have an internal mic cable, but it works very well.</li>
  <li><strong>Microphone Cable (XLR)</strong>. This is an easy place to skimp for some people,
but you don’t want to pick up outside noise, so make sure you go with a
shielded XLR cable which is a few feet longer than the maximum size of your
boom pole, fully extended.</li>
  <li><strong>Clip / Shockmount / Zeppelin / Windscreen</strong>. You need something to isolate
the microphone from the wind, vibration, and other distorting effects of
the environment, which would distract from otherwise relatively clean
audio. Shockmounts can be had for relatively little, as can windscreens.
A zeppelin can cost a bundle, unless you make a DIY one – but they produce
very clean-sounding results.</li>
  <li><strong>Wire clips / wraps</strong>. Either some electrical tape (a cinematographer’s
best friend, after gaffe tape), or some inexpensive bobble hair ties
(available at most dollar stores) will allow you to keep the XLR cable
near the pole – otherwise you may find it dropping into frame at the most
inopportune times.</li>
  <li><strong>Microphone</strong>. There is a great deal of conjecture over the “best” budget
microphone to use. The most important things to consider are the polar
pickup pattern, the signal-to-noise ratio, and the frequency response of
any microphone you’re testing.</li>
  <li><strong>Portable digital recorder</strong>. Covered in the portable recorder section.</li>
  <li><strong>Headphones</strong>. A set of headphones, preferably full cup earphones, are
essential to monitoring the sound for disturbances and/or interruptions.
My favorite pair is the <a href="http://amzn.to/1qwuDgi">Sennheiser HD-280 PRO</a>,
as they’re relatively inexpensive (under 100 USD), and produce a fairly
accurate reproduction of live audio.</li>
  <li><strong>Storage media</strong>. Make sure you don’t buy off-brand media cards. Try to
stick with SanDisk and Lexar media, if you can. The trick is that these
companies generally tend to QA their products a bit more rigorously than
most off-brand manufacturers. This can make the difference between
usable audio and a very upset director.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="technique-and-directionality">Technique and Directionality</h2>

<p>Rather than iterate all of the techniques involved in actually operating a
boom mic rig, and keeping in mind that pictures are worth a thousand words…</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.viddler.com/player/39021abf/0/">Boom Mic 101</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Audio is half of your deliverables – so make sure your boom operator knows how
to deliver the best possible audio to your audio engineer for post production.
Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BMPC4K Workflow with Premiere and Resolve]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/08/bmpc4k-workflow-with-premiere-and-resolve/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T07:05:17-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/08/bmpc4k-workflow-with-premiere-and-resolve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a number of “accepted” workflows for going between Adobe Premiere
(as an NLE) and Davinci Resolve (for color correction/grading) for BMPC4K
footage. I am going to detail the workflow I have been using, which should
be useful both for the BMPC4K camera, as well as the BMPCC and BMCC cameras.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Preparation</strong>. Make sure your camera is producing footage at the 23.98
fps frame rate, rather than 24 fps. “True” 24 fps is not quite the same
thing as the “24P” frame rate we are used to.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Load your media onto your workstation</strong>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create simple proxies</strong>. Using
<a href="https://github.com/shootthemoonfilms/prores-proxies">prores-proxies</a>,
create “cheap” lower quality proxies encoded using the H.264 codec in
Quicktime files. I have been experimenting with using the “.mpg”
extension to <a href="http://blogs.adobe.com/VideoRoad/2012/12/premiere-pro-and-quicktime-and-nikon-oh-my.html">force Premiere to use its own internal Quicktime decoder</a>,
rather than the relatively dodgy external one, but the basic process
is the same.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Edit</strong>. Using the proxy files, edit your footage in Premiere. You do
not have to bother with any fancy transitions or effects yet – just
perform a basic edit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Export to Resolve</strong>. Export a “Final Cut Pro XML” file, using the
File &gt; Export menu option.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create a new Resolve Project</strong>. Open Resolve, and create a new project.
Import the original files (not the proxies) into your media pool.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Import the XML from Premiere</strong>. Import the “Final Cut Pro XML” export,
with “Automatically import source clips into pool” deselected. This last
part is very important, as it forces Resolve to use the clips you already
have in the Media Pool.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Color Grade</strong>. Perform your color grade in Resolve.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Export</strong>. In the “Delivery” tab, select the whole timeline, choose
“Easy Setup”,and select  “Final Cut Pro XML Round-Trip”. Change any options
here to your liking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Import Roundtrip XML in Premiere</strong>. Import the Round-Trip XML file in
Premiere. This will bring in all of the graded footage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Perform the remainder of your edits</strong>. Tweak your footage, copy or
create your title cards, etc.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>This is a very basic overview of my current BMPC4K + Resolve + Premiere
workflow right now, and it may change.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[48 Hours with the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-07T13:45:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year, my team (<a href="http://www.shootthemoonfilms.com">Shoot the Moon Films</a>),
entered the 2014 <a href="http://48hourfilm.com/en/boston/">Boston 48 Hour Film Festival</a>
for the first time. It’s an interesting experience, going from genre and
parameters to fully formed script, to planning and preproduction, to
shooting and execution, to editing, scoring, grading, and full post-production
in a single weekend. I’ve learned a lot about working with the 
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">BMPC4K</a>
camera in that time. I am going to iterate over some of the more important
things that I learned over the weekend.</p>

<h2 id="overheating">Overheating</h2>

<p>This simply did not happen. I had heard some horror stories about the camera
body breaking or overheating after long periods of filming, but even in 
direct sunlight for significant periods of time, I did not find this to be
the case. My EOS body used to overheat more than this one…</p>

<h2 id="nd-filters">ND filters</h2>

<p>My Tiffen 77VND was indispensible. If I didn’t have that single piece of
equipment, every exterior shot would have been very, very different. I wanted
a medium DOF and a standard shutter rate for my exterior shots – which meant
that the sunlight had to be stopped down. The variable ND filter delivered
perfectly.</p>

<h2 id="evf">EVF</h2>

<p>The Cineroid was a life-saver. I do not think I would have done as well
without its superior focus-peaking, crop indications, etc. The only feature
sorely missing from the EVF4CSS is waveforms/scopes, which would have been
a bit more useful than eyeballing the full extent of the dynamic range.</p>

<h2 id="v-mount-batteries">V-mount batteries</h2>

<p>If you are not turning your camera off between takes, you are going to need
more than one battery for a day-long shoot. Do <strong>NOT</strong> skimp on a V-mount
battery charger. They take a very long time to trickle charge, so make sure
you have a rapid charger. Also, spares. They may be expensive, but having to
wait on a battery charging could blow a shoot.</p>

<h2 id="audio">Audio</h2>

<p>This is less a “thing” with the BMPC4K body, and more of a general observation.
You cannot skimp on sound. You just <em>can’t</em>. You can always rely entirely on
tight OTS shots and other closeups and use on-camera mics, but it shuts off
an entire avenue of creative wider shots. A boom operator is <em>not</em> just your
buddy holding a mic on a pole – they need to know what they are doing,
otherwise you could be pushing very substandard audio into post-production.
Especially on a tight time limit, this can make the difference between making
a deadline, or having truly horrendous sound.</p>

<p>Also, get a really competent audio engineer. Preferably a really anal-retentive
one with an insane attention to detail. Even if you have perfect video, really
crappy audio can break the illusion of your film. <strong>DO NOT SKIMP</strong>. SERIOUSLY.</p>

<h2 id="that-pa-or-ad----you-need-them-more-than-you-think">That PA or AD – you need them more than you think</h2>

<p>If someone is not taking copious shot notes, you are going to find yourself
up at some ungodly hour, digging through footage for that shot that you
<em>know</em> you got. Save yourself the trouble, and have someone taking care of
all of that.</p>

<h2 id="proxy-files">Proxy files</h2>

<p>I used a new method of creating intermediate proxy files for editing, since
Premiere was not very cooperative in directly loading the Prores files from
the camera. <em>I made my code public in a project called
<a href="https://github.com/shootthemoonfilms/prores-proxies">prores-proxies</a>.</em> This
little trick made sure that, instead of having to render all of my footage
out at the Davinci Resolve speed of 3-6 fps (on my non-Red-Rocket workstation),
I was able to render it to proxies at about full speed (which was about 24fps).
Without this, I wouldn’t have been able to edit the footage without several
footage drops during the day – if at all – during the limited timeframe I
had to do so.</p>

<h2 id="premiere-quicktime-support-on-windows-is-dog-food">Premiere Quicktime support on Windows is dog food</h2>

<p>Something is wrong with it. I have no idea why, but the QT decoder decided
to “give up the ghost” quite a few times during editing. There is supposedly
a renaming hack, which allows the Premiere internal decoder to handle the
files, but I was not privvy to this information during editing. I will update
my documentation and/or author a post on this at some point in the near future,
as it is <strong>VERY</strong> irritating.</p>

<h2 id="too-many-cooks">Too many cooks</h2>

<p>One person edits. Someone can <em>assist</em> them, but you need to have one editor, 
who makes the decisions as to what goes into your final product. If you try
to “edit by committee”, you may end up with a very tired and frustrated primary
editor, and the possibility of some very incomprehensible footage.</p>

<p>If your editor and director are not the same person, the director sits in
with the editor to make decisions, where they need to be made. Ideally the
script notes, etc, provide enough information to the editor to perform his
job.</p>

<p>Also, do not get caught up in reviewing dailies if you are taking part in a
time-sensitive competition. This is a recipe for disaster.</p>

<h2 id="coloring">Coloring</h2>

<p>Even shooting with 10-bit ProRes 422 HQ, the advantage over H.264 DSLR
footage is immediately apparent. There is a lot of latitude for coloring
and correction, which would simply not be possible with the same level of
output quality with H.264.</p>

<p>I ended up performing a manual grading (as in, no LUTs or presets) for the
project we did, and I am very satisfied with the end result.</p>

<h2 id="grain">Grain</h2>

<p>I love the “film grain” that the sensor on this camera produces. I am sure
that I have mentioned it in earlier posts, but it really does give that
organic film look to your output.</p>

<h2 id="do-not-use-services-like-google-drive-for-your-deliverables">Do not use services like Google Drive for your deliverables</h2>

<p>They tend to like to really hurt you in upstream speeds – only when you are
on serious deadline. A better alternative for large media files is to set up
<a href="http://www.bittorrent.com/sync">btsync</a> on both sides, and transfer with far
more efficiency. You will be glad that you did it.</p>

<h2 id="too-many-hats--sink-ships">Too many hats … sink ships?</h2>

<p>There is serious temptation to wear more than one hat. Hell, we all wear more
than one hat on most small sets. The issue comes when you end up wearing
three or four (director, cinematographer, editor, colorist), and realize that
you do not get to sleep until everything is “out the door”. Delegate. Find
people who are good at this stuff, and let them do it. You do not have to be
good at everything, just find people who are.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I had a good time – but I could have been less stressed out, if I had known
some of this in advance.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CAME-06 Blackmagic Cage Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T21:52:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of setting up the <a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">Blackmagic Production Camera 4K</a>,
I have been trying to put together a solid, fairly low-cost set of
accessories for the camera body.</p>

<p>I became aware of a low-cost Chinese cage for the BMCC/BMPC4K
bodies manufactured by an outfit called
“<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/">Xiamen Came Photographic Equipment Co., Ltd.</a>”,
which are available sporting both top and bottom 15mm rail mounts, 
along with the normal mounting options and handles present with
most cage designs. The cage in question is available for
<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">$198, shipping included, from the manufacturer</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://jbuchbinder.com/images/came-06.jpg" width="289" height="400" title="&#34;CAME-06 Cage&#34;" alt="&#34;CAME-06 Cage&#34;" /></p>

<p>My unit arrived today, via DHL, in a box which seemed almost
Ikea-esque in its packing. First thing to note, which is not
indicated either on the website or the packaging: “some assembly
required”. Secondly – no instructions. Thankfully, the entire
assembly procedure seemed pretty obvious with the provided
Allen wrenches. I noticed that there is a 5/8” mount on the
bottom of the unit (as well as a 1/4”-20 mount) for attaching to
the fluid head or quick-release plate of your choosing. This wasn’t
indicated on the website, but I had my suspicions, which were
thankfully confirmed.</p>

<p>The first major issue I encountered was the lack of four of the
required screws for assembly. Undaunted, I took a quick trip to 
the nearest “home improvement” store, and purchased four
M4-.70 x 12 bolts with phillips heads (in packs of two), which
worked like a charm.</p>

<p>The second slightly annoying issue was that one of the included
30cm 15mm rods was completely unthreaded, so it wouldn’t be
possible to attach it to any other rods, should it need to be
extended. The inclusion of the rods was a bit of a plus, so I
can’t really be too upset about that.</p>

<p>The build quality, once assembled, is quite good. The CAME-06
cage is machined properly, and does not interfere with the
operation of the BMPC4K unit at all, and has enough mount points
to allow me to put handles, arms, and other accessories on it,
which was the secondary purpose of purchasing the cage, after
being able to properly mount the camera on a decent QR plate.</p>

<p>Additionally, it has a set of Hirth joints on either side,
ostensibly for attaching handle mounts. I have no use for them
at the moment, but they seem to be workable.</p>

<p>As the next step up in price is another 70$, and this unit
arrived from China in less than four business days from my
initial order, the annoyance of a $1.00 bolt purchase seems
miniscule, considering the usability of the cage itself. It
isn’t a full system, like the Tilta, Lanparte, and others,
but can be built into a system incrementally.</p>

<p>Verdict: Know what you’re getting yourself into. If you want
a pre-assembled unit, next day shipping, and would rather pay
more money for the lack of inconvenience, you should avoid the
CAME-06. It’s a good deal for the price, however.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

<p><em>Postscript: The manufacturer offered to reimburse me for the
missing screws within a day of me writing to them, so they do
seem to be relatively responsive whenever there is a mixup.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First look at the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T11:17:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was lucky enough to be one of the early people on the waiting list for
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/">Blackmagic Design</a>’s new 4K “Production
Camera” body, which I received last week. It boasts a global shutter, Ultra
4K resolution, ProRes/RAW recording at 1080p/4K resolutions, a super 35mm
sensor, EF mount, and around 12 stops of dynamic range – among other
features. I took it out for a test spin with a fellow cinematographer, just
to see how far I could push the image.</p>

<p>After a test run of “horror” shots with both a Canon EF IS lens and a
manual Rokinon Cine lens, I’ve been learning about the benefits and caveats
of the BMPC body. I’m going to enumerate some of those here.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p><strong>Dynamic Range</strong>. This cooks the hell out of the H.264 image that I’ve been
getting out of the 5D mark III. I can see a full gamut of sky color without losing my subjects – and that’s without additional or reflected light.</p>

<p><strong>Cinematic Quality</strong>. This might have something to do with the depth of the
image, or the amazing amount of data that the body is storing for each frame,
but it is definitely capable of breathtaking quality. I haven’t seen any
artifacts from the footage I’ve taken so far, at either HD or 4K resolution.</p>

<p><strong>Metadata</strong>. The touch screen allows some metadata to be stored for each
clip, including the name of the project, scene number, etc, and allows it to
be edited on the camera body afterwards. It also has a numeric unique numbering
system, with customizable body IDs, which beats the MVI_xxxx.MOV or
MM1Axxxx.MOV scheme from Canon.</p>

<p><strong>Resolve</strong>. The body comes with a <em>full</em> copy of DaVinci Resolve 10. The
only way to truly appreciate it is to actually use it. It essentially puts
Fast Color Corrector and Colorista to shame. The only downside is that it
does take quite a bit longer to run than most of the plugin-based correction
and grading tools, unless you’re willing to invest in either a Red Rocket
card or a bunch of fairly powerful GPU units for your machine. Either way,
it is well worth the time and effort to learn how to use it.</p>

<p><strong>Baked in Zebras and Focus Peaking</strong>. This is less of a revelation for me,
coming from using Magic Lantern, but users of stock Canon bodies don’t know
what they’re missing. You can also acquire these via EVF features – but it
can’t be a bad thing to have those features in the body, as well.</p>

<p><strong>Crop Factor</strong>. It’s about the same crop factor as an APS-C crop, for you
7D and Rebel users, so it’s only a big deal to acclimate if you’re coming
from a full-frame body, like the 5D or 6D. The upshot is that you’re not
going to have to blow a lot of money on extremely wide glass, as would be
required by the BMPCC.</p>

<p><strong>Global Shutter</strong>. If you have a lot of fast motion or quick pans, the lack
of the “jello” effect from rolling shutter is very, very noticeable. This is
one of the prime reasons I purchased this body – and it works as well as
promised.</p>

<p><strong>RAW and ProRes</strong>. (Yes, I know “RAW” isn’t an acronym – I just like it enough to shout it…) No firmware hacks, no playing around, you get ProRes
and RAW footage out of this camera body. As of the time of writing, RAW has
been disabled in the firmware, but I’m expecting an update “any day now”
which will re-enable it. This makes me think twice about having usde H.264
as a codec for so long. And the logarithmic data collection means that all
of that nice dynamic range is intact through the coloring process, so you’re
not losing out there.</p>

<p><strong>EF Mount</strong>. This is a big deal for me, as it keeps me from having to rebuy
all of my glass. All of my M42, EF, and Nikon mount glass will be fine with
this. And as an added bonus, the FD mount glass I have (using the Lens
Doctor EF-FD mount adapter) works fine, and without the vignette I have on
the full-frame sensor.</p>

<h2 id="caveats">Caveats</h2>

<p><strong>Mounting</strong>. The standard 1/4” mount on the bottom of the camera is more
or less useless; the mount plates either shift or scratch the bottom of the
camera – so I ended up using the aluminum handles for my tests. They’re not
particularly useful, considering the weighting of the camera, so I’m waiting
for a cage to arrive. I only considered cages with upper and lower 15mm
rod mounts (for options, of course). These are the ones I found to be the
best choices:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">CAME-06 BMCC Cage</a> - $198 -
The cheapest of the non-ePhoto bunch. It’s just a cage with two 30cm
15mm rods included, so you have to kit the rest of it out, but it’s
potentially the best deal, considering the price jump to the
Wooden Camera or Tilta rigs.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ginirigs-usa.com/bmcc-rigs-and-cages/207-the-bmcc-box-cage.html">Gini Box Cage for BMPC</a> - $269 -
This is a slightly more well-known version of the CAME-06. I don’t know
the difference in build quality, but you’re getting similar type kitting.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/NkeVCv">Wooden Camera Base Kit</a> - $939 -
A well designed, modular kit. Expensive, but potentially worth it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/1lGfAud">Tilta TT-BMC-05</a> - $1570 -
Not necessarily the most affordable, but very well designed. Expect to
pay a hefty markup for their branded accessories. Note that this is an
<em>entire</em> rig, rather than just a base kit, so the extra money is probably
worth it, if you have it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Glossy Screen</strong>. The screen is <em>very</em> reflective. I completely understand
the virtual need for an EVF, otherwise you’re in daguerreotype shade cloth
territory. Because it has SDI outputs, rather than HDMI, it’s probably a
good idea to go with one of the SDI EVFs. Unfortunately, they’re not cheap.
You more or less have the pick of these:</p>

<ul>
  <li><del><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/827800-REG/Cineroid_EVF4MSS_EVF_Metal_with_HD_SDI.html">Cineroid EVF4MSS</a> - $699 - 
The least expensive of the set.</del></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/982065-REG/cineroid_evf4css_electronic_viewfinder.html">Cineroid EVF4CSS</a> - $599 -
I realized that you can’t really use the EVF4MSS, despite its metal
materials, because it only supports up to 1080i, whereas the BMPC4k
requires 1080p.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/894123-REG/Cineroid_EVF4RVW_with_Retina_Display.html">Cineroid EVF4RVW</a> - $995 -
Retina display version of the EVF4CSS. Higher resolution, higher price.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/852192-REG/Alphatron_Broadcast_Electronics_EVF_035W_3G_EVF_035W_3G_Electronic_View_Finder.html">Alphatron EVF-035W-3G</a> - $1395 -
The most expensive, but also most highly reviewed SDI EVF. Shane Hurlbut,
A.S.C., endorsed this particular EVF for use with the BMPC body.</li>
</ul>

<p>Otherwise, you’re in the market for both an EVF and an HDMI-to-SDI converter,
which will tack on an addition few hundred dollars. The temporary budget
solution, in my case, is to use a cloth until the EVF arrives …</p>

<p><strong>Battery Life</strong>. The internal battery isn’t supposed to provide much shoot
time ; virtually everyone using the camera has pointed out that it’s meant
to be a sort of “buffer” between battery changes with an external battery.
I bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9XDal">Switronix PB-70</a> for the body, which
sports a RED-style <a href="http://www.red.com/store/products/accessory-v-mount">V-mount</a>,
as well as a traditional 1/4”-20 mount. It can power the camera alone for
at least four hours, and can additionally power other devices, like EVFs,
HDMI-SDI converters, monitors, follow focus devices, et cetera, by the
extensible power connectors. I have to buy an extra one, so I can have one
charging and one plugged in, but it seems to be a decent solution.</p>

<p>Additionally, it helps to have the battery mounted on the camera assembly,
otherwise it is moderately unweildy. The cheapest mounting solution for
15mm rods I found was the <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9YGao">Ikan BMC-PBK-1-S</a> mount,
which has a small distribution center built into it. It’s slightly redundant,
as the adapter that came with the PB-70 isn’t used, but for the money, it’s
a good buy. It may make sense to buy the slightly more expensive
<a href="http://amzn.to/1hcVO4P">Lanparte plate</a>, which has a number of additional
power outputs.</p>

<p><strong>The Sun</strong>. Besides the glossy screen, the sun tends to blow out the fairly
sensitive BMPC4k sensor. The solution is to use ND filters to reduce the
amount of light coming into the sensor. You might be tempted to increase the
f-stop, but you’ll also be increasing the depth of field to be more
un-cinematic, so the ND filter is a must-have if you find yourself shooting in 
the direct sun, and don’t want to start using high shutter speeds. The
downside is going to come in the “price” category; if you buy cheap ND filters,
it will destroy the quality of the image, so you’re best off sticking with
Tiffen or other brand-name high quality filters. They don’t come particularly
cheap, however.</p>

<p>My recommendation to get started would be the 
<a href="http://amzn.to/1qINli9">Tiffen 77VND</a> 77mm variable neutral density
filter. It handles most of the reduction you’ll need, and at about $150, it’s
far less expensive than a set of 4x4 filter glass.</p>

<h2 id="overall">Overall</h2>

<p>I’m glad I didn’t wait for the Panasonic GH4. I know that’s going to come
off as a little odd, but for the smaller sensor, M4/3 mount and its relatively
insane crop factor, expensive add-on cinema kit, even <em>odder</em> form factor,
H.264 codec, limited dynamic range, and rolling shutter – I feel that the
BMPC4k body is going to do just fine. After all, no camera body makes you
film better, or makes you a better cinematographer. All it can do is allow
you the ability to increase your output quality – if you work for it.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I haven’t posted any video clips yet due to the stabilization issues
I had encountered using the handles alone. I may update the post to include
some stills and short clips with the IS lens.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lens Selection for Cinematography]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/12/21/lens-selection-for-cinematography/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T19:48:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/12/21/lens-selection-for-cinematography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The lens of your camera is arguably one of the most important parts of the
camera ; it has the job of controlling light, adjusting focus (and focal
length in variable focal length lenses), controlling depth-of-field
through the aperture, and adding character to the shots you have lovingly
framed. <em>(It should be noted that the sensor of a digital video camera
body is also very important, in terms of sensitivity, resolution, size,
and other factors, but it is out of the scope of this article.)</em></p>

<p>There are quite a few factors to consider when choosing the lens you will
use for a shot, as well as the lenses you will pack for a shoot. Do you
pack one or two variable focal-length lenses, or do you pack a series of
strategic length prime lenses? Do you stay with your native lens mount?
Do you use vintage lenses? Do you need super-fast lenses?</p>

<p>As of the writing of this, I’ve been known to primarily use three or four
prime lenses (24mm, 35mm, 50mm, and 85mm), while packing a 105mm or 135mm
with a set of extension tubes for extreme macro usage. This setup will
<strong>not</strong> work for everyone, as I will explain.</p>

<h2 id="lens-mount">Lens Mount</h2>

<p>There are several types of lens mounts, and depending on the type of camera
body you use, one (or two) will be a “native” mount. For example, if you
shoot using a Canon EOS camera (T3i, 7D, 5D mk3, C100, etc), you will most
likely be using primarily EF mount lenses (and/or EF-S lenses if you aren’t
shooting with a full-frame sensor). These native lenses have the advantage
of having auto-focus / focus-confirmation electronics, as well as being able
to mount with no additional hardware required. Auto-focus isn’t really an
issue with cinematography, and focus-confirmation isn’t a <em>huge</em> advantage,
especially if your camera has focus peaking – but these lenses were
<em>designed</em> to work with your camera body.</p>

<p>Other lens mounts can be accommodated with adapter rings, which can usually
be purchased for varying amounts from online retailers. I have a few
M42 adapter rings for using old Pentax screw-mount lenses with the EF mount
on my camera, and they work flawlessly for me. Some of the more expensive
ones even have focus confirmation capabilities.</p>

<p>Photographers might give some pause to the idea of not having focus
confirmation or auto focus, but cinematographers should be fine with it.
Lens mount should only factor into your decision to use a lens by whether
or not you have the appropriate adapter ring configuration to use that
lens, in my opinion.</p>

<h2 id="prime-or-variable-focal-length-zoom">Prime or Variable Focal Length (Zoom)</h2>

<p>A great deal of the answer to this question depends on the primary type
of cinematography in which you tend to engage. A variable focal length
lens is essentially a single lens which offers an “infinite number of
focal lengths between its two bounds”, but there are other factors to be
considered when using one. For example, many lower-cost variable focal
length lenses will tend to have variable maximum apertures, depending on
the target focal length.</p>

<p>If you’re engaged in documentary cinematography or non-planned shoots
(such as many modern “web series” shoots), you may want to stick with
the widest range of variable focal length lens you can accommodate. A
24-70mm lens will usually handle most shots which would be required by
those mediums, and will mostly eliminate the hassle of changing lenses
during critical (and possibly situationally-limited) shoot times.</p>

<p>A serious trade-off is that most variable focal length lenses are not
“fast” (i.e. do not have a very low f-stop number for their maximum
aperture size), and therefore tend to require more light. The faster
lenses among that class tend to increase in cost greatly.</p>

<p>Prime lenses usually do one thing, and try to do it very well. They
range down (and below) f/1.2, and are far more cost effective for a
single focal length. If you have the time to change lenses in between
shots, and tend away from smash zooms (which I tend to find are a bit
over-used) and dolly/zoom combination shots, you might want to tend
towards a collection of primes.</p>

<h2 id="how-fast-is-fast">How fast is fast?</h2>

<p>The majority of consumer-grade lenses tend to have smaller maximum aperture
sizes than f/2.8, but there are a fair number of inexpensive primes which
can be had with an f/2.8 maximum aperture size, and relatively inexpensive
(compared to some) lenses can be had down to f/1.4 or so, depending on the
relative concessions you’re willing to make regarding the lens quality,
mount, manufacturer, et cetera.</p>

<p>As the aperture size increases, the depth of field decreases in size, but
the amount of light hitting the sensor increases. Low light cinematography
has historically relied on “fast” lenses rather than increased sensor
sensitivity, primarily due to the increasing role that sensor “noise” 
plays at high ISO levels. This tradeoff means that you may have to decide
whether depth of field or light sensitivity will be the primary determining
factor in the maximum aperture rating of the lenses you’re using.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: Another thing to note is that lenses tend not to be their sharpest
or best when fully open, so you may have to shoot slightly further shut
than the maximum aperture rating.</em></p>

<h2 id="vintage-lenses">Vintage Lenses</h2>

<p>Some cinematographers (and photographers) will <em>swear</em> by vintage glass.
Optics from lenses like old Carl Zeiss lenses are still amazing, and some
of these lenses are sold for less than the comparable modern lenses for
them. It can be a potentially <em>expensive</em> habit, however, since
cinematographers have been driving up the cost of purchasing these lenses,
as their lack of focus controls is far less bothersome than it would be
to photographers.</p>

<p>If you can purchase vintage lenses (or happen upon a cache of them), it’s
something to seriously consider. They have their own character, and when
used thoughtfully, can add much to your footage.</p>

<h2 id="focal-length">Focal length</h2>

<p><em>NOTE: If you’re going with variable focal length lenses exclusively, 
you may be able to safely skip this section. It deals mostly with the
reasoning behind using certain focal length lenses.</em></p>

<p>Selection of focal length depends on a number of factors. Entire chapters,
and even whole <em>books</em> have been written about selecting focal lengths
for cinematography and photography. A great deal of it has to do with
the type of shot you are working with, as well as the framing, etc. I’m
going to hit some of the considerations, but I suggest further reading.</p>

<p>When considering focal lengths on cameras, I tend to consider them using
the standard of a “full frame” sensor, since my camera has one. This means
that the written focal length of a lens corresponds directly to the
<em>effective</em> focal length of that lens. A larger “crop factor” (which is
the case for smaller sensor sizes, like the Canon APS-C sensor and the
Micro 4/3 sensors) means that a lens’s effective focal length is longer
for those sensors. You can figure out the effective focal length by
multiplying the stated focal length by the crop factor. For example,
an APS-C crop factor is 1.5x, so a 35mm lens would have an effective
focal length of 52.5mm, and a 50mm lens would have an effective focal
length of 75mm.</p>

<p>“Wide angle” shots, which are usually used for establishing shots in
cinema, generally tend to rely on very “wide” lenses, which are lenses
with short focal lengths. As you move further away from 35mm effective
focal length, the field of view present in your frame increases, which
increases geometric distortion towards the edges of the frame. This has
been referred to as a “fish eye” effect, when present in more than
moderate amounts.</p>

<p>As an aside, I have seen cinematographers use extremely wide lenses
(18mm and shorter) to shoot closeup shots of actors and actresses in
tight quarters – and I must warn against it, unless you are 
<strong>acutely aware</strong> of the geometric distortion which you are introducing
into the frame. This has very unpleasant effects on the faces of actors
when used for close shots, and I know few actors who take kindly to being
represented in a grossly distorted manner.</p>

<p>A 50mm effective focal length is essentially what your eye sees; at least,
that’s the way I’ve come to think of it. It’s a very neutral lens to use
for most shots. I recommend that this length be a standard part of any
lens kit you’re putting together.</p>

<p>50mm lenses have been popular with the Canon DSLR cinematography crowd,
primarily due to the inexpensive nature of the “nifty fifty”, a 50mm
f/1.8 prime which clocks in at a little over 100 USD new. Its optics aren’t
that fantastic, but its point of entry is so low in the cost department
that many people will own one. If you do, consider buying an f/1.4 version
of the same lens (or the f/1.2 L, if you’re successful, or have some sort
of trust fund laying around), as the optical and build quality is far
superior to the 50mm f/1.8 lens. It’s a “midway” focal length, but very
usable for a variety of shots.</p>

<p>Greater than 50mm effective focal lengh lenses are considered “long”
lenses. They tend to “compress” the space they capture, much as wide angle
lenses tend to expand and distort it. One must be careful with using long
lenses for handheld and steadicam work, as camera shake tends to be
magnified with longer lenses. </p>

<p>Long lenses can also be used for closeup and extreme closeup shots by using
“extension tubes” – what my brother used to refer to as “expensive air”.
They increase the amount of light required, and are not as easy or compact
as most macro lenses, but they’re relatively cheap, and cut down on the
number of lenses you have to carry.</p>

<h2 id="what-the-hell-is-a-bokeh">What the hell is a “bokeh”?</h2>

<p>The term “bokeh” is a recent addition to the vocabulary of the photographer
and cinematographer ; it simply refers to the blur produced by out of
focus objects, particularly lights, by a lens. It is determined largely by
the quality of the optics of the lens, as well as the number of blades in
the lens’s aperture. Higher blade counts generally produce more “pleasing”
bokeh, approaching the cinematic standard of almost circular light blur.</p>

<h2 id="you-havent-told-me-which-lenses">You haven’t told me which lenses!</h2>

<p>This isn’t intended to dictate which lenses a cinematographer <em>must</em> carry,
nor push certain choices over others, but merely to attempt to educate
about sensible lens selection.</p>

<p>Consider buying a Pelican case, or other shock resistant case, for travelling
to shoots. If you’re carrying a lot of glass, you can’t afford to deal
with the downtime of a broken lens.</p>

<p>There are a huge number of lenses, both modern and “ancient”, and you can
equip yourself with any variety of lenses, depending on your particular
idiom and shooting style. Don’t fall into the trap of assuming that lens
selection is unnecessary, or that everything should be shot with a single
lens ; it’s just another aspect of cinematic creativity. Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic range]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T11:08:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a photographer or cinematographer, I’m sure you’ve come into contact with
limitations in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range">dynamic range</a>.
I have run into limitations with dynamic range in both the visual and audio
field, since anything that involves “real world” signals is going to 
potentially run up against the ability of the digital mediums on which we
rely to properly store the entire gamut of available analog data that we are
able to perceive with our eyes and ears. To combat the loss of data, computer
scientists and electrical engineers developed the process of dynamic range
compression, which is usually referred to as simple “compression”. This
reduces the gamut of presented information to a digitally representable
format. There is, however, something which is lost – and that is the
original dynamic range ; the amount of variance between the strongest and
weakest signal. In small doses, or when done with finesse, this provides the
ability to produce better sounding and better looking content in the digital
realm. When overused, we see results like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudness_war">loudness war</a>.</p>

<p>I like to explore the more figurative aspects of many technical concepts, to 
which most avid readers of my work would attest. In that vein of ideas, consider
the derivative concept of dynamics as a function of cinematic tension/resolution
and feeling.</p>

<p>Much like a written work, cinematic works generally tend to follow a
“<a href="http://www.dailywritingtips.com/how-to-structure-a-story-the-eight-point-arc/">plot/story arc</a>”,
which have a number of basic stages, even if the presentation, order, and
presence will vary between works. As cinematographers, one of our jobs is to
attempt to portray the basic plot elements, character interactions, and other
potentially metaphysical aspects of the story through the lensing, lighting,
focal points, composition, and method of stabilization and capture we use.
<em>(I’m aware that there are other control points, but forgive me my omissions
for the sake of some semblence of brevity.)</em> For example, for a more
“cinéma vérité” style for a combat or heavy action sequence, a filmmaker could
choose to shoot with less stabilization, looser composition, and less staged
lighting, which would present the audience with the perception that the scene
is far closer to the work of a documentarian than a staged film scene. In
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120815/">Saving Private Ryan</a>, for example, the
battle scenes have a decreased exposure time, resulting in action appearing
far more caustic and (what we believe is) more realistic. This allows the
relative dynamics of the scenes in question to be raised to allow far more
tension and action to be shown, through simple camera work.</p>

<p>The issue with techniques like this begin to manifest themselves when they
begin to flatten the dynamic of a film work through rampant and flagrant
overuse. At some point, cinematographers realized that they could shoot
<em>entire films</em> with these techniques, ostensibly to raise those tension and
action levels to that same high. By doing this, they have effectively
flattened the dynamic range of their works, producing an effectively and
uniformly “loud” work. The questions that you might be asking are “why is this
a bad thing, and why should I care?”</p>

<p>We view things as deltas, or differences. We understand happiness because we
understand sadness, heat because we experience cold, and comfort and
companionship because we can contrast it with loneliness. If the range we are
give to deal with is only the “best parts”, we begin to lose our ability to
appreciate it, and all of those things which should have made it special and
artistic become mere convention. Think about it – if everyone screamed
everything at the same volume, rather than having varying levels of emphasis
and volume, wouldn’t that screaming have lost its impact and importance?</p>

<p>Every technique that you have as a cinematographer or photographer is another
potential tool in your figurative tool box; but just because you have them
doesn’t mean that you have to use one particular one <em>all the time</em>. Handheld
camerawork has its place, and even though modern technology has provided many
methods of stabilizing camera and lens motion, from the steadicam to image
stabilization/vibration reduction lens to three point shoulder rigs, we still
find many cinematographers intentionally introducing shake into their
footage. I wrote an <a href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/06/03/stabilization/">entire essay</a> 
on the importance of stabilization, so I won’t reiterate my grievances here.</p>

<p>It’s important to understand why you’re doing something rather than
simply doing it for convenience or convention. If you’re using a wide open
aperture, are you doing it because you’re having lighting issues, or simply
because you think that everything should be shot with the thinnest DOF
possible? Is there some sort of artistic reason why you chose to shoot with
a 24mm vs a 35mm lens for a particular shot? Are you using a tripod-based
shot rather than a steadicam for a reason? Asking questions and analyzing
your own work, as well as the work of others, is key to artistic growth, as
well as understanding how to use your skillset as a photographer or
cinematographer.</p>

<p>I am, by no means, at the top of the skill grouping for photography <em>or</em>
cinematography. Many of the entries I have authored here are products of
making mistakes, and they are the attempt I am making to keep others from
having to make some of the very same mistakes I have made. Even films and
other work which we don’t particularly like as a whole may have a few 
setups or shots which provide food for thought. So, watch those films with
a critical eye, and hopefully we can all expand our “toolboxes”, as well
as learn how to use them in a more effective manner. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Signal to noise ratio]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T15:06:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To quote the venerable Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Signal-to-noise ratio (often abbreviated SNR or S/N) is a measure used in science and engineering that compares the level of a desired signal to the level of background noise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This has a number of applications in engineering, but it also nicely
encapsulates a basic truth of dealing with equipment, people, and works –
there is always a certain amount of background noise. (For more information
on the concept, check out <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal-to-noise_ratio">this article</a>.)</p>

<p>In an ideal world, all equipment would be flawless and noiseless, everyone
would be wonderful at what they do, and all works would be exceptional 
<em>(don’t mind the inherent logical issue in the statement “all works would be
exceptional”; I was trying to make a point, so please forgive me my
linguistic foibles)</em>. As it so happens, due to a fun little thing called the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Krueger Effect</a>,
we tend to assume that our works are better than they actual are, until we
reach a particular skill level, at which point we start underestimating our
own skill levels. Succinctly put, we’re all terrible at figuring out how good
or bad we are at any particular skill.</p>

<p>This is a real pickle, especially when dealing with other people. With very
few exceptions, we’re going to end up working with other people. This is more
applicable in cinematography than in photography, since there are usually more
people involved with a film production than with a still photo shoot (although
I’m sure there are plenty of instances which would prove me wrong in that
aspect). </p>

<p><em>I’m going to restrict my examples to cinematography projects, to keep
this a bit more manageable and readable.</em></p>

<p>First, look at your potential crew. If you’re dealing with a low-budget indie
shoot, which most of us are, you are either not paying your crew or are paying
them very little money. You’ve already eliminated the possibility of a great
number of highly experienced, educated, and trained people being involved,
simply by eliminating the carrot of a serious payday. It could be additionally
argued that those who do work for a living are not necessarily <em>great</em> at
what they do, but that’s a little tangential to the core of the argument.
Out of those people, you’re generally going to tend to see the talent curve
follow the infamous <a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/NormalDistribution.html">standard/normal distribution curve</a>.
This means some will be utterly atrocious, some will be genius, and the
vast majority will lie somewhere between those two points. The outliers and
bounds will depend on the sample size, but the general concept tends to be
the same, which is that most people are not going to possess genius-level
skills in the vast majority of a sample set.</p>

<p>Second, look at your potential actors/on-screen talent. You’re in the same
boat as you were with the crew – except that a single truly terrible actor
will destroy the illusion you’re trying to create, so you have to hope that
your lower bound is pretty high, otherwise your end product will most likely
suffer. (It should also be said that a really great director has been known
to coax amazing performances out of lackluster talent, but we can’t all be
Stanley Kubrick, Darren Aronofsky, or P.T. Anderson…)</p>

<p>So, what are we to do? We need to start acknowledging that not everything
we’re going to make is going to be the best thing <strong>ever</strong>. It’s an anathema
to the general self-aggrandizing L.A. film culture, but we have to respect
the normal distribution curve – most films will be mediocre, some will be
agonizingly bad, and some will be amazing. The DKE means we’ll always think
that they’re all amazingly wonderful, but we need to be far more critical of
our own works ; at least, if we want to try to produce high-quality output.</p>

<p>We also need to understand that there’s a place for our hubris, as well as
our humility. We cannot grow as filmmakers, photographers, artists, or as
people, until we both appreciate the skill-set we have, while at the same
time understanding the limits of what we have accomplished right now, and
always striving to produce better, become better, and encourage better. We
can’t all be the <strong>best</strong>, but we can all become <strong>better</strong>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checking for deprecated Wordpress functions]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/13/checking-for-deprecated-wordpress-functions/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-13T15:29:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/13/checking-for-deprecated-wordpress-functions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the major pains involved in Wordpress development and work (and one
of the reasons why this isn’t hosted on Wordpress anymore) is that of their
quickly changing API.</p>

<p>I’ve encountered issues where plugins have suddenly (and quietly) stopped
functioning, due to a deprecated function call being removed from the
Wordpress API. I’m sharing my “solution” to this issue, which is a script
(which can be integrated into a CI system), which scans your plugin and/or
theme code and gives you a list of the deprecated functions you’re using,
as well as where they exist in your code.</p>

<div><script src="https://gist.github.com/7419000.js"></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash
#
# Wordpress Deprecated function checker
#
# Version: 0.2
#
# Author: Michiel Roos &lt;michiel@donationbasedhosting.org&gt;
#         Jeff Buchbinder (https://github.com/jbuchbinder)
# 
# www.php.net/manual/en/migration53.deprecated.php
#
# Original code: http://www.typofree.org/article/archive/2011/may/title/check-your-php-code-for-deprecated-ini-directives-and-functions/
#
# Jeff's notes:
#
# *) This version should return a non-zero bash &quot;errorlevel&quot; if deprecated
#    functions are found, which should allow easy integration into CI systems.
# *) This was adapted from a deprecated function checker to allow Wordpress
#    specific pre-upgrade checks.

tag=$1

if [ &quot;$tag&quot; == &quot;&quot; ]; then
    echo &quot;Wordpress version must be specified.&quot;
    exit 1
fi

whereami=&quot;$( cd &quot;$(dirname &quot;$0&quot;)&quot;; pwd )&quot;

function dfunctions() {
    tag=$1
    
    # Derived from the list at http://codex.wordpress.org/Category:Deprecated_Functions
    # (Use Coral Cache to cut down on Wordpress TRAC load.)
    deprecated_sources=(
    	http://core.trac.wordpress.org.nyud.net/browser/tags/${tag}/src/wp-includes/deprecated.php?format=txt
    	http://core.trac.wordpress.org.nyud.net/browser/tags/${tag}/src/wp-admin/includes/deprecated.php?format=txt
    	http://core.trac.wordpress.org.nyud.net/browser/tags/${tag}/src/wp-includes/pluggable-deprecated.ph?format=txt
    	http://core.trac.wordpress.org.nyud.net/browser/tags/${tag}/src/wp-includes/ms-deprecated.php?format=txt
    	http://core.trac.wordpress.org.nyud.net/browser/tags/${tag}/src/wp-admin/includes/ms-deprecated.php?format=txt
    )
    
    for s in ${deprecated_sources}; do
	    wget -q -O /dev/stdout &quot;$s&quot; | grep '^function ' | cut -d' ' -f2 | cut -d'(' -f 1
    done
}
deprecatedFunctions=(
    $( dfunctions ${tag} )
)

len=${#deprecatedFunctions[*]}
i=0

echo &quot;Checking for deprectated functions ______________________________________&quot;
echo &quot;&quot;

found=0

while [ $i -lt $len ]; do
    echo &quot;  // checking for '${deprecatedFunctions[$i]}()'&quot;
    grep -rn --color --include=*.php &quot;^[^#\/]*[^a-zA-Z_]${deprecatedFunctions[$i]}[[:space:]]*(&quot; *;
    if [ $? -ne 0 ]; then
        found=1
    fi
    echo &quot;&quot;
    let i++
done

exit $found
</code></pre></noscript></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Ganglia for OpenBSD 4.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/29/building-ganglia-for-openbsd-4-dot-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-29T12:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/29/building-ganglia-for-openbsd-4-dot-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had to build a modern version of the <a href="http://ganglia.info">Ganglia</a>
monitoring system for an <a href="http://www.openbsd.org/">OpenBSD</a> 4.3 firewall, which
hadn’t been upgraded to a modern version of OpenBSD in quite some time. I
documented the process, which I’m sharing here.</p>

<div><script src="https://gist.github.com/7217488.js"></script>
<noscript><pre><code># Build and install gmond on OpenBSD 4.3

# Install prerequisites
pkg add automake-1.9.6p2 autoconf-2.61p1 libtool libconfuse unzip wget

# Compile and install apr-1.4
wget -c http://mirrors.gigenet.com/apache/apr/apr-1.4.8.tar.gz
tar zxvf apr-1.4.8.tar.gz
cd apr-1.4.8
./configure &amp;&amp; make &amp;&amp; make install
cd ..

# Download and install monitor-core
wget -c https://github.com/ganglia/monitor-core/archive/master.zip -O master.zip --no-check-certificate
unzip master.zip
cd monitor-core-master
export AUTOMAKE_VERSION=1.9
export AUTOCONF_VERSION=2.61
./bootstrap
./configure --sysconfdir=/etc --without-gmetad --with-libapr=/usr/local/apr/bin/apr-1-config --with-libconfuse=/usr/local 

# Need to patch some minor stuff...
# libmetrics/openbsd/metrics.c:
#   line 446:
#     kp = kvm_getprocs(kd, KERN_PROC_ALL, 0, sizeof(struct kinfo_proc), &amp;cnt);
#   should be changed to:
#     kp = kvm_getprocs(kd, KERN_PROC_ALL, 0, &amp;cnt);
#
#   line 466:
#     kp = kvm_getprocs(kd, KERN_PROC_ALL, 0, sizeof(struct kinfo_proc), &amp;cnt);
#   should be changed to:
#     kp = kvm_getprocs(kd, KERN_PROC_ALL, 0, &amp;cnt);
#
#   line 468 should be commented out.

make all &amp;&amp; make install
cd ..</code></pre></noscript></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Preparing for and recovering from disaster]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/13/preparing-for-and-recovering-from-disaster/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-13T20:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/13/preparing-for-and-recovering-from-disaster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the greatest nightmares associated with digital cinematography and
photography is that of the specter of data loss. The very notion that your
carefully planned shots or footage could disappear in a single instant can
be Earth-shattering, since it may not be possible to reshoot (or may be
prohibitively expensive). The best defense is to be prepared, not only for
the possibility that you may lose data, but also to safeguard against that
possibility through preventitive measures.</p>

<h2 id="preparation">Preparation</h2>

<p>There are a number of things you can do to try to protect against data loss,
both before and after shooting has taken place. Here are a few of them:</p>

<p><strong>Don’t use dodgy or off-brand memory cards.</strong> This may seem pretty obvious
to those who have been down this road, but really crappy cards tend to have
dodgy QA processes involved in their manufacture, so although you may get a
good card, you’re just as likely to get a dud – which could end up with your
data. I’ve found that “Amazon Basics” and “KomputerBay” cards have failed me
pretty regularly. Even “Transcend” cards have been pretty dodgy for me, on
occasion. I tend to stick with “SanDisk” branded cards, when I use SD media,
and there are a few decent manufacturers of CF media (Lexar, SanDisk, etc),
which tend to produce quality cards, in my experience.</p>

<p><strong>Storage media doesn’t last forever.</strong> Every piece of flash media has a
certain number of R/W cycles before it becomes unstable and/or unusable.
After a period of time, you might want to start regularly replacing your
media cards to avoid the possibility that errors will begin to occur. It’s
also a good idea to low-level format the cards in between uses, which
supposedly increases their lifespan.</p>

<p><strong>A single physical copy of your product is a bad idea.</strong> If you just move
files off to your laptop harddrive, you’re practically expecting something
to destroy your media. A single SSD or spinning platter in a laptop is a
prime target for an accident to wipe out your data. Ideally, a RAID
(<em>R</em>edundant <em>A</em>rray of <em>I</em>nexpensive <em>D</em>isks) array would provide a
good tradeoff between inexpensive media and redundant storage. I built a
pretty inexpensive one with the following components:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/19EmtYA">Sans Digital MR2UT+ MobileRAID</a>: A two-disk
enclosure, which, when set to RAID-1, gives you a set of mirrored
hard disks, accessible by USB 3.0 or an eSATA interface.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/19IlAdp">Seagate Barracuda 2 TB HDD</a>: Two of these
disks will provide you with a total of 2 TB of redundant storage.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>A single physical location is a bad idea.</strong> Consider off-site backup. If
you don’t have the money to store your data in <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">S3</a>
or a similar service, consider using something like
<a href="http://labs.bittorrent.com/experiments/sync.html">Bittorrent Sync</a>, with a
friend or two providing remote backup locations. If this isn’t feasible,
periodically backing up to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Linear_Tape">DLT</a>
or another backup tape, then storing that offsite, may be useful. If you
are questioning “why do I need off-site backup”, just remember that a single
fire or natural disaster can destroy all of your hard work…</p>

<p><strong>Camera-based writing solutions.</strong> Certain cameras (the Canon EOS 5D
Mark III, for example) have multiple media card slots, and have the ability
to write multiple copies of the same media. This can help circumvent the
tragic circumstance (to which I have fallen victim) of a completed shoot
with the inability to read any of the captured data later on. To understand
this, <a href="http://protogtech.com/cameras/canon-5d-mark-iii-record-separately-vs-record-to-multiple-performance-comparison/">read more here</a>.
It should be noted that there are some performance limitations to this,
but if you’re not shooting RAW video and your camera body can handle this,
you might want to seriously consider it.</p>

<h2 id="recovery">Recovery</h2>

<p>There is a pantheon of free and open-source software suites which provide
recovery of lost files, deleted files, destroyed partitions, etc. The true
nightmare scenario would involve a piece of damaged media, from which the
data cannot be extracted – but never assume this unless you have exhausted
all other avenues of recovery.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.cgsecurity.org/wiki/PhotoRec">PhotoRec/Testdisk</a> (Open source,
Linux/Windows/Mac/DOS/etc). This is one of my favorites, although it
may potentially require some fairly in-depth technical expertise to
fully exploit its potential.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.piriform.com/recuva">Recuva</a> (Freeware, Windows). Recovers
deleted files.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.hirensbootcd.org">Hiren’s Boot CD</a> (Freeware, Boot Disc).
Hiren’s is a classic recovery and utility boot disk, which can be
booted on any Intel-based computer. The download is free, and it has
a very comprehensive suite of recovery tools. If you don’t have a copy
of this disc hanging around your studio or house – why not?</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.wondershare.com/disk-utility/cr2-photo-recovery.html">Wondershare Photo Recovery</a> (Freeware, Windows/Mac).
A semi-commercial digital media file recovery suite.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.icare-recovery.com/free/camera-raw-photo-recovery-free.html">iCare Recovery Free</a> (Trialware, Windows).
This has a 2GB maximum data file recovery limit with the trial, otherwise
a license has to be purchased.</li>
  <li><a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~oskin/saveimg.html">saveimg</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
Extracts JPEG images from raw disk devices. Requires some expert
knowledge to use properly.</li>
  <li><a href="http://foremost.sourceforge.net/">Foremost</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
Digital forensic tool to recover files based on headers, footers, and
internal data structures.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.lc-tech.com/pc/sandisk-rescuepro-and-rescuepro-deluxe/">SanDisk RescuePRO</a> (Trialware, Windows).
SanDisk’s recommended recovery software.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/ddrescue/ddrescue.html">ddrescue</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
A data recovery tool. It copies data from one file or block device
(hard disc, cdrom, etc) to another, trying hard to rescue data in case
of read errors.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.stellarphotorecoverysoftware.com/camera-recovery/">Stellar Photo Recovery</a> (Trialware, Windows/Mac).
Another digital photo recovery suite. The trialware shows what can be
recovered, with previews.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.pcinspector.de/default.htm?language=1">PC Inspector</a> (Freeware, Windows).</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.prosofteng.com/products/data_rescue.php">DataRescue</a> (Mac).</li>
  <li><a href="http://subrosasoft.com/OSXSoftware/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;cPath=1&amp;products_id=3">Camera Salvage</a> (Freeware, Windows).</li>
  <li><a href="http://datarescue.com/">PhotoRescue</a> (Windows/Mac).</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.cfcardrecovery.com/">CF Card Recovery</a> (Trialware, Windows/Mac).</li>
</ul>

<p>Hopefully, this will either make it easier to avoid potential data loss, or
at least help to minimize the impact, if and when you end up losing data.</p>

<p>As always, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Composing for Aspect Ratios]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/30/composing-for-aspect-ratios/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T20:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/30/composing-for-aspect-ratios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Aspect ratios, simply put (for those who are unaware), are the ratios between
the width and height of a single frame of video. Television has had a 4:3
ratio (4 units of width to 3 units of height), until the popularization of
“HD” television, using a “widescreen” ratio of 16:9. I’m not going to go
through the entire history of aspect ratios in cinema, as there is a
<a href="http://vimeo.com/68830569">great retrospective available on vimeo</a>.</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/68830569 "></iframe></div>

<p>Most DSLR cinematography is done, by default, with a 16:9 ratio, as the
maximum capture size for their video is generally 1920x1080, abbreviated as
1080p (to additionally indicate progressive, rather than interlaced, scan).
It is relatively easy to enforce a “wider” aspect ratio by dropping lines at
the top and bottom of the frame, which most watch-at-home film viewers will
identify as “black bars” at the top and bottom of the frame. This does,
however, introduce an interesting issue – that of composing inside that
frame. That ends up looking something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://jbuchbinder.com/images/black-bars-aspect-ratio-16-9-21-9-4-3-cinemawide.png" alt="Black bars for different aspect ratios" title="Black bars for different aspect ratios" /></p>

<p>Standard compositional rules generally make use of the two frame diagonals
(top left to bottom right, and bottom left to top right) and both horizontal
and vertical thirds. Most compositional choices for “balanced” frames have
tended to rely on these invisible divisions to create a pleasing image, even
though the rules are really <em>guidelines</em>, and are not absolute. If you, as
a cinematographer, decide that you’re going to use an alternate aspect ratio,
you cannot properly compose by using the thirds or diagonals indicated by any
common guide or viewfinder in 16:9 ratio, as they will result in a vastly
skewed product, compared to the original on-camera image. I’ve seen a number
of forums on DSLR cinematography which had suggested everything from
using a black marker to denote the frame to using black tape to cover the
segments outside of the final crop. A more “modern” solution for Canon
DSLR owners is using <a href="http://magiclantern.wikia.com/wiki/Cropmarks">Magic Lantern cropmarks</a>.
If you’re shooting with another DSLR brand, you may be at the mercy of the
firmware, or any of the aforementioned hacks.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I’d like to mention, at this point in this article, that there are
other compositional rules, including <a href="http://photoinf.com/Golden_Mean/Eugene_Ilchenko/GoldenSection.html">golden ratio/mean/spiral/rectangle</a>,
so please don’t take the rule of thirds and diagonals to be the only important
and pleasing ways to frame an image….</em></p>

<p>Besides attempting to find a way to follow common compositional rules, there
is another side to aspect ratio: selecting the appropriate one for the story
you are attempting to tell. Apart from the 16:9 ratio being the “standard
format” for HDTV broadcasts and web-based series, it is much taller (i.e.,
it offers more headroom for shots) than Cinemascope (2.35:1) or some of the
other aspect ratios. Depending on the types of shots which you are using to
compose your film, it may be advantageous to have a wider, yet thinner,
view of the world which comes with “shorter” aspect ratios. Again there is
no “one size fits all” for aspect ratios, and it should be a conscious
decision for the material which you are filming.</p>

<p>An added advantage to using a shorter aspect ratio is that, due to the
camera bodies recording the entire frame, regardless of target aspect
ratio, additional editing and recomposition “wiggle room” is available in
the editing and post-production process. If something isn’t framed in the
exact way it should be, this can be corrected later by adjusting the vertical
positioning of the frame within the crop. Most (if not all) NLE software
has vertical positioning, including
<a href="http://help.adobe.com/en_US/premierepro/cs/using/WSC7A162B6-6EF1-49e1-8622-8127366710BB.html">Adobe Premiere</a>,
<a href="http://vegasaur.com/pan-crop-assistant">Sony Vegas</a>,
and <a href="http://www.peachpit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=1677950&amp;seqNum=8">Final Cut Pro</a>,
so you shouldn’t have any issues doing this. I’m aware that the ideal
cinematographer does everything in-camera (as I have vociferously
advocated in past), and does not rely on post-production to fix mistakes,
this does allow for that possibility.</p>

<p>Aspect ratios additionally carry some subconscious baggage with them, due
to the associations we have made with previous material filmed using them,
much in the same way we associate film grain with high-end Hollywood
pictures, even when, in many cases, that film grain was added back to
the digital footage in post-production.</p>

<p>The quick takeaway is that you shouldn’t embark on a project without having
made a conscious decision regarding the aspect ratio which you are using for
that project, considered the ramifications and technical concerns associated
with that decision (including making sure that you can properly frame and
compose shots in that aspect ratio), and storyboarded and/or prepared your
material considering your chosen aspect ratio. It is yet another variable
which can be tweaked to help make an already good project that much better,
and like all power, it comes with responsibility. So, choose –
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oF2UrYSDb3k">but choose wisely</a>, and as
always, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Documentary Filming]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/19/on-documentary-filming/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T16:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/19/on-documentary-filming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had the pleasure of shooting for a documentary down in
Birmingham, AL, about one of the people involved in the 
<a href="http://www.nps.gov/nr/travel/civilrights/al11.htm">16th Street Baptist Church Bombing</a>
in 1963. For those who don’t know, that event was one of the most
important parts of the Civil Rights movement in the 1960s. The
50th anniversary of the bombing was this September (2013), so I had
gone with a small film crew to cover the event, and interview some of
the people involved.</p>

<p>I had never shot documentary footage, apart from some small controlled
one-on-one interviews, so this was an interesting learning experience for
me. I’d like to share some of the more important things which I learned
over the course of my experience down there.</p>

<p><strong>Batteries</strong>. You’re going to run out of them. I ran through four batteries
over the course of a filming day – which I thought would be enough, but
weren’t. If you have one thing which requires a strange and unique battery,
you should have at least one spare, even if it’s new. Someone is invariably
going to leave something on, chew up the battery, and leave you short a
vital piece of equipment. If you’re shooting with a DSLR, try to get a
multi-battery grip, so that you don’t have to change batteries as often.</p>

<p><strong>One Shot</strong>. You only have <em>one shot</em> to get event coverage correctly,
which means that, ideally, you should be covering from more than one angle,
to provide not only options in editing, but some sort of redundancy.
Otherwise, you can easily be left with a serious dearth of footage for
what could be a vital part.</p>

<p><strong>Focus and Calibration</strong>. Get there early, get set up, get everything
metered and working properly <em>before</em> things start moving. You really can’t
easily recalibrate during taping without potentially ruining footage. Did
I forget to mention that you only get <em>one shot</em> with event footage?</p>

<p><strong>Depth of Field: More is Better</strong>. You’re not shooting an art piece, you’re
trying to cover something which probably only happens once, so you shouldn’t
be shooting at f/2.8 or something ridiculous like that. Yes, you can sometimes
take advantage of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperfocal_distance">hyperfocal distance</a>
of a lens to keep far-away objects in focus – but you should, most likely,
find a fairly closed aperture to work with. This can be challenging in low
light scenarios, where you’ll be fighting the specter of sensor noise at
extremely high ISO levels when you close the iris more than a little.</p>

<p><strong>Positivity</strong>. You need to be happy and in a good place when shooting people
and interviews, especially in a one-on-one setting. Other people take certain
cues from your body language and demeanor, and hostility will produce
hostility. If at all possible, try to work on documentary projects which you
like, or identify with.</p>

<p><strong>Lens Changes</strong>. If you can avoid it, don’t. Wear cargo pants or a vest with
lens pockets, much like most photographers, if you absolutely <em>must</em> change
lenses. If you’re shooting a long distance, go with something like the
<a href="http://amzn.to/14nI8Cm">Canon EF 70-200mm f/2.8L IS II USM</a> lens, or if you
are dealing with shorter distances, the
<a href="http://amzn.to/189gQmi">Canon EF 24-70mm f/2.8L II USM</a> lens. Carrying a few
primes around will work well for static interview shots, but they’re going to
be a real pain when you’re dealing with moving targets, no matter how quick
you are with focus peaking assistance. If you’re shooting with a shoulder rig,
you’re going to want an IS/VR lens, if you have one available – it cuts down
on a lot of shudder and shake.</p>

<p><strong>Bring a Spare</strong>. Got one lav mic? You might want to bring a second one.
If there’s a small piece of equipment or accessory which, if missing, could
screw you, it’s going to go missing. Especially when you’re far from home
base and without the benefit of an equipment store.</p>

<p><strong>You’re Going To Mess Up</strong>. This is pretty obvious – no matter how careful
you are, something is going to get messed up. The trick is to try to make
everything redundant enough that it doesn’t matter.</p>

<p><strong>It’s Not About Your Equipment</strong>. Someone there is going to have a better
camera, better lenses, and better <em>everything</em> than you have. Go far enough,
and your rig is going to look bad to someone. Just remember, you’re there for
a reason, so know your equipment, and use it as well as you can.</p>

<p><strong>Rocking Out</strong>. If you’re interviewing someone who is rocking back and forth,
bring it to their attention. It creates massive focusing, framing, and
perspective issues. Don’t be intimidated; they can rock as much as they’d
like, just as soon as you’re done filming.</p>

<p><strong>Network</strong>. If you’re looking for an interview with someone, talking to
some of the people around them may lead you to another interviewee who may
produce even better results. There’s no cost associated with being polite.</p>

<p><strong>Respect the Eyeline</strong>. For static interviews, don’t shoot up or down on
someone’s eye-line unless you are trying to indicate something about that
person. You should be even with their eye-line on initial shot setup. This
is also a good idea when doing non-static interviews, when possible.</p>

<p><strong>Make Two Copies</strong>. When you transfer the data off of your memory cards,
make two copies, and if possible, don’t transport them together. Redundancy
is the name of the game here, since even the best footage means diddly/squat
if no one ever gets to see it.</p>

<p><strong>Bring a Sound Guy</strong>. I know, you don’t think you need one – you’ve got a
lav mic, right? A sound engineer is half of your production, since you’re in
charge of the visuals. Also, boom mic operators generally should be fairly
competent sound engineers, to avoid issues later on in the post-production
process – when possible.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t Go For The Cheaper Chicken</strong>. When booking accommodations, don’t go
for the least expensive hotel – there’s a good chance that it’s in a dodgy
part of town, and that extra 10 dollars a night might buy you not only a
bit of security, but might buy you a better night’s sleep. Protip: the
cheapest hotel is generally right next to a) train tracks with 24-hour train
service, b) an open-air coal mine, c) a condemned house with mysterious
block parties at all hours of the night, or d) all of the above…</p>

<p><strong>Get Stills</strong>. If you’re doing a documentary with a bunch of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Burns_effect">Ken Burns effect</a> style
picture montages, you should try to either take stills yourself, or have
another camera operator capture some for you. If you can, attempt to take
pictures of landmarks or buildings when they are not occupied, unless it
specifically works in your storytelling to have them occupied or surrounded.</p>

<p>There are many, many more things to think about when it comes to filming
documentaries and documentary footage – but hopefully, these bullet points
will help someone else avoid some of the pitfalls I experienced on my first
documentary shoot. Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are you a cinematographer or a camera operator?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/are-you-a-cinematographer-or-a-camera-operator/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T21:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/are-you-a-cinematographer-or-a-camera-operator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s only a slight difference in the textbook definition between a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinematographer">cinematographer</a> and a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camera_operator">camera operator</a>. Besides the
slight variance in responsibilities (a cinematographer/DP can be responsible
for several camera operators), there are some additional skills and
aptitudes which play into the decision to try to be a cinematographer.</p>

<p>None of this is meant to downplay the skill and experience which make a
great camera operator. Knowing your equipment, being able to choose the
proper lenses and camera settings, being able to operate that equipment,
being able to interpret the direction of both the director and the
cinematographer, and being able to hold together a cohesive shot –
these are all the hallmarks of a great camera operator.</p>

<p>At a much, much more basic level, there’s an <em>art</em> to cinematography, which
transcends the physical manipulations of the equipment involved, and becomes
more about creating a sort of separate reality; that of capturing a little
slice of time and space, motion and stillness, light and dark, vibrant
colors and subtle undertones. That’s the part of this that, to me, offers
the most promising creativity and the most fulfilling, yet burdening, tasks.</p>

<p>It’s very easy to get lost in the minutiae of camera settings adjustments,
equipment acquisition, troubleshooting and stabilization, among other
demons – but the <em>art</em> is the derivative of those functions.</p>

<p>To properly illustrate this, I think of a concert I attended, quite a few
years ago. The guitarist, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/VernonReid">Vernon Reid</a>,
was (and still is), an amazing technical instrumentalist. I watched him dance
over the semi-circle of effects pedals and boxes, his hands moving,
seemingly effortlessly over the six strings on his instrument. It struck me
as astounding. We are all, in some way, capable of recognizing genius and
immense skill, even if we cannot reproduce it, or explain it in purely
quantifiable terms. In that way, the body of his technical skills simply
became a foundation for the <em>art</em> which was made by way of them. I wish I
could explain it better – I only know that I could recognize it when I saw
it. The man himself, whom I had the pleasure of speaking with for a few
brief moments, was very humble and very “zen” about his skill and his art.</p>

<p>Due to my particular circumstances, I’ve been able to pick and choose projects,
more of late, specifically based on their relative merits to me. As such, I
haven’t had much experience acting strictly as a “camera operator”. There
may be some hubris, on my part, which would have come out of getting to
perform the artistic duties of a cinematographer on the vast majority of the
projects on which I’ve been involved. It has given me an affinity for the
creative aspects of the job. For as long as I’ve been involved with
cinematography, I have always assumed that being a “camera operator” has been
a step towards being a cinematographer; a way of honing the technical
foundation of the craft, so that the art can come later. It seemed like an
“apprenticeship”, much as the old focus pullers became second unit
cameramen, to eventually move up to first units, then perhaps aspire to
become a cinematographer one day…</p>

<p>The landscape, mostly due to the explosion of low-cost cinematography
(fueled primarily by DSLR cinematography), has been shifting away from that
old model. Most projects have one, perhaps two camera operators – and the
primary camera operator is usually the cinematographer/DP. Many projects
don’t even <em>have</em> a second camera operator – it simply isn’t required.</p>

<p>Ultimately, it depends what your plans and/or revenue model is.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you want to learn more about how to get your equipment to perform
the way you want it to perform, you may do well working as a camera
operator with a seasoned cinematographer, rather than holding out for
a DP position on a project.</li>
  <li>If you want to make a living behind a camera, you can’t really differentiate
between cinematography and camera operator work – at least as long as
you want to keep a steady revenue stream up. Even the best cinematographers
can moonlight as strict “camera operators” when the pay is right.</li>
  <li>If you want to work in a lower pressure environment, you might want to
be a camera operator. Cinematographers are responsible for everything
visual which goes on in a project, and it can be a lot of stress.</li>
  <li>If you feel passionate enough about a project to want to be involved at
any cost, you might sign on as a camera operator.</li>
</ul>

<p>Even though there’s a lot of competition for certain spots on certain
projects, we’re all on the same team; we all (for the most part) are
interested in shooting great footage, and many of us are concerned about
creating enduring works of art, wherever possible. We all have great
potential for growth, so whatever your career and job choice, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prime Lenses and Proper Depth of Field]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/prime-lenses-and-proper-depth-of-field/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T13:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/prime-lenses-and-proper-depth-of-field</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Depth of field is a massively misunderstood “side effect” of iris size, and
an ultimately useful storytelling tool (when used properly).</p>

<p>DSLR photography has spawned a large group of cinematographers who are
dealing with largely light-insensitive camera sensors (usually producing
fairly unacceptable noise when used at greater sensitivies than ISO 800).
This has created a need for “fast” lenses, which are lenses which have very
large maximum apertures, featuring maximum f-stop ratings like f/2.0, f/1.8,
and even f/1.4 (there are even some <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/news/2013/08/06/kubrick-s-f-0-7-lenses-now-available-for-rent-but-start-saving-up">f/0.7 lenses</a> out there, but I’m
sticking to the realm of affordable DSLR cinematography, at the moment).
Using firmware like <a href="http://magiclantern.fm/">Magic Lantern</a> allows us to use
focus peaking to exploit manual-focus and non-EF mount lenses (for those
Canon-philes among us), to bring down the effective cost of shooting “fast”
lenses. I have some M42 “Pentax screw-mount” lenses which open to f/2.8 –
acquired for less than 10 USD each, plus a 7 USD <a href="http://amzn.to/1fVPGyf">M42-to-EF adapter ring</a>.
If you’re interested in more information on how to use focus peaking, check
out <a href="http://fstoppers.com/using-magic-lantern-with-focus-peaking-for-free-lensing">how it works</a>.</p>

<p>So, you’ve beaten high-cost DSLR and cinema camera body manufacturers by
using “fast” lenses, right? Well, not so fast, there… You have to consider
the <em>side effect</em> of fast lenses and wide apertures: the shallow depth of
field. It’s both a blessing and a curse; we tend to associate shallow depth
of field images and video with expensive equipment (rightfully so, in most
cases) and a more personal type of image, but those lenses are not
universally usable “wide open”. Many shots come off looking amateurish and
ill-composed, when half of the subjects are out of focus, because they’ve
exceeded the edges of the “sharp” area in the focus range.</p>

<p>(There’s also lack of lens sharpness and chromatic abberation to consider,
which are generally present, to some degree, in the widest aperture settings
available on most lenses. That’s a very intensely technical discussion,
however, and will probably be reserved for a future posting.)</p>

<p>When considering the depth of field you want, consider the subject (or
literal <em>focus</em>) of the shot, and figure out how much of the shot needs to
be in focus to properly tell your story. The depth of field is very
important for exposing the mise-en-scène in the way which best represents
both the explicit visuals and external representation of internal
character development and exposition. If your character needs to “pop”
out of the scenery, a narrow DOF would be perfect – but if they are to
appear as a figurative cog in the machinery of the world, you’re probably
going to be looking for the widest DOF (approaching infinity) as you can
get. When widening the DOF like this, you’ll most likely have to compensate
by boosting the ambient lighting, or adding additional lighting, to
adjust for the decreased light hitting your camera sensor.</p>

<p>There are a number of tools for figuring out the proper DOF for a certain
shot, based on the camera/sensor, lens focal length, and distance to
primary focal point.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/dofjs.html">Web-based DOF calculator</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/android.html">Android calculator</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/iphone.html">iOS calculator</a></li>
</ul>

<p>There are more of them, but if you specify the variables, you can adjust
the aperture f-stop to the widest setting which properly fits the scene
and visuals which you’re attempting to achieve.</p>

<p>Like anything else, this isn’t strictly an instructional A-to-B guide on
how to achieve stunning visuals; it’s simply an attempt to share some of
what I’ve learned, and to help share the knowledge and tools to exploit
your own inner artistic vision. Good luck shooting!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
