<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: remember, no one cares | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/remember-no-one-cares/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-03T23:10:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whom do you root for?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/01/whom-do-you-root-for/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-01T16:38:14-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/01/whom-do-you-root-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend’s son asked me which Superbowl team I would be rooting for during the big game – and I didn’t have a satisfactory answer for him. Team sports have always held a “<a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/10/16/five-case-studies-on-politicization/">red tribe/blue tribe</a>” quality to me, even from a fairly early age. A great deal of that has to do with how we become associated with team sports, among other concepts.</p>

<p>There is a certain <a href="http://www.apa.org/monitor/apr04/beliefs.aspx">genetic component</a> in how certain concepts, particularly belief systems, are transmitted – but studies tend to indicate that our beliefs are, at least, initially drawn from the belief systems of our parents (see: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobo_doll_experiment">1960s Bobo Doll experiment</a>). This means that our initial viewpoints tend to stem from our parents, although it should be noted that some belief systems (when pushed too strongly by parents), result in children <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0007123413000033">rebelling against those same beliefs</a>.</p>

<p>Regardless of all of that, team sports is a bit too – arbitrary – in its fandom. A great deal of knowing which team you’re going to be rooting for is tied up in where you live in proximity to that team. The upshot of this is that if you had been born a hundred miles away from where you were born, there’s a very distinct chance that your favorite sports team would be different. It’s vaguely the same lottery present with religion – if you were born to a family of a different faith than your parents, there’s an overwhelming chance that you would follow that faith instead of whichever faith (or non-theist belief system) you have now. The same can be said for political ideology ; whether primarily by genetics or primarily by learned behavior, we tend to “inherit” these things from our parents (or other primary role models).</p>

<p>Tribes are artificial constructs meant to extend natural family bonds beyond those with close genetic similitude, and the notion is generally thought to predate the modern notion of the Nation-State. The internal workings of tribalism at a sociological level are constantly being challenged by anthropologists and sociologists, but we do have a number of fairly solid theories describing their operation, at the moment.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Patriotism is, fundamentally, a conviction that a particular country is the best in the world because you were born in it - George Bernard Shaw, 1893</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Patriotism is framed as being a larger, more structured version of team fandom – at least, in my supposition. If our fealty is simply based on luck of birth, how much stock should we put into it?</p>

<p>I’m going to round this out with a very simple observation: if it makes you happy (and isn’t hurting other people), there’s probably no reason why you shouldn’t be doing it. If sports fandom is your thing, by all means, don’t let my pseudo-analysis hinder you from enjoying the trials and tribulations of your favorite team. If not, I hope that this will, at least to some degree, help explain why others are so fascinated by their favorite tribe / team / nation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experts vs Relativism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/28/experts-vs-relativism/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-28T05:04:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/28/experts-vs-relativism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the larger search for guidance, justification, or confirmation, we tend to weigh different opinions – especially expert opinions – based on how they relate to our trust “weighting” of them, by association. That being said, there are two, drastically different, models of weighted opinions: experts, or everybody (which can be understood through the concept of “universal relativism”).</p>

<h2 id="what-constitutes-an-expert----education-vs-experience">What constitutes an expert – education vs experience?</h2>

<p>Experts, with expert opinions, are the preferred mechanism of conferred knowledge in academia. Departing from the trappings of academia for a moment, it can also be asserted that extensive experience also can produce an expert. I personally prefer the latter to the former. Anecdotally, <a href="http://redlinedoc.com/">my father</a> (who is a physician, but not a GP), used to tell me that his functional medical knowledge came primarily from his internship and residency, rather than having been conferred during medical school.</p>

<p>I have referred to the self-taught school of learning as the “<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119217/">Good Will Hunting</a> school of education”, referencing the Will Hunting character’s iconic line about education:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You wasted $150,000 on an education you coulda got (sic) for $1.50 in late charges at the library.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The role of seasoned educators in higher education should not be undervalued, nor should all skill-sets or educational concepts be learned exclusively or primarily through experience rather than through a traditional learning environment.</p>

<p>A distinction could be said to be made between hard and soft sciences (and which was pointed out by my good friend and colleague Chris), in that soft sciences are generally predicated on observations and theories which are not primarily verifiable (for the most part). Hard sciences have the benefit of verifiable and reproducible results, which allow them to be absorbed without a particular mentor. Soft sciences rely heavily on particular ideologies which, although they can be absorbed strictly through self-guided research, lend themselves to educational institution ideologues and their inherent personal biases.</p>

<h2 id="why-almost-universal-relativism">Why “almost universal relativism”?</h2>

<p>Relativism, being the point of view that there is no absolute truth or validity, is generally framed around the idea of “moral relativism” – having to do with ethics. I use the phrase “universal relativism”, possibly incorrectly, to describe a more intellectual form of relativism; the idea that we all have equally valid opinions, with equal truth and validity behind them.</p>

<p>I personally abhor this point of view, because it’s pretty easily dismissed unless a purely metaphysical vantage point is taken. Put in a more easily digestible way: <strong>Universal relativism only works if the world is only seen as a construct of our individual imaginations and views.</strong> If something cannot be perceived, does that mean that it does not exist? Possibly, according to that particular mode of thinking.</p>

<p>As far as disproving the idea that all theories and vantage points have equal validity behind them, take the example of the makeup of <em>The Moon</em>. If someone had the view that it was made of green cheese, it would not, in any way, affect the actual makeup of the moon, nor would it possess the same absolute validity which could be assessed through observation and analysis of the physical evidence showing the actual makeup. That’s a simple, albeit silly, example of a viewpoint which is not as equally true or valid as another.</p>

<h2 id="dunning-kruger-effect">Dunning-Kruger Effect</h2>

<p>What sort of a write-up would this be if I didn’t at least mention the Dunning-Kruger Effect?</p>

<p>We’re bad at self-assessment. It’s a cognitive bias that has the backing of some <a href="http://psycnet.apa.org/index.cfm?fa=search.displayRecord&amp;id=3282CD93-C8F8-1D4B-0757-5027602AE6AC&amp;resultID=11&amp;page=1&amp;dbTab=pa&amp;search=true">scientific studies</a> to show that, to varying degrees, we tend to either under or over estimate our skill levels, as well as the skill levels of those around us. This would, predictably, create issues in identifying and trusting the opinions of those who would theoretically be more skilled than we are.</p>

<h2 id="why-we-cant-have-it-both-ways-a-paradox">Why we can’t have it both ways (a paradox)</h2>

<p>Universal relativism and a system of experts are mutually impossible. They simply cannot co-exist within a person’s framework for judging expertise. This can be logically broken down like this:</p>

<p>1) Relativism believes that everyone’s opinions and observations have equal weight.
2) A system of experts believes that certain people have acquired a superior skill set or knowledge base than those around them.
3) Opinions and observations hold the same essential position as learned skills and knowledge, using the patterns established by relativism. (The Dunning-Kruger Effect would indicate that those with a certain belief in their own knowledge and skill will tend to over-estimate them against other people.)
4) A hierarchy of expertise cannot, therefore, exist in a system where everyone’s opinions and truths are considered equally valid.</p>

<h2 id="confirmation-bias-or-why-we-want-to-have-it-both-ways">Confirmation bias, or why we want to have it both ways</h2>

<p>Another, potentially more insidious, bias is <strong>confirmation bias</strong>. It’s an innate tendency we all share to favor information which confirms our own opinions, truths, et cetera – and it’s one of the reasons why relativism (or, at least, some subsets of it) are exceptionally popular. It means that we’re always right, all the time. Even if someone else is actually right, we’re still right, because our own opinions and truths would hold the same value as theirs.</p>

<p>But wait – we also like appealing to experts. There’s a logical fallacy called <strong>appeal to authority</strong>, which involves using a position of expertise or authority to disprove or dismiss someone else’s opinions and truths. For this authority to exist, we have to sanction, in some small way, a system of experts. We will however tend to ignore them when they disagree with our conclusions.</p>

<p>Or, to pervert an old idiomatic proverb, we want to have our cake and eat it too.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>There has to be some take-away from all of this ; how else are we to learn if we’re so distinctly predisposed to be terrible at accepting new points of view, or even judging the validity of those hierarchies of experts out there?</p>

<p>I tend towards the idea of a repeatable, independently verifiable methodology – although, that tends to fall apart outside of the hard sciences.</p>

<p>I suppose that, if you’re driven to universal relativism, stay there. Don’t accept hierarchies of experts, and continue to assume that everyone’s opinions are equally valid. If you believe in hierarchies of experts, make sure you take a step back and attempt to objectively examine the schools of thinking of which you are an acolyte.</p>

<p>There isn’t an absolute truth for everything, and we’re not very good at being objective – but with a little bit of work, we can try to see a little more of the other sides of problems, and perhaps bring ourselves a little needed perspective.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/04/02/migrating-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-02T08:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/04/02/migrating-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After much hemming, hawing, and gnashing of teeth, I’m migrating my years of sporadic blogging from <a href="http://wordpress.org/">Wordpress</a> to <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>. It seems to integrate a little bit better with both my “command line ethos” and my workflow. I’m sure (for anyone keeping track) that there are probably going to be some weird formatting issues, potentially broken pages, and other incidences of oddness in some places. Please excuse the mess, we’re remodeling.</p>

<p>In addition to the move, I’m trying to move away from blog entries regarding political events – not because I should be worried about potential ramifications for my professional/public life – but rather because there’s only a certain amount of pissing into the wind that a man can do before he gets tired of having a mouthful of piss. That’s not to say that there won’t be <em>any</em> political stuff here, but there’s going to be far less.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Election 2012 Summary]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2012/11/06/election-2012-summary/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2012/11/06/election-2012-summary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s the day before the 2012 Presidental Election. I’m disappointed, as usual, by the choice of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">far right</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barack_Obama">center right</a> “choices” that we have. I again am forced into the decision of either voting for the preferable third party candidate, with whom I share views on the vast majority of issues (<a href="http://www.jillstein.org/">Dr. Jill Stein</a>, for anyone wondering — I still think Ron Paul is a complete crankcase, and Gary Johnson is way too “fuck Federalism” for my taste) and effectively helping to elect an out-of-touch sociopathic plutocrat butt-munch, or vote the “lesser of two evils” and probably end up with a Democrat who is going to “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/obama-says-hell-renew-pursuit-of-grand-bargain-offering-specifics-on-agenda/2012/10/24/0e2b843c-1e0e-11e2-9cd5-b55c38388962_story.html">Grand Bargain</a>” away the Great Society programs. All of that being said, I have a few serious issues with this election cycle.</p>

<p><em>Throwing bullshit at the wall to see what sticks / low information idiots destroy America.</em> Don’t bother reading Politifact. Their attempt to be “non partisan” by rating the attempt to replace Medicare with a privatized program (effectively ending the program as we know it) as “half true” (and then upgrading to “<a href="http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/statements/2012/oct/03/barack-obama/obama-says-romney-wants-turn-medicare-voucher-prog/">mostly true</a>“, after rounds of pounding), simply because the word “voucher” was used to describe the festering husk of Medicare after it had been dessicated by years of crap like “Medicare Advantage” and Governor Rick Scott’s <a href="http://www.wusf.usf.edu/news/2010/06/18/whistleblowers_say_rick_scott_knew_about_medicare_fraud">side ventures into fraud</a>, then given out as coupons/vouchers to purchase overpriced and underregulated private insurance. You know, after “Obamacare is repealed” and the jackholes in the insurance industry can go back to fucking people in any way they see fit — government regulation and oversight is apparently for places like Europe, Canada — hell, anywhere but here. But I digress.</p>

<p>The whole idea that Romney had been running a campaign which has profited greatly by effectively lying about the other guy — wholesale, mind you, not the usual half-truths we see from Presidental campaigns in the United States — is pretty sickening. A friend who works in the Connecticut prison system recently mentioned that he was going to vote for Romney because “Obamacare is going to make me pay more for my health insurance; and I have to look out for myself”. Some jackasses at work told him this, and he believed it — even though it’s patently and demonstrably false. As I saw somewhere on the interwebs “Obama isn’t a brown skinned guy who gives out free healthcare and hates rich people — you’re thinking of Jesus.” People apparently will follow their rampant self-interest, Grover-Norquist-style, even if it means screwing the shit out of everyone else. Not cool, America, not cool.</p>

<p><em>Voting for a third party candidate isn’t going to change squat, even if they won.</em> I can’t stress this enough. Enough of the country lives in some weird mix of medieval England and the 1950s, and votes as a bloc for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rick_Santorum">loudest, crassest bible-thumper</a> in any election cycle (think of Dubya, who shouldn’t have been able to win an election cycle against a warm jar of Russian piss, had the contest been set up that way). Look, we’re going to have tea-hadist, teanderthals, whatever you want to call them, in the House of Representatives and the Senate. Low information, Dunning-Kruger-Effect proving, “self made” government haters, who don’t believe in science, and sure as hell don’t believe in the government to which they have been elected. Nothing is going to go well that way — and it’s a pretty good indictment of why both direct and representative democracy do not function well in a country full of ill informed voters. Voters, to which “intellectualism” is an anathema to their way of life. I don’t want a President or Representative with whom I can drink a can of local alcoholic swill — I want someone who is smarter than I am; someone who is intellectually invested in leading. I want someone who actually gives a half a fuck about *everyone*, not just the guys with money or the guys who are the loudest at the moment. A Green Party president, however nice, is only one leg of the trifecta of United States government. They might be able to stop some wars, and perhaps appoint less awful corporatists to the Supreme Court — but they don’t make the laws around here. Educate, educate, educate — that’s the only way out of this shit-hole. (Also, don’t even think about “Charter Schools”. They’re not only *not* a panacea, but by effectively removing the top tier of students and privatizing education, we’re removing the only trappings of equality which the lower end of the socioeconomic chain has…)</p>

<p><em>Voter disenfranchisement under the guise of “voter fraud”.</em> I don’t even need to really go into this, since so many other people have done it so well. I’ll lazy link to <a href="http://bobcesca.com/blog-archives/2012/11/six-hour-lines-and-voter-suppression-in-florida-and-ohio.html">Bob Cesca</a>, the <a href="http://www.aclu.org/voter-suppression-america">ACLU</a>, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/10/25/how_gop_voter_suppression_could_win_florida_and_the_white_house_for_romney/">Salon</a>, and <a href="http://www.motherjones.com/politics/2012/11/timeline-history-voter-suppression">Mother Jones</a>. I would find something a bit more right-leaning, but they’re still bitching about a statistically irrelevant excuse for disenfranchising <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-250_162-57511312/study-voter-id-law-would-exclude-up-to-700000-young-minorities/">primarily minority voters</a> — which apparently <a href="http://www.examiner.com/article/video-republicans-caught-committing-voter-fraud-only-registering-romney-voters">those same asshats have been perpetrating</a>. Stay classy, conservatives.</p>

<p><em>Military industrial complex leg-humping time.</em> We need to find out who is going to <a href="http://www.iraqbodycount.org/">bomb more dark people into pits in the sand</a>, and fast! Candidates are now trying to <a href="http://www.tonysrants.com/military/breaking-five-hundred-generals-and-admirals-endorse-mitt-romney/">rack up military endorsements</a> as fast as they can. This does not bode well for not killing people unnecessarily, as you can probably guess. I mean, when you frame the “debate” (which there really isn’t, at this point) as “keeping us safe”, you already know what the outcome is going to be, since both major political parties are completely in the tank for <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2010/mar/28/opinion/la-oe-hayden28-2010mar28">The Long War</a>. We haven’t been attacked by another country since Pearl Harbor, guys. And, in case you didn’t notice, the terrorists who flew planes into our buildings did so primarily because <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motives_for_the_September_11_attacks">we’ve been dicking with their countries for years</a>. Noam Chomsky got his <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/fighting_words/2011/05/chomskys_follies.html">ass chewed out by Chris Hitchens</a> for saying just that (not that I agree with Chris Hitchens’s views on the Iraq War, it’s just interesting that he thought it worthy of a piece in Slate). Honestly, I think Chomsky is a bit more knowledgeable and trustworthy on the subject than Hitchens — but again, I digress.</p>

<p><em>Trying to discredit math.</em> I wish I were kidding about this, since it is vaguely reminiscent of the same anti-intellectualism sentiment portrayed by Dick Nixon, and shows that the vast majority of people like to live in some sort of weird bubble. You know, the kind where “you’re for us, or you’re a fucking idiot”. Nate Silver, who has been <a href="http://www.advocate.com/politics/media/2012/10/28/nate-silver-laughs-accusation-he-too-effeminate-analyze-polls">vilified by Romney bootlickers for giving the answers straight from the math</a> demonstrates the bizarre “bubble world” that the GOP candidate has around him, reminiscent of the same “information bubble” of the less-than-venerable George W Bush.</p>

<p><em>Redefining what it means to be a “businessman”.</em> Have you ever seen the movie “<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102609/">Other People’s Money</a>“? Take away the empathy and life lessons learned, and you’ve got Willard Romney. “Leveraged buyouts”, especially when accomplished with a few million dollars of seed capital from your old man, have squat to do with the Conservative ideal of the job creator wunderkind. Seriously. Leveraged buyouts involve using other people’s money to purchase a controlling instance in a functional company, and saddle it with the burden of paying not only the original capital for its own takeover back, but also sucking the marrow of the company out to pay yourself a hefty sum for the pleasure of having downsized and screwed the hell out of that same company. It may be business (vulture capitalism at its very “best”), but it’s certainly not “business experience” in any relevant context to a nation’s economy, assuming that you were willing to accept the framing that a government should be run like a business, which it shouldn’t. (Quick rundown of that logic: Business’s primary motive is profit, whereas governments have to serve the populace without regard to financial status or profit. Governments also print their own money. It’s not the same thing, guys. It’s like saying that you can be the best train conductor *evar* because you have a driver’s license or learner’s permit.)</p>

<p><em>Rampant self-interest trumping rational societal decisions.</em> Norquist proved this years ago in California; people simply will not vote for things that cost them money, even if it makes society better and enriches the country. I’m not sure if this is a “Boomer generation” thing, or if we’re just turning into selfish, ignorant, navel-gazing fuckwads through cultural inundation. I’ve seen people use the specter of “tax increases” as a reason for voting the GOP party line, even when those supposed “tax increases” aren’t born out by reality. Jeez, if you get your news from a crazy idiot like Glenn Beck (theblaze.com, anyone?), do you really think it’s going to somehow shape your decisions in some sort of informed and non-navel-gazing context? </p>

<p>I’ll end this with a <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=efKguI0NFek">George Carlin quote</a>: “If you’ve got selfish, ignorant citizens, you’re going to get selfish ignorant leaders.” I don’t think I could have said it better, George.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Imaginary Horserace, 2012 Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2012/11/05/imaginary-horserace-2012-edition/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2012/11/05/imaginary-horserace-2012-edition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, the 2012 United States Presidental Election is effectively between Barack Obama and Willard “Mitt” Romney. I don’t think I can stress how little this registers on my “give-a-fuck-o-meter”, although I have been inundated by dire prognostications regarding the end of our “American Way of Life ™” (whatever that is) and a lot of scare-tactic advertising campaigns unleashed by the virtually unlimited flow of corporate money (or as Constitutional Originalist fuckwads like Antonin Scalia would say, “free speech”) into the current election cycle.</p>

<p>The problem is, there <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.blogs.nytimes.com/">isn’t really a horse race to be had</a>. When FiveThirtyEight is pushing a 70 percent chance of a fairly popular incumbent president retaining a seat, one could wonder how the news media cycle could possibly make anything of it. As of this weekend, the Budgetary Wunderkind Paul Ryan has joined Mitt Romney’s unexciting ticket — and it doesn’t make any damn difference. Mittens ain’t winning this election, folks. We can show as many “real ‘muricans” as we can cram on the television, spitting opinions out of both sides of their figurative asses, but it’s not going to affect the outcome of this election. Well, unless the entire point of this chest-beating is going to be making a Mitt Romney victory seem plausible enough so that, if the need arises, disenfranchising voters can be made to seem to more naturally produce a victory for a statistical underdog. You know, if I were into conspiracy theories.</p>

<p>As far as policies go, I don’t agree with any of the Republican candidates’ policies. That’s my general disclosure: I don’t believe dry humping stacks of Atlas Shrugged is going to magically cure the economy, and I don’t believe that dropping government involvement in economics and allowing self regulation will somehow stimulate anything other than the same massive greed and theft we’ve seen already. However, for the most part, both parties are pretty closely aligned on most of the substantial issues.</p>

<p><em>Both parties are going to continue stacking bodies in other countries in wars we don’t belong in, and are going to continue funding the military at bank-busting levels.</em></p>

<p><em>Both parties are going to eschew any audit of the Federal Reserve</em> (yeah, yeah, I know, Ron Paul and I coincide on something — even a broken crackpot is right once a day) <em>or any prosecution of the fuckers who blew up the global economy for their own person gain.</em> (If you don’t believe me on that one, check out Bill Black’s take on it. They’ve done bad, criminally prosecutable things. Obama won’t prosecute because he’s scared that he’ll appear to be discouraging “business”, and Mittens won’t touch them because his business ethics and interests are pretty closely aligned with those jackals.)</p>

<p><em>Both parties are going to continue pushing “tax cuts” as economic stimulus.</em> They aren’t, at least not *lasting* economic stimulus. If we gave a shit about decreasing unemployment or “job creation”, we would be pushing another WPA, not giving handjobs to banksters.</p>

<p><em>Both parties will get rid of Medicare and Social Security.</em> They may not talk about it, but both are going to do it, eventually. Simpson-Bowles was commissioned by the *Obama* administration, and Mittens has made the Paul Ryan budgetary plan of voucher-izing (read: privatizing) Social Security and Medicare a major plank of his campaign. Apparently, “very serious” people want you to fucking do everything on your own, because they don’t believe you’re anything but a Randian moocher….</p>

<p>All they have for differences, at least in the running of their campaigns, are wedge issues. One supports abortion rights, another doesn’t. One is into allowing religious exemptions to health coverage, another isn’t. One is into the DREAM Act, one has a “nuanced” position (or whatever he’s decided his position is today — I don’t think the polls from “real ‘muricans” have come in yet today).</p>

<p>We’re getting the Status Quo, folks. We never had a damn chance, either; both establishment parties are owned by the same basic money sources, and you’d better believe that they’re getting their money’s worth.</p>

<p>Before anyone accuses me of leaving out Senator Ron Paul: <a href="http://dissentingjustice.blogspot.com/2011/08/five-reasons-why-ron-paul-should-never.html">he’s a fucking crank</a>. <a href="http://world.std.com/~mhuben/libindex.html">Libertarianism is a fucking crank “philosophy”</a>, and his bullshit disregard for other people, in the guise of individualism, is going to hurt more people than it helps. <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/05/earth-to-libertarians-private-parties-have-coercive-power-too.html">Government isn’t the only coercive force</a>, people. More importantly, if you’re fine with state government but hate the federal government — we tried that “exceptionally limited Federal Government” thing with the Articles of Confederation. It failed pretty spectacularly, so stop asking for a do-over, please.</p>

<p>The current paradigm, being pushed by the so-called “right” and “centrist right”, is that people don’t deserve anything other than what they “earn”. It’s an interesting wet-dream, which pays homage to the fraudulent concept of the meritocracy. If you’ve been paying attention for the last 20 years, we don’t have a meritocracy. Those who do well by others and play by the rules do *not* finish first, but those willing to loot, pillage, and burn — they are our new *Gods*. We deify CEOs, in the vain hope that we, too, may ascend to the Olympian summits with them, to enjoy the fruits of our Job Creator mojo. Honestly, I’m not sure whether the people pushing this fanticrap (a mixture of fantasy and crap, for the uninitiated) believe it, making them fools, or are using it to get ahead, making them scoundrels; regardless, if you hear someone trying to spread this particular Gospel of Supply Side Economics, try to make sure they end up on the outer side of your front door.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
