<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: photography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-27T15:19:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fine Line Between Confidence and Hubris]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T15:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to make sense of two necessarily contrary positions in regard to skill, art, and aesthetics. This is something of which I’ve been trying to make sense for quite some time.</p>

<h2 id="aesthetics-technique-and-intent">Aesthetics, Technique, and Intent</h2>

<p>The fundamental balance of aesthetics in any art-form is, in my supposition, the balance between the personal sense and the general public sense. This is somewhat necessitated by a very strange mechanism – that of our inherent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">inability to accurately self-assess</a> our own skills and works. I would secondarily posit that art is effectively a combination of <strong>technique</strong> (skill) and <strong>intent</strong>. (Some have additionally added <strong>context</strong> to that, but I’m going to put that aside as an adjunct of intent for now.)</p>

<p>Technique is teachable. Technique is learnable (depending on the amount of time put in, internal aptitudes, etc). Technique is something which, to one degree or another, is somewhat quantifiable. A great deal of education in the arts is devoted to attempting to teach classical techniques, if only for the sake of eventually learning which ones can be accepted and which ones can be disregarded.</p>

<p>Intent, on the other hand, is a really hairy beast. It is <strong>not</strong> able to be deterministically divined from a work in a vacuum. Even more frustrating is that it can be broken into <strong>perceived intent</strong> (how we internalize what we’ve seen, heard, and experienced), and <strong>original intent</strong> (how the artist actually originally intended the art to be consumed). But wait – the original intent can further be broken into <strong>original intent</strong> and <strong>revisionist intent</strong>, where the artist retro-fits an original intent onto a piece for one reason or another – even though it was not originally present in the design and execution phases. (My personal belief is that this is done primary for reasons dealing with popularity, but I don’t have any data to back this up.)</p>

<p>If art is a combination of these two things, how can art be “judged” by others if the original artist’s intent cannot be accurately determined? Should it be consumed and rated based on the perceived intent, which is completely subjective based on the person consuming it?</p>

<h2 id="coming-back-to-confidence-and-hubris">Coming back to Confidence and Hubris</h2>

<p>The next logical question in the context of this reading would be “what does this have to do with the difference between confidence and hubris?”</p>

<p>Confidence is somewhat necessary in the artistic process, as it helps shape the intent of the work. If we have no belief or confidence in what we are doing, it is very difficult to move forward with doing it.</p>

<p>Technique, however, requires a certain amount of humble nature to learn and master. If we believe that we have nothing else to learn, we stop learning. As the source material from Dunning-Kruger concludes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the miscalibration of the incompetent stems from an error about the self, whereas the miscalibration of the highly competent stems from an error about others</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, hubris is a base requirement for successful intent, as we need to believe that what we are doing has some sort of artistic merit, both to ourselves and for the external validation provided by others. We would need to be able to weather the concerns of others to forge our own artistic path.</p>

<p>But technique requires a humility which contradicts that hubris, for if we do not know our place in the grand spectrum of abilities, how can we ever hope to know when we can improve, or how to improve?</p>

<h2 id="societal-homogenization">Societal Homogenization</h2>

<p>To a degree, all artists who come in contact with other art or other artists will experience a level of homogenization of their work. The Millenial generation, replete with Instagram pictures, <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/doge">Doge-level memes</a>, and an inflated sense of self (unencumbered by a history of perceived failures) seem to experience this effect at a greater magnitude than seen before. I’m not sure if this is due to the replicating effect of social networking, an increased population size (similar to the compounding effect of scientific discoveries with larger populations), or some other ancillary effect with which I’m unfamiliar.</p>

<p>I mention societal homogenization of art-forms because it leads me to the next question…</p>

<h2 id="is-it-me-or-is-it-the-world">Is it me, or is it the world?</h2>

<p>The question that I ask is “Is it me, or is it the world?”</p>

<p>If my aesthetic is different than the vast popular aesthetic, am I wrong, or does society at large just have bad taste? I can’t answer that question. If aesthetics are the domain of popular opinion, I’m wrong, and confidence needs to be cut back in favor of humility and a level of homogenization. If original intent is the important part of the equation, I should be forging ahead, allowing confidence (and eventually hubris) to shape the end-products of artistic labor.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do">What do you do?</h2>

<p>I’ve struggled with this – and due to the paradoxical nature of the problem, the only solution I can offer is to make the decision about how to proceed with your art based on <em>your</em> intent. If you’re trying to make a living from your art, primarily, go for the homogenization – you will see better returns from a more commercially viable product. If you’re trying to make “better art”, go your own way – either you will create something which will transcend you or you won’t, but at least you will have made art which is yours.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The danger of the shortcut mentality]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T13:00:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In “<a href="/2013/06/28/skill-in-the-age-of-instagram/">Skill in the Age of Instagram</a>”, I had opined about the lost value of skill sets, and how the modern approach to skills is to “approximate” them with shortcuts like Instagram, Autotune, and Photoshop.</p>

<p>Even though these tools offer the quickest and shortest “path” to the immediate goal, being your current project, they retard your potential growth by limiting your skills and knowledge about what you’re doing. If the pseudo-magic time-saving software is taken away (or encounters a limitation), how will you continue to be able to function without it?</p>

<h2 id="in-cinematography">In cinematography</h2>

<p>Cinematography is rife with this kind of intellectual laziness, as all creative fields have a tendency to be. A few of the places I’ve seen this have been:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Cameras</strong>. If you haven’t met a single cinematographer who has lamented that s/he is being held back by his/her rig, you haven’t gotten out very much. I call crap on that argument, mainly because of fine work like <a href="http://erbpfilm.com/film/upstreamcolor">Shane Carruth’s “Upstream Color”</a>. Learn to use what you’ve got, rather than pining for something better / different.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Color correction and grading</strong>. Virtually every amateur forum on color correction and grading is full of people asking where they can get a “one size fits all” <a href="http://nofilmschool.com/2011/05/what-is-a-look-up-table-lut-anyway">LUT</a> which will make their footage look “like Hollywood”. If there was such a thing, the entire industry of color grading specialists would just be wasting their time and skills. There’s even an “Instagram” of sorts for color grading – Magic Bullet Looks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus</strong>. I’m still surprised at the number of people who complain that cameras do not do the focusing work <em>for</em> them. (It’s easier to remind them that, much like other electronics, more expensive things have fewer bells and whistles – and autofocus is a terrible, terrible idea.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Lighting</strong>. As soon as low light cameras capable of cine work, like the A7s, came out, people came crawling out of the woodwork, happy that they no longer would have to worry about learning to light a scene. Putting aside the relative noisiness of the sensors, low light / no light <em>still</em> does not look like actual lit footage.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Falling into these thought pattern “traps” may seem easier at first, but following this “shortcut mentality” doesn’t may off in the long game.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<p>I’m not sure. I have previously said that I believed intellectual laziness or possibly a culture obsessed with instant gratification could be blamed for attempting to take the easy way out. Upon further observation, I cannot isolate a single cause behind the widespread acceptance of these tools and shortcuts, but I’ll iterate through possible causes.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Illusory superiority</strong>. We aren’t very good at figuring out how good or bad we are at something (the concept of illusory superiority contends that we usually overestimate our skill level, and the Dunning-Kruger effect also stipulates that we will eventually <em>under</em>-estimate our skill level, once we’ve gotten past a certain point). It’s one of the reasons why 90% of drivers believe that they’re in the top 10% of the skill curve – and also could help explain why using some of the aforementioned tools has become so prevalent. If we believe we’re in the top percentiles of a skill set, we’ll also believe that whatever we do (as part of our “process”) is, and must be, inherently correct. This can be seen by the inability of many Instagram filter users to understand why their tool is an “easy way out”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Instant gratification</strong>. Our culture, especially the now-pervasive “<a href="http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2014/03/07/millennials-in-adulthood/">millenial generation</a>”, which has come into cultural power with a shorter-than-ever attention span and a lack of any understanding of their own skill levels, thanks to a society hell-bent on issuing participation awards to everyone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Intellectual laziness</strong>. Increasingly, people seem to be less interested in <em>how</em> something works, and simply interested <em>that</em> it works.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>“Keeping up with the Joneses”</strong>. There is a look and feel “arms race”, which closely parallels the <a href="http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/sep11/articles/loudness.htm">loudness war</a>, in that photographers and cinematographers are pressed to try to replicate the look and feel of their Instagrammified and Photoshopped brethren.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The social disease</strong>. No, not “the herp”; the disease of social networking. A seemingly endless desire for likes, “+1”s, shares, and every other type of social networking accolades, has been a driving force in recent years; “<a href="http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/abs/10.1089/cpb.2009.0003">self-status seeking</a>” is one of the primary goals of those who engage in social networking. In efforts to garner the esteem of “friends” and “contacts” on these social networks, users are adopting the lowest common denominator, in many cases, to attempt to appeal to the greatest number of followers. </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-the-solution">What’s the solution?</h2>

<p>This is where I’m at a bit of a loss. I’d like to believe that, given time, those who possess the requisite skills of the trade will advance, simply by virtue of having learned to ply their skills more effectively, and those who use “skill approximation” software will drop off, or will continue to produce mediocre or cookie-cutter output.</p>

<p>That being said, it didn’t happen that way with pitch-correction software. Musical artists no longer have to be able to sing in tune (although, you could point at musicians like Bob Dylan to say “they never had to be able to”, but I digress) to be able to rise to the top of the pop music charts, and photographers don’t have to be able to take a clean picture to be able to produce a cover image for a magazine. The exact opposite, in fact, is expected from professional photographers – knowledge of manipulation tools is <em>expected</em>, and some photographers are becoming well known through their Instagram-filtered images.</p>

<p><em>(As an aside, even though I do have an <a href="http://instagram.com/jbuchbinderphotos">Instagram account</a>, I do tag my photos with <strong>#nofilter</strong> and <strong>#noprocessing</strong> to indicate that I do not manipulate them, apart from the forced square ratio imposed by Instagram.)</em></p>

<p>I can only recommend the long road – and I’m going to end this post with a quote that, while it may seem to be a bit cliché, is perfectly apropos:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Two roads diverged in a wood, and I— /
I took the one less traveled by, /
And that has made all the difference.
- “The Road Not Taken”, Robert Frost</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is even more appropriate that the oft-misconstrued sentiment of Frost’s poem was to lament that he had chosen the more difficult route, not to celebrate that he had taken it.</p>

<p>So please, take the long road of learning and discovery, rather than looking for shortcuts ; you’ll be a better, more skilled person for having done so. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Importance of Failure]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/11/the-importance-of-failure/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T20:04:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/11/the-importance-of-failure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Failing is a terrible thing, we are taught. As a result of inherent cognitive biases and our own illusory superiority (look up the <a href="http://www.spring.org.uk/2012/06/the-dunning-kruger-effect-why-the-incompetent-dont-know-theyre-incompetent.php">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>, if you’re curious about this), we believe that we are right the majority of times, that we are more skilled than those around us, and that we have nothing of import to learn from not succeeding.</p>

<p>I’m going to uncharacteristically detour into a quick anecdote. I was attending a film festival a little while ago, and had ended up talking to one of the festival’s organizers. She had asked me about how I got into film, and talked a little bit about some of her own projects. After a while, I mentioned how I learned more from my failures than I did from my successes. She stopped the line of conversion, and said that she didn’t, because she “always” succeeded.</p>

<p>There’s a lesson to be learned from her. If you never fail (or never allow yourself to be put in a situation when you fail, or never accept that you have failed), you aren’t going to be able to examine your process to figure out how you can improve. If we’re at the height of our skill set at the present moment, I view that assessment as a dismal failure; we should always expect that, given time and effort, we should continue to improve as time goes on.</p>

<p>I don’t necessarily <em>hate</em> everything I’ve done in past projects, but can instead view my previous work as evolutionary improvement. Every project I do should be the best work I’ve done <em>so far</em>, and if it isn’t, I should be taking steps to make sure that the next one is.</p>

<h2 id="understanding-failure-and-criticism">Understanding Failure and Criticism</h2>

<p>We do not accept criticism well – especially not as artists. Most of our work is, to some degree, very personal. We then view attacks on our work as attacks on some part of ourselves, and become much more defensive than we should be.</p>

<p><strong>Cognitive bias</strong> is a serious issue with us accepting criticism, or any differing points of view from our own. Without getting into too much detail about the mechanics of cognitive bias, it is important to emphasize the importance of recognizing that we all possess it, to one degree or another.</p>

<p><strong>High expectations</strong> tends to result in a feeling of having failed at a much deeper level than the project at hand. A very insightful person had written (about film festival contests, in particular) that you had to be committed to making the best thing you could, not winning. It may not sound like a lot of inherent difference, but stripping your expectations for a project can allow you to be much more free in your ability to execute that project.</p>

<p><strong>People who criticize or critique can help you.</strong> Every failure which is left without analysis is a missed opportunity. You cannot learn from your missteps and mistakes without looking at them with a critical eye. A third party with less vested interest in you and your project can give you the perspective you need to improve.</p>

<h2 id="post-mortem-analyses">Post Mortem Analyses</h2>

<p>I come from a pretty heavy information technology background, and one of the favorite “failure analysis” tools we tend to use after something breaks is something called a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmortem_documentation">post mortem</a>, which is short for “post mortem documentation”. It involves a rigorous process of analyzing key elements which were responsible for both successful and unsuccessful aspects of a project or event.</p>

<p>For example, I performed both a post mortem on our <a href="/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/">2014 48 Hour Boston Festival project</a>, which documented some of the things I learned about working with a new camera body, as well as working under tight time constraints, and a post mortem on our <a href="/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project/">2014 48 Hour Providence Horror Festival project</a>, which took home a number of awards, including “Best Film”. Even the analysis of our <strong>successful</strong> project found issues which needed to be addressed before our next project.</p>

<h2 id="your-worst-critic">Your Worst Critic</h2>

<p>… is you (or at least, it should be). You need to be the harshest critic you have.</p>

<p>The rationale I give for this is that you cannot rely on those intrinsically involved in either your professional or personal life, who all have some sort of stake in how well you do something, to be critical enough of what you do. If you can’t expect complete, harsh honesty from those around you – then <em>you</em> are going to have to try to be as harsh as possible with what you’re putting out.</p>

<p><em>(Yes, I’m aware that the younger generation has been indoctrinated, to a certain point, with the notion that everything they do is the best, most awesome, most <strong>EPIC</strong> thing that any human being has ever done – but if you want to succeed artistically, you’ve got to overcome that.)</em></p>

<h2 id="avoid-negativity">Avoid Negativity</h2>

<p>Failure doesn’t have to be a negative thing. Any experience from which we learn a valuable lesson or draw potential improvement from should not be a negative experience. Much like the rest of life, this isn’t the end product of what you’re capable of. It isn’t the last, greatest thing you do – unless, of course, you become disheartened and stop producing things.</p>

<p>Stay positive, learn from your successes <strong>and</strong> your failures – and good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic range]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T11:08:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a photographer or cinematographer, I’m sure you’ve come into contact with
limitations in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range">dynamic range</a>.
I have run into limitations with dynamic range in both the visual and audio
field, since anything that involves “real world” signals is going to 
potentially run up against the ability of the digital mediums on which we
rely to properly store the entire gamut of available analog data that we are
able to perceive with our eyes and ears. To combat the loss of data, computer
scientists and electrical engineers developed the process of dynamic range
compression, which is usually referred to as simple “compression”. This
reduces the gamut of presented information to a digitally representable
format. There is, however, something which is lost – and that is the
original dynamic range ; the amount of variance between the strongest and
weakest signal. In small doses, or when done with finesse, this provides the
ability to produce better sounding and better looking content in the digital
realm. When overused, we see results like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudness_war">loudness war</a>.</p>

<p>I like to explore the more figurative aspects of many technical concepts, to 
which most avid readers of my work would attest. In that vein of ideas, consider
the derivative concept of dynamics as a function of cinematic tension/resolution
and feeling.</p>

<p>Much like a written work, cinematic works generally tend to follow a
“<a href="http://www.dailywritingtips.com/how-to-structure-a-story-the-eight-point-arc/">plot/story arc</a>”,
which have a number of basic stages, even if the presentation, order, and
presence will vary between works. As cinematographers, one of our jobs is to
attempt to portray the basic plot elements, character interactions, and other
potentially metaphysical aspects of the story through the lensing, lighting,
focal points, composition, and method of stabilization and capture we use.
<em>(I’m aware that there are other control points, but forgive me my omissions
for the sake of some semblence of brevity.)</em> For example, for a more
“cinéma vérité” style for a combat or heavy action sequence, a filmmaker could
choose to shoot with less stabilization, looser composition, and less staged
lighting, which would present the audience with the perception that the scene
is far closer to the work of a documentarian than a staged film scene. In
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120815/">Saving Private Ryan</a>, for example, the
battle scenes have a decreased exposure time, resulting in action appearing
far more caustic and (what we believe is) more realistic. This allows the
relative dynamics of the scenes in question to be raised to allow far more
tension and action to be shown, through simple camera work.</p>

<p>The issue with techniques like this begin to manifest themselves when they
begin to flatten the dynamic of a film work through rampant and flagrant
overuse. At some point, cinematographers realized that they could shoot
<em>entire films</em> with these techniques, ostensibly to raise those tension and
action levels to that same high. By doing this, they have effectively
flattened the dynamic range of their works, producing an effectively and
uniformly “loud” work. The questions that you might be asking are “why is this
a bad thing, and why should I care?”</p>

<p>We view things as deltas, or differences. We understand happiness because we
understand sadness, heat because we experience cold, and comfort and
companionship because we can contrast it with loneliness. If the range we are
give to deal with is only the “best parts”, we begin to lose our ability to
appreciate it, and all of those things which should have made it special and
artistic become mere convention. Think about it – if everyone screamed
everything at the same volume, rather than having varying levels of emphasis
and volume, wouldn’t that screaming have lost its impact and importance?</p>

<p>Every technique that you have as a cinematographer or photographer is another
potential tool in your figurative tool box; but just because you have them
doesn’t mean that you have to use one particular one <em>all the time</em>. Handheld
camerawork has its place, and even though modern technology has provided many
methods of stabilizing camera and lens motion, from the steadicam to image
stabilization/vibration reduction lens to three point shoulder rigs, we still
find many cinematographers intentionally introducing shake into their
footage. I wrote an <a href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/06/03/stabilization/">entire essay</a> 
on the importance of stabilization, so I won’t reiterate my grievances here.</p>

<p>It’s important to understand why you’re doing something rather than
simply doing it for convenience or convention. If you’re using a wide open
aperture, are you doing it because you’re having lighting issues, or simply
because you think that everything should be shot with the thinnest DOF
possible? Is there some sort of artistic reason why you chose to shoot with
a 24mm vs a 35mm lens for a particular shot? Are you using a tripod-based
shot rather than a steadicam for a reason? Asking questions and analyzing
your own work, as well as the work of others, is key to artistic growth, as
well as understanding how to use your skillset as a photographer or
cinematographer.</p>

<p>I am, by no means, at the top of the skill grouping for photography <em>or</em>
cinematography. Many of the entries I have authored here are products of
making mistakes, and they are the attempt I am making to keep others from
having to make some of the very same mistakes I have made. Even films and
other work which we don’t particularly like as a whole may have a few 
setups or shots which provide food for thought. So, watch those films with
a critical eye, and hopefully we can all expand our “toolboxes”, as well
as learn how to use them in a more effective manner. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Signal to noise ratio]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T15:06:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To quote the venerable Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Signal-to-noise ratio (often abbreviated SNR or S/N) is a measure used in science and engineering that compares the level of a desired signal to the level of background noise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This has a number of applications in engineering, but it also nicely
encapsulates a basic truth of dealing with equipment, people, and works –
there is always a certain amount of background noise. (For more information
on the concept, check out <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal-to-noise_ratio">this article</a>.)</p>

<p>In an ideal world, all equipment would be flawless and noiseless, everyone
would be wonderful at what they do, and all works would be exceptional 
<em>(don’t mind the inherent logical issue in the statement “all works would be
exceptional”; I was trying to make a point, so please forgive me my
linguistic foibles)</em>. As it so happens, due to a fun little thing called the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Krueger Effect</a>,
we tend to assume that our works are better than they actual are, until we
reach a particular skill level, at which point we start underestimating our
own skill levels. Succinctly put, we’re all terrible at figuring out how good
or bad we are at any particular skill.</p>

<p>This is a real pickle, especially when dealing with other people. With very
few exceptions, we’re going to end up working with other people. This is more
applicable in cinematography than in photography, since there are usually more
people involved with a film production than with a still photo shoot (although
I’m sure there are plenty of instances which would prove me wrong in that
aspect). </p>

<p><em>I’m going to restrict my examples to cinematography projects, to keep
this a bit more manageable and readable.</em></p>

<p>First, look at your potential crew. If you’re dealing with a low-budget indie
shoot, which most of us are, you are either not paying your crew or are paying
them very little money. You’ve already eliminated the possibility of a great
number of highly experienced, educated, and trained people being involved,
simply by eliminating the carrot of a serious payday. It could be additionally
argued that those who do work for a living are not necessarily <em>great</em> at
what they do, but that’s a little tangential to the core of the argument.
Out of those people, you’re generally going to tend to see the talent curve
follow the infamous <a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/NormalDistribution.html">standard/normal distribution curve</a>.
This means some will be utterly atrocious, some will be genius, and the
vast majority will lie somewhere between those two points. The outliers and
bounds will depend on the sample size, but the general concept tends to be
the same, which is that most people are not going to possess genius-level
skills in the vast majority of a sample set.</p>

<p>Second, look at your potential actors/on-screen talent. You’re in the same
boat as you were with the crew – except that a single truly terrible actor
will destroy the illusion you’re trying to create, so you have to hope that
your lower bound is pretty high, otherwise your end product will most likely
suffer. (It should also be said that a really great director has been known
to coax amazing performances out of lackluster talent, but we can’t all be
Stanley Kubrick, Darren Aronofsky, or P.T. Anderson…)</p>

<p>So, what are we to do? We need to start acknowledging that not everything
we’re going to make is going to be the best thing <strong>ever</strong>. It’s an anathema
to the general self-aggrandizing L.A. film culture, but we have to respect
the normal distribution curve – most films will be mediocre, some will be
agonizingly bad, and some will be amazing. The DKE means we’ll always think
that they’re all amazingly wonderful, but we need to be far more critical of
our own works ; at least, if we want to try to produce high-quality output.</p>

<p>We also need to understand that there’s a place for our hubris, as well as
our humility. We cannot grow as filmmakers, photographers, artists, or as
people, until we both appreciate the skill-set we have, while at the same
time understanding the limits of what we have accomplished right now, and
always striving to produce better, become better, and encourage better. We
can’t all be the <strong>best</strong>, but we can all become <strong>better</strong>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
