<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reviews | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/reviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-05T16:32:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CAME-06 Blackmagic Cage Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T21:52:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of setting up the <a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">Blackmagic Production Camera 4K</a>,
I have been trying to put together a solid, fairly low-cost set of
accessories for the camera body.</p>

<p>I became aware of a low-cost Chinese cage for the BMCC/BMPC4K
bodies manufactured by an outfit called
“<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/">Xiamen Came Photographic Equipment Co., Ltd.</a>”,
which are available sporting both top and bottom 15mm rail mounts, 
along with the normal mounting options and handles present with
most cage designs. The cage in question is available for
<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">$198, shipping included, from the manufacturer</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/came-06.jpg" width="289" height="400" title="“CAME-06 Cage”" ></p>

<p>My unit arrived today, via DHL, in a box which seemed almost
Ikea-esque in its packing. First thing to note, which is not
indicated either on the website or the packaging: “some assembly
required”. Secondly – no instructions. Thankfully, the entire
assembly procedure seemed pretty obvious with the provided
Allen wrenches. I noticed that there is a 5/8” mount on the
bottom of the unit (as well as a 1/4”-20 mount) for attaching to
the fluid head or quick-release plate of your choosing. This wasn’t
indicated on the website, but I had my suspicions, which were
thankfully confirmed.</p>

<p>The first major issue I encountered was the lack of four of the
required screws for assembly. Undaunted, I took a quick trip to 
the nearest “home improvement” store, and purchased four
M4-.70 x 12 bolts with phillips heads (in packs of two), which
worked like a charm.</p>

<p>The second slightly annoying issue was that one of the included
30cm 15mm rods was completely unthreaded, so it wouldn’t be
possible to attach it to any other rods, should it need to be
extended. The inclusion of the rods was a bit of a plus, so I
can’t really be too upset about that.</p>

<p>The build quality, once assembled, is quite good. The CAME-06
cage is machined properly, and does not interfere with the
operation of the BMPC4K unit at all, and has enough mount points
to allow me to put handles, arms, and other accessories on it,
which was the secondary purpose of purchasing the cage, after
being able to properly mount the camera on a decent QR plate.</p>

<p>Additionally, it has a set of Hirth joints on either side,
ostensibly for attaching handle mounts. I have no use for them
at the moment, but they seem to be workable.</p>

<p>As the next step up in price is another 70$, and this unit
arrived from China in less than four business days from my
initial order, the annoyance of a $1.00 bolt purchase seems
miniscule, considering the usability of the cage itself. It
isn’t a full system, like the Tilta, Lanparte, and others,
but can be built into a system incrementally.</p>

<p>Verdict: Know what you’re getting yourself into. If you want
a pre-assembled unit, next day shipping, and would rather pay
more money for the lack of inconvenience, you should avoid the
CAME-06. It’s a good deal for the price, however.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

<p><em>Postscript: The manufacturer offered to reimburse me for the
missing screws within a day of me writing to them, so they do
seem to be relatively responsive whenever there is a mixup.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First look at the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T11:17:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was lucky enough to be one of the early people on the waiting list for
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/">Blackmagic Design</a>’s new 4K “Production
Camera” body, which I received last week. It boasts a global shutter, Ultra
4K resolution, ProRes/RAW recording at 1080p/4K resolutions, a super 35mm
sensor, EF mount, and around 12 stops of dynamic range – among other
features. I took it out for a test spin with a fellow cinematographer, just
to see how far I could push the image.</p>

<p>After a test run of “horror” shots with both a Canon EF IS lens and a
manual Rokinon Cine lens, I’ve been learning about the benefits and caveats
of the BMPC body. I’m going to enumerate some of those here.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p><strong>Dynamic Range</strong>. This cooks the hell out of the H.264 image that I’ve been
getting out of the 5D mark III. I can see a full gamut of sky color without losing my subjects – and that’s without additional or reflected light.</p>

<p><strong>Cinematic Quality</strong>. This might have something to do with the depth of the
image, or the amazing amount of data that the body is storing for each frame,
but it is definitely capable of breathtaking quality. I haven’t seen any
artifacts from the footage I’ve taken so far, at either HD or 4K resolution.</p>

<p><strong>Metadata</strong>. The touch screen allows some metadata to be stored for each
clip, including the name of the project, scene number, etc, and allows it to
be edited on the camera body afterwards. It also has a numeric unique numbering
system, with customizable body IDs, which beats the MVI_xxxx.MOV or
MM1Axxxx.MOV scheme from Canon.</p>

<p><strong>Resolve</strong>. The body comes with a <em>full</em> copy of DaVinci Resolve 10. The
only way to truly appreciate it is to actually use it. It essentially puts
Fast Color Corrector and Colorista to shame. The only downside is that it
does take quite a bit longer to run than most of the plugin-based correction
and grading tools, unless you’re willing to invest in either a Red Rocket
card or a bunch of fairly powerful GPU units for your machine. Either way,
it is well worth the time and effort to learn how to use it.</p>

<p><strong>Baked in Zebras and Focus Peaking</strong>. This is less of a revelation for me,
coming from using Magic Lantern, but users of stock Canon bodies don’t know
what they’re missing. You can also acquire these via EVF features – but it
can’t be a bad thing to have those features in the body, as well.</p>

<p><strong>Crop Factor</strong>. It’s about the same crop factor as an APS-C crop, for you
7D and Rebel users, so it’s only a big deal to acclimate if you’re coming
from a full-frame body, like the 5D or 6D. The upshot is that you’re not
going to have to blow a lot of money on extremely wide glass, as would be
required by the BMPCC.</p>

<p><strong>Global Shutter</strong>. If you have a lot of fast motion or quick pans, the lack
of the “jello” effect from rolling shutter is very, very noticeable. This is
one of the prime reasons I purchased this body – and it works as well as
promised.</p>

<p><strong>RAW and ProRes</strong>. (Yes, I know “RAW” isn’t an acronym – I just like it enough to shout it…) No firmware hacks, no playing around, you get ProRes
and RAW footage out of this camera body. As of the time of writing, RAW has
been disabled in the firmware, but I’m expecting an update “any day now”
which will re-enable it. This makes me think twice about having usde H.264
as a codec for so long. And the logarithmic data collection means that all
of that nice dynamic range is intact through the coloring process, so you’re
not losing out there.</p>

<p><strong>EF Mount</strong>. This is a big deal for me, as it keeps me from having to rebuy
all of my glass. All of my M42, EF, and Nikon mount glass will be fine with
this. And as an added bonus, the FD mount glass I have (using the Lens
Doctor EF-FD mount adapter) works fine, and without the vignette I have on
the full-frame sensor.</p>

<h2 id="caveats">Caveats</h2>

<p><strong>Mounting</strong>. The standard 1/4” mount on the bottom of the camera is more
or less useless; the mount plates either shift or scratch the bottom of the
camera – so I ended up using the aluminum handles for my tests. They’re not
particularly useful, considering the weighting of the camera, so I’m waiting
for a cage to arrive. I only considered cages with upper and lower 15mm
rod mounts (for options, of course). These are the ones I found to be the
best choices:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">CAME-06 BMCC Cage</a> - $198 -
The cheapest of the non-ePhoto bunch. It’s just a cage with two 30cm
15mm rods included, so you have to kit the rest of it out, but it’s
potentially the best deal, considering the price jump to the
Wooden Camera or Tilta rigs.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ginirigs-usa.com/bmcc-rigs-and-cages/207-the-bmcc-box-cage.html">Gini Box Cage for BMPC</a> - $269 -
This is a slightly more well-known version of the CAME-06. I don’t know
the difference in build quality, but you’re getting similar type kitting.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/NkeVCv">Wooden Camera Base Kit</a> - $939 -
A well designed, modular kit. Expensive, but potentially worth it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/1lGfAud">Tilta TT-BMC-05</a> - $1570 -
Not necessarily the most affordable, but very well designed. Expect to
pay a hefty markup for their branded accessories. Note that this is an
<em>entire</em> rig, rather than just a base kit, so the extra money is probably
worth it, if you have it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Glossy Screen</strong>. The screen is <em>very</em> reflective. I completely understand
the virtual need for an EVF, otherwise you’re in daguerreotype shade cloth
territory. Because it has SDI outputs, rather than HDMI, it’s probably a
good idea to go with one of the SDI EVFs. Unfortunately, they’re not cheap.
You more or less have the pick of these:</p>

<ul>
  <li><del><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/827800-REG/Cineroid_EVF4MSS_EVF_Metal_with_HD_SDI.html">Cineroid EVF4MSS</a> - $699 - 
The least expensive of the set.</del></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/982065-REG/cineroid_evf4css_electronic_viewfinder.html">Cineroid EVF4CSS</a> - $599 -
I realized that you can’t really use the EVF4MSS, despite its metal
materials, because it only supports up to 1080i, whereas the BMPC4k
requires 1080p.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/894123-REG/Cineroid_EVF4RVW_with_Retina_Display.html">Cineroid EVF4RVW</a> - $995 -
Retina display version of the EVF4CSS. Higher resolution, higher price.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/852192-REG/Alphatron_Broadcast_Electronics_EVF_035W_3G_EVF_035W_3G_Electronic_View_Finder.html">Alphatron EVF-035W-3G</a> - $1395 -
The most expensive, but also most highly reviewed SDI EVF. Shane Hurlbut,
A.S.C., endorsed this particular EVF for use with the BMPC body.</li>
</ul>

<p>Otherwise, you’re in the market for both an EVF and an HDMI-to-SDI converter,
which will tack on an addition few hundred dollars. The temporary budget
solution, in my case, is to use a cloth until the EVF arrives …</p>

<p><strong>Battery Life</strong>. The internal battery isn’t supposed to provide much shoot
time ; virtually everyone using the camera has pointed out that it’s meant
to be a sort of “buffer” between battery changes with an external battery.
I bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9XDal">Switronix PB-70</a> for the body, which
sports a RED-style <a href="http://www.red.com/store/products/accessory-v-mount">V-mount</a>,
as well as a traditional 1/4”-20 mount. It can power the camera alone for
at least four hours, and can additionally power other devices, like EVFs,
HDMI-SDI converters, monitors, follow focus devices, et cetera, by the
extensible power connectors. I have to buy an extra one, so I can have one
charging and one plugged in, but it seems to be a decent solution.</p>

<p>Additionally, it helps to have the battery mounted on the camera assembly,
otherwise it is moderately unweildy. The cheapest mounting solution for
15mm rods I found was the <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9YGao">Ikan BMC-PBK-1-S</a> mount,
which has a small distribution center built into it. It’s slightly redundant,
as the adapter that came with the PB-70 isn’t used, but for the money, it’s
a good buy. It may make sense to buy the slightly more expensive
<a href="http://amzn.to/1hcVO4P">Lanparte plate</a>, which has a number of additional
power outputs.</p>

<p><strong>The Sun</strong>. Besides the glossy screen, the sun tends to blow out the fairly
sensitive BMPC4k sensor. The solution is to use ND filters to reduce the
amount of light coming into the sensor. You might be tempted to increase the
f-stop, but you’ll also be increasing the depth of field to be more
un-cinematic, so the ND filter is a must-have if you find yourself shooting in 
the direct sun, and don’t want to start using high shutter speeds. The
downside is going to come in the “price” category; if you buy cheap ND filters,
it will destroy the quality of the image, so you’re best off sticking with
Tiffen or other brand-name high quality filters. They don’t come particularly
cheap, however.</p>

<p>My recommendation to get started would be the 
<a href="http://amzn.to/1qINli9">Tiffen 77VND</a> 77mm variable neutral density
filter. It handles most of the reduction you’ll need, and at about $150, it’s
far less expensive than a set of 4x4 filter glass.</p>

<h2 id="overall">Overall</h2>

<p>I’m glad I didn’t wait for the Panasonic GH4. I know that’s going to come
off as a little odd, but for the smaller sensor, M4/3 mount and its relatively
insane crop factor, expensive add-on cinema kit, even <em>odder</em> form factor,
H.264 codec, limited dynamic range, and rolling shutter – I feel that the
BMPC4k body is going to do just fine. After all, no camera body makes you
film better, or makes you a better cinematographer. All it can do is allow
you the ability to increase your output quality – if you work for it.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I haven’t posted any video clips yet due to the stabilization issues
I had encountered using the handles alone. I may update the post to include
some stills and short clips with the IS lens.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
