<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: video and animation | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/video-and-animation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-21T19:13:25-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improved Film Noir rendering]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/08/09/improved-film-noir-rendering/"/>
    <updated>2007-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/08/09/improved-film-noir-rendering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to my brother, who is much better with <a href="http://www.goof.com/pcg/marc/gimp.html">gimp-perl</a> than I am, there’s a vastly improved version of the original <strong>RenderFilmNoir.pl</strong> script, available <a href="http://jbuchbinder.com/wp-content/uploads/2007/08/renderfilmnoirpl.gz">here</a>.</p>

<p><em>If you get a chance (shameless plug), please patronize his <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/grendelkhan/">Flickr page</a>, as we does work very hard at being a great photographer …</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Linux support for ADS DVD Xpress DX2]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/07/22/linux-support-for-ads-dvd-xpress-dx2/"/>
    <updated>2007-07-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/07/22/linux-support-for-ads-dvd-xpress-dx2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I take no credit for this at all, but the maintainer of the go7007 linux driver recently added support for the ADS DVD Xpress DX2 (which until recently was conveniently available at Walmart and other retail stores) after I took a picture of the board and asked him *very* nicely. If you get any kind of mileage out of it and decide that you really *have* to send someone money, please send it to him. (To avoid spam, check out the name of the package maintainer.)</p>

<p>I’m posting a copy of this as a kind of public service, since I haven’t seen any upstream releases in a while. Disclaimer that your mileage may very. I have had great luck with this, and have used it to preserve old VHS content … I would also recommend using the <a href="http://colabti.de/convertx/">ffrecord</a> tool, since it has better av sync than the included tools.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Original driver : <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/wis-go7007/">Original Driver on Sourceforge</a></li>
  <li>Patch : <a href="http://home.comcast.net/~bender647/go7007/">Patches for Wischip Go7007 Linux Driver</a></li>
  <li>Site for device : <a href="http://www.adstech.com/products/USBAV-709-EF/intro/USBAV-709_intro.asp?pid=USBAV-709-EF">www.adstech.com</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>UPDATE: As of March 2010, I have posted an updated patch against a newer kernel, available <a href="/2010/03/25/updated-linux-support-for-ads-dvd-xpress-dx2/">here</a>.</strong></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First stopmotion test]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/05/21/first-stopmotion-test/"/>
    <updated>2007-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2007/05/21/first-stopmotion-test</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our first few stopmotion animation tests were successful. As per everything else we do, everything was done with Linux and freely available opensource software. In this case, <a href="http://gphoto.org">gphoto2</a>, imagemagick and mplayer (with ffmpeg thrown in for the .flv conversion for <a href="http://www.youtube.com/">Gootube</a>.</p>

<p>We used my Canon 350D mounted on a tripod with <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/grendelkhan/">Adam’s</a> fixed focal length 135mm lens, with fixed lighting and a green background for eventual <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chroma_key">chromakeying</a>. There was a quick hack involved getting gphoto2 to immediately spit out a photo, instead of trying to logically process it, which was solved with:</p>

<p><code>gphoto2 --set-config "Capture size class"="Full Image" --capture-preview --filename "${OUTPUTFILE}" --force-overwrite</code></p>

<p>(If you choose to try this, remember that whatever format you set your camera to will be the format that it comes out in, so don’t set it to RAW unless you really don’t value your time and want to have to convert it using dcraw.)</p>

<p>The first video can be viewed at .</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
