<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T12:53:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stabilization]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/06/03/stabilization/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-03T14:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/06/03/stabilization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cinematography is, first and foremost, an artform. That being said, I'd like to
also emphasize the caveat that it is a <em>technical</em> artform, and requires a
certain degree of skill and/or technical proficiency to be able to consistently
create artful work.</p>

<p>It could be argued that no, this isn't the case, based solely on the
promulgation of iDevice and consumer-grade video device footage. This type of
footage does not require a modicum of skill, or even practice. In the same way
that it is possible to take a fantastic picture with an Android or iOS device,
it is <em>possible</em> to film usable content with a consumer grade device -- but
not only is it technically limiting (based on the sensors, alone), but it
offers virtually no control over the footage, other than some basic focus and
exposure controls. I would argue that the resulting footage could result in
decent quality output if either a) the operator had an artistic eye, and was
able to use their technology with some skill/proficiency, or b) they were
extremely lucky. However, I digress.</p>

<p>One of the most consistently over-used (and misused, incidentally) is
"<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cin%C3%A9ma_v%C3%A9rit%C3%A9">cinéma vérité</a>". In modern cinematographer parlance, it has come to mean
any footage which resembles that of an unskilled operator, which theoretically
lends an air of realism and observationalism (see any first year film school
book on observational cinema if you're unfamiliar with the concept) to a
piece. It's easier, for example, to immerse a viewer in the world of a
Zombie Apocalypse if they feel as though they could be the one sitting behind
the camera.</p>

<p>This concept has been expanded, partially through the over-saturation of
"<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reality_television">reality television</a>" and "<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Found_footage_(genre)">found footage</a>" genre pieces. Far from
being necessitated by the artistic content of those genres, it is rather a
<a href="http://alifetimeindarkrooms.blogspot.com/2012/02/okay-for-pitys-sake-enough-with-found.html">much more profitable</a>, and can be executed with far crummier equipment
and with a lower technical skill (and ostensibly artistic skill) element. I'm
not going to argue that there is <em>no</em> artistic or technical skill involved
in making either of those genres of television or film, as that would be
foolhardy -- and there are always exceptions to the general rule.</p>

<p>Cinéma vérité is a bit more troubling when used as an excuse for technical
incompetence, lack of technique, or lack of foresight and caring. Most
recently, I've heard shaky and unstabilized footage "explained away" as
being necessitated by the genre of cinéma vérité -- and I'm not buying that
excuse. The majority of footage in film can and should be stabilized, as
well as planned out and executed in a thoughtful manner. That's where the
"art" of cinematography lies; otherwise, you're just a camera jockey, no
matter how fancy your equipment may be. As I've said before, the most
important piece of equipment you own is your eye; everything else just helps
your execution.</p>

<p>There is no excuse for shaky footage in this age of
<a href="http://www.usa.canon.com/cusa/consumer/standard_display/Lens_Advantage_IS">image stabilization systems</a> and <a href="http://littlegreatideas.com/stabilizer/diy/">inexpensive stabilizers</a> which you
can build for a few dollars worth of parts from your local home improvement
store. It adds a lot of cinematographic value and apparent production value
to have more stable shots. I'd prefer not to experience vertigo when watching
a simple walking tracking shot, when possible. One of my favorite "why the
hell did that guy do that" moments was in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0119173/">G.I. Jane</a> (of which I'm not
a fan), where the combat scenes are filmed with what appears to be
<em>intentional</em> camera shake. Far from transporting the viewer into the middle
of the morass, it only conveys confusion and vertigo. Used in more moderate
amounts, it could have proved much more effective, in my opinion.</p>

<p>Even if you're dead-set on the idea of making your next film project using
the "cinéma vérité" genre, there are a few things you should consider before
proceeding unstabilized:</p>

<ol>
<li><em>Does this somehow add to the feel of the film?</em> If you are introducing
camera shake into your cinematography, it should be adding something
tangible, like a certain feeling, to a scene.</li>
<li><em>Am I overusing this?</em> If you're shooting every shot this way, you might
want to reconsider your methodology, unless you're shooting a guerilla
documentary.</li>
<li><em>Am I doing this due to a technical limitation?</em> If you are using
"cinéma vérité" as an excuse for being unable to stabilize your footage,
invest in a cheap stabilization system, IS lenses, a tripod, or any of
the other ways of creating less shaky footage. They're too inexpensive
to let shake stand in the way of otherwise great footage.</li>
</ol>


<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gear vs Skill]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/05/03/gear-vs-skill/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-03T18:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/05/03/gear-vs-skill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I remember a conversation I had with my brother, a few years back. He was
talking about the amount of photographic equipment which he had been dumping
money into purchasing, in the hopes of improving the output from his camera.
After months, if not years, of ordering and collecting equipment, he thought
that <em>one more thing</em> would make some difference. He then had an epiphany,
after viewing a photo of a sunset taken with a $12 disposable camera. The
full comment was:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>It's even more impressive that such a sweet shot was taken with that cheapass Dakota. Every time I get the fool notion into my head that some new and expensive piece of equipment will make me a better photographer, I look at this picture and think, "ah, yes. Right."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I've been thinking about this, as I acquire more cinematography gear. At
which point does it become less about the gear, and more about the wetware?
(Wetware, for those who are unaware, refers to your biological "meat
equipment".)</p>

<p>I'm divided on this point. I do feel that there are certain limitations
inherent in not possessing the proper tool for the job. To put a concrete
example together: if you're using a Canon EOS T2i, your image quality isn't
going to be the same as using a much higher quality camera and sensor
(sticking to the DSLR for this point), but it's theoretically possible to
clean up footage in post-production to <em>approach</em> the type of output which
you could acchieve with a higher-grade sensor and optics. However, if you're
using a standard kit lens on that camera (which probably tops out at an f/3.5
if you're really, really lucky), you're not going to be able to get the
narrow depth-of-field which is associated with most "cinematic" shots. A
<a href="http://www.usa.canon.com/cusa/consumer/products/cameras/ef_lens_lineup/ef_50mm_f_1_8_ii">Canon 50mm f/1.8 "plastic fantasic"</a> lens (on which I've seen far too many
budding cinematographers rely exclusively) is an interesting start, but can't
completely replace a series of really wide open glass primes (sub-f/2.0).</p>

<p>The flip side of the coin is the point which my brother had made; if your
eye sucks, your footage sucks. A lot of the cinematographers (and just plain
old camera operators) with which I've come in contact have bemoaned not
owning a RED ONE, or even a higher grade DSLR camera body -- and assuming
that any decent footage I can pull has everything to do with the equipment
I'm using, and nothing to do with my ability to use said equipment.</p>

<p>Years ago, I remember a gig I had, as a bass player. At the time, I had
brought a <a href="http://www.vintagewashburn.com/Bass/Mercurybass.html">Washburn MB-6</a> (a strange Mercury series instrument with
fantastic action, scored on eBay for very little money), and had finished
a really heart-felt set. Some jackass came up to me and complimented the
instrument.  I figured, from that point on, I would just assume that if
someone commented my instrument, they were implicitly insulting me, by
implying that the instrument provided the quality which they admired, and
that anyone would have been able to do the same, given the chance to play
that instrument.</p>

<p>To sum up, you need a good eye -- more than anything else -- but it's also
important to have the right equipment for the right purpose. Oh, and don't
forget to stablize your shots ...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Heading to the 2013 Boston International Film Festival]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/04/12/heading-to-the-2013-boston-international-film-festival/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-12T13:38:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/blog/2013/04/12/heading-to-the-2013-boston-international-film-festival</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm heading off to the 2013 <a href="http://www.bifilmfestival.com/">Boston International Film Festival</a>
opening ceremonies this evening, where the first short film which I
directed, edited, and shot is being screened/premiered. It's called
"<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2538194/">Heroin; A Love Story</a>", and centers around a friendship in the
midst of addiction in South Boston, and was written by my partner in
filmmaking/crime, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm4492303/">Brian Farmer</a>.</p>

<p>I'm planning on posting some photos and information about the
opening night and film screening as soon as I have them available.</p>

<p><em>I hope to focus some of my upcoming entries on cinematography and
filmmaking topics, rather than my usual fare of semi-coherent
rants about miscellaneous topics, punctuated by obscure technical
postings.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
