<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-12T18:52:50-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boom!]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/12/boom/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-12T08:44:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/12/boom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are quite a few guides, tutorials, videos, and other resources on how to
capture usable boom audio. Most of these have a few usable sections with a
bunch of fluff or useless information accompanying them. This is my attempt to
compile a “quick guide” to capturing usable boom audio, assuming you don’t have
a competent audio engineer in your employ (which I highly recommend). Audio is
half of your deliverable product, as a cinematographer, so you should make sure
that you capture the highest quality audio possible.</p>

<h2 id="proximity-reflections-and-the-inverse-square-law">Proximity, Reflections, and the Inverse Square Law</h2>

<p>Much like light, sound decreases exponentially as you move away from the source
of the sound. One of the first things which you will realize when starting to
capture audio is that it sounds increasingly awful as you move further away –
which can be attributed to two things:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>As you move further away, relative volume decreases</strong>. The background
sounds (“noise floor”, for anyone trying to be technical), consisting of both
the present background noises and any noises introduced in the recording
process, increase when you increase the sensitivity of your recording
equipment. As the source sound becomes quieter, bringing sound up in post
production will also increase that noise. <em>(If anyone says “just record some
room tone”, ignore them; it won’t help you if your source recording is
terrible, since that’s only a solution if you can gate and isolate the
primary sounds in post.)</em> This is one of the compelling reasons why boom
operators are utilized; they allow a recording to be made from closer to
the source.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Reflections</strong>. Light bounces off of everything, as we are taught, and we
have to be careful to deal with those reflections, in terms of color,
brightness, et cetera. Sound does the same thing. It bounces off of surfaces,
but because sound travels slower than light, we <em>notice</em> when it takes a
few milliseconds longer for sound to arrive at our recording device. Even
more insidious, those reflections (which take on different properties and
sounds based on the materials on which they are reflecting) can sound
<em>louder</em> than the original sound – which will make your recording sound
terrible. The closer you are in proximity to the source, the softer the
reflections will be, in comparison to the original sound.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="polarpickup-patterns">Polar/Pickup Patterns</h2>

<p>Not all microphones, or even microphone <em>types</em> are created equal. They all have
different “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microphone#Microphone_polar_patterns">polar patterns</a>”
which describe the areas of sensitivity which the microphones use to pick up
sound. When attempting to capture dialog, for example, an omnidirectional
microphone would be a poor choice, as it picks up sound equally from all
directions, taking away the ability to create greater isolation for the primary
sound source. The most popular boom microphone type is the “shotgun” microphone,
which has a very directed polar pattern, allowing specific isolation of the
sound in question.</p>

<h2 id="levels-peaking-and-limiting">Levels, Peaking, and Limiting</h2>

<p>Getting the recording level <em>just right</em> is one of the more tricky parts of
recording external boom audio. If the audio is too high, “peaking” will occur.
Peaking is the phenomenon which can be heard when the top part of a sinusoidal
wave (which naturally recorded sounds have) becomes squared when the top of the
wave is clipped by hitting the top limit for recording signal. If the audio is
too low, the signal-to-noise ratio will be too low, and bringing the signal up
to a usable level will bring the sound floor up to an obscenely loud level –
making gating nearly impossible to perform.</p>

<p>To properly deal with this, you need to adjust the signal level so that the
loudest sound comes in under 0 dB, which is where most recorders “peak”. If
certain sounds surpass 0 dB, some audio recorders have the ability to apply a
“limiter” effect, which will push the sound level back down to a usable value
as it is recorded. It’s not a desired effect, but it can save you from
clipping.</p>

<p>As you’re adjusting audio levels, you’ll see a constantly fluctuating level of
audio when no primary sound source is active. This is the “sound floor”, and
should be as far away from the bulk of the primary sound levels as possible.</p>

<h2 id="portable-recording-devices">Portable Recording Devices</h2>

<p>I recommend avoiding the <a href="http://amzn.to/1jyOxm5">Tascam DR-40</a> unit unless
you’re <em>positive</em> that you are using a balanced microphone. It tends to have a
weird firmware issue which produces a
<a href="http://www.dvxuser.com/V6/showthread.php?268124-Tascam-Dr-40-Buzz-Clicking-noise">strange clicking sound</a>
(almost impossible to remove) every quarter of a second when presented with an
unbalanced microphone. If you’re worried about this, go for the
<a href="http://amzn.to/QAUvXD">Zoom H4n</a>. It’s a bit more expensive, but it seems to
handle less expensive microphones in a more able fashion, as well as having
signal limiting and a host of other interesting features.</p>

<h2 id="compression-and-formats">Compression and Formats</h2>

<p>Most digital recorder units will record, at a minimum MP3 and WAV formats. WAV
is an uncompressed audio format, which means that it takes up more storage space
than a compressed format, but retains all of the information captured (at the
resolution captured). MP3 is a compressed format, using a psycho-acoustic model,
which means that it drops pieces of information which it figures we aren’t going
to be able to hear. MP3 files take up a smaller amount of space compared to
the same resolution WAV files – but that comes at the cost of throwing some
of the information out. MP3 @ 192kbps or above tends to have enough information
for most uses.</p>

<h2 id="equipment">Equipment</h2>

<p>There’s no “correct” equipment which you need to purchase to be able to capture
boom audio properly. There are, however, a few piece of equipment you’re
probably going to need.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Extendable Boom Pole</strong>. It’s tempting to go with a converted painters’
pole, but trust me – it pays to go with a decent boom pole. This is mainly
due to the additional noises which can be generated by swinging around a
makeshift boom pole. I personally recommend the
<a href="http://amzn.to/1l3TQaQ">On Stage MBP7000</a> boom pole for budget operators. It
doesn’t have an internal mic cable, but it works very well.</li>
  <li><strong>Microphone Cable (XLR)</strong>. This is an easy place to skimp for some people,
but you don’t want to pick up outside noise, so make sure you go with a
shielded XLR cable which is a few feet longer than the maximum size of your
boom pole, fully extended.</li>
  <li><strong>Clip / Shockmount / Zeppelin / Windscreen</strong>. You need something to isolate
the microphone from the wind, vibration, and other distorting effects of
the environment, which would distract from otherwise relatively clean
audio. Shockmounts can be had for relatively little, as can windscreens.
A zeppelin can cost a bundle, unless you make a DIY one – but they produce
very clean-sounding results.</li>
  <li><strong>Wire clips / wraps</strong>. Either some electrical tape (a cinematographer’s
best friend, after gaffe tape), or some inexpensive bobble hair ties
(available at most dollar stores) will allow you to keep the XLR cable
near the pole – otherwise you may find it dropping into frame at the most
inopportune times.</li>
  <li><strong>Microphone</strong>. There is a great deal of conjecture over the “best” budget
microphone to use. The most important things to consider are the polar
pickup pattern, the signal-to-noise ratio, and the frequency response of
any microphone you’re testing.</li>
  <li><strong>Portable digital recorder</strong>. Covered in the portable recorder section.</li>
  <li><strong>Headphones</strong>. A set of headphones, preferably full cup earphones, are
essential to monitoring the sound for disturbances and/or interruptions.
My favorite pair is the <a href="http://amzn.to/1qwuDgi">Sennheiser HD-280 PRO</a>,
as they’re relatively inexpensive (under 100 USD), and produce a fairly
accurate reproduction of live audio.</li>
  <li><strong>Storage media</strong>. Make sure you don’t buy off-brand media cards. Try to
stick with SanDisk and Lexar media, if you can. The trick is that these
companies generally tend to QA their products a bit more rigorously than
most off-brand manufacturers. This can make the difference between
usable audio and a very upset director.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="technique-and-directionality">Technique and Directionality</h2>

<p>Rather than iterate all of the techniques involved in actually operating a
boom mic rig, and keeping in mind that pictures are worth a thousand words…</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.viddler.com/player/39021abf/0/">Boom Mic 101</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Audio is half of your deliverables – so make sure your boom operator knows how
to deliver the best possible audio to your audio engineer for post production.
Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BMPC4K Workflow with Premiere and Resolve]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/08/bmpc4k-workflow-with-premiere-and-resolve/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T07:05:17-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/08/bmpc4k-workflow-with-premiere-and-resolve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a number of “accepted” workflows for going between Adobe Premiere
(as an NLE) and Davinci Resolve (for color correction/grading) for BMPC4K
footage. I am going to detail the workflow I have been using, which should
be useful both for the BMPC4K camera, as well as the BMPCC and BMCC cameras.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Preparation</strong>. Make sure your camera is producing footage at the 23.98
fps frame rate, rather than 24 fps. “True” 24 fps is not quite the same
thing as the “24P” frame rate we are used to.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Load your media onto your workstation</strong>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create simple proxies</strong>. Using
<a href="https://github.com/shootthemoonfilms/prores-proxies">prores-proxies</a>,
create “cheap” lower quality proxies encoded using the H.264 codec in
Quicktime files. I have been experimenting with using the “.mpg”
extension to <a href="http://blogs.adobe.com/VideoRoad/2012/12/premiere-pro-and-quicktime-and-nikon-oh-my.html">force Premiere to use its own internal Quicktime decoder</a>,
rather than the relatively dodgy external one, but the basic process
is the same.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Edit</strong>. Using the proxy files, edit your footage in Premiere. You do
not have to bother with any fancy transitions or effects yet – just
perform a basic edit.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Export to Resolve</strong>. Export a “Final Cut Pro XML” file, using the
File &gt; Export menu option.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Create a new Resolve Project</strong>. Open Resolve, and create a new project.
Import the original files (not the proxies) into your media pool.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Import the XML from Premiere</strong>. Import the “Final Cut Pro XML” export,
with “Automatically import source clips into pool” deselected. This last
part is very important, as it forces Resolve to use the clips you already
have in the Media Pool.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Color Grade</strong>. Perform your color grade in Resolve.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Export</strong>. In the “Delivery” tab, select the whole timeline, choose
“Easy Setup”,and select  “Final Cut Pro XML Round-Trip”. Change any options
here to your liking.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Import Roundtrip XML in Premiere</strong>. Import the Round-Trip XML file in
Premiere. This will bring in all of the graded footage.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Perform the remainder of your edits</strong>. Tweak your footage, copy or
create your title cards, etc.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>This is a very basic overview of my current BMPC4K + Resolve + Premiere
workflow right now, and it may change.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[48 Hours with the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-07T13:45:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year, my team (<a href="http://www.shootthemoonfilms.com">Shoot the Moon Films</a>),
entered the 2014 <a href="http://48hourfilm.com/en/boston/">Boston 48 Hour Film Festival</a>
for the first time. It’s an interesting experience, going from genre and
parameters to fully formed script, to planning and preproduction, to
shooting and execution, to editing, scoring, grading, and full post-production
in a single weekend. I’ve learned a lot about working with the 
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">BMPC4K</a>
camera in that time. I am going to iterate over some of the more important
things that I learned over the weekend.</p>

<h2 id="overheating">Overheating</h2>

<p>This simply did not happen. I had heard some horror stories about the camera
body breaking or overheating after long periods of filming, but even in 
direct sunlight for significant periods of time, I did not find this to be
the case. My EOS body used to overheat more than this one…</p>

<h2 id="nd-filters">ND filters</h2>

<p>My Tiffen 77VND was indispensible. If I didn’t have that single piece of
equipment, every exterior shot would have been very, very different. I wanted
a medium DOF and a standard shutter rate for my exterior shots – which meant
that the sunlight had to be stopped down. The variable ND filter delivered
perfectly.</p>

<h2 id="evf">EVF</h2>

<p>The Cineroid was a life-saver. I do not think I would have done as well
without its superior focus-peaking, crop indications, etc. The only feature
sorely missing from the EVF4CSS is waveforms/scopes, which would have been
a bit more useful than eyeballing the full extent of the dynamic range.</p>

<h2 id="v-mount-batteries">V-mount batteries</h2>

<p>If you are not turning your camera off between takes, you are going to need
more than one battery for a day-long shoot. Do <strong>NOT</strong> skimp on a V-mount
battery charger. They take a very long time to trickle charge, so make sure
you have a rapid charger. Also, spares. They may be expensive, but having to
wait on a battery charging could blow a shoot.</p>

<h2 id="audio">Audio</h2>

<p>This is less a “thing” with the BMPC4K body, and more of a general observation.
You cannot skimp on sound. You just <em>can’t</em>. You can always rely entirely on
tight OTS shots and other closeups and use on-camera mics, but it shuts off
an entire avenue of creative wider shots. A boom operator is <em>not</em> just your
buddy holding a mic on a pole – they need to know what they are doing,
otherwise you could be pushing very substandard audio into post-production.
Especially on a tight time limit, this can make the difference between making
a deadline, or having truly horrendous sound.</p>

<p>Also, get a really competent audio engineer. Preferably a really anal-retentive
one with an insane attention to detail. Even if you have perfect video, really
crappy audio can break the illusion of your film. <strong>DO NOT SKIMP</strong>. SERIOUSLY.</p>

<h2 id="that-pa-or-ad----you-need-them-more-than-you-think">That PA or AD – you need them more than you think</h2>

<p>If someone is not taking copious shot notes, you are going to find yourself
up at some ungodly hour, digging through footage for that shot that you
<em>know</em> you got. Save yourself the trouble, and have someone taking care of
all of that.</p>

<h2 id="proxy-files">Proxy files</h2>

<p>I used a new method of creating intermediate proxy files for editing, since
Premiere was not very cooperative in directly loading the Prores files from
the camera. <em>I made my code public in a project called
<a href="https://github.com/shootthemoonfilms/prores-proxies">prores-proxies</a>.</em> This
little trick made sure that, instead of having to render all of my footage
out at the Davinci Resolve speed of 3-6 fps (on my non-Red-Rocket workstation),
I was able to render it to proxies at about full speed (which was about 24fps).
Without this, I wouldn’t have been able to edit the footage without several
footage drops during the day – if at all – during the limited timeframe I
had to do so.</p>

<h2 id="premiere-quicktime-support-on-windows-is-dog-food">Premiere Quicktime support on Windows is dog food</h2>

<p>Something is wrong with it. I have no idea why, but the QT decoder decided
to “give up the ghost” quite a few times during editing. There is supposedly
a renaming hack, which allows the Premiere internal decoder to handle the
files, but I was not privvy to this information during editing. I will update
my documentation and/or author a post on this at some point in the near future,
as it is <strong>VERY</strong> irritating.</p>

<h2 id="too-many-cooks">Too many cooks</h2>

<p>One person edits. Someone can <em>assist</em> them, but you need to have one editor, 
who makes the decisions as to what goes into your final product. If you try
to “edit by committee”, you may end up with a very tired and frustrated primary
editor, and the possibility of some very incomprehensible footage.</p>

<p>If your editor and director are not the same person, the director sits in
with the editor to make decisions, where they need to be made. Ideally the
script notes, etc, provide enough information to the editor to perform his
job.</p>

<p>Also, do not get caught up in reviewing dailies if you are taking part in a
time-sensitive competition. This is a recipe for disaster.</p>

<h2 id="coloring">Coloring</h2>

<p>Even shooting with 10-bit ProRes 422 HQ, the advantage over H.264 DSLR
footage is immediately apparent. There is a lot of latitude for coloring
and correction, which would simply not be possible with the same level of
output quality with H.264.</p>

<p>I ended up performing a manual grading (as in, no LUTs or presets) for the
project we did, and I am very satisfied with the end result.</p>

<h2 id="grain">Grain</h2>

<p>I love the “film grain” that the sensor on this camera produces. I am sure
that I have mentioned it in earlier posts, but it really does give that
organic film look to your output.</p>

<h2 id="do-not-use-services-like-google-drive-for-your-deliverables">Do not use services like Google Drive for your deliverables</h2>

<p>They tend to like to really hurt you in upstream speeds – only when you are
on serious deadline. A better alternative for large media files is to set up
<a href="http://www.bittorrent.com/sync">btsync</a> on both sides, and transfer with far
more efficiency. You will be glad that you did it.</p>

<h2 id="too-many-hats--sink-ships">Too many hats … sink ships?</h2>

<p>There is serious temptation to wear more than one hat. Hell, we all wear more
than one hat on most small sets. The issue comes when you end up wearing
three or four (director, cinematographer, editor, colorist), and realize that
you do not get to sleep until everything is “out the door”. Delegate. Find
people who are good at this stuff, and let them do it. You do not have to be
good at everything, just find people who are.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I had a good time – but I could have been less stressed out, if I had known
some of this in advance.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CAME-06 Blackmagic Cage Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T21:52:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of setting up the <a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">Blackmagic Production Camera 4K</a>,
I have been trying to put together a solid, fairly low-cost set of
accessories for the camera body.</p>

<p>I became aware of a low-cost Chinese cage for the BMCC/BMPC4K
bodies manufactured by an outfit called
“<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/">Xiamen Came Photographic Equipment Co., Ltd.</a>”,
which are available sporting both top and bottom 15mm rail mounts, 
along with the normal mounting options and handles present with
most cage designs. The cage in question is available for
<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">$198, shipping included, from the manufacturer</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/came-06.jpg" width="289" height="400" title="“CAME-06 Cage”" ></p>

<p>My unit arrived today, via DHL, in a box which seemed almost
Ikea-esque in its packing. First thing to note, which is not
indicated either on the website or the packaging: “some assembly
required”. Secondly – no instructions. Thankfully, the entire
assembly procedure seemed pretty obvious with the provided
Allen wrenches. I noticed that there is a 5/8” mount on the
bottom of the unit (as well as a 1/4”-20 mount) for attaching to
the fluid head or quick-release plate of your choosing. This wasn’t
indicated on the website, but I had my suspicions, which were
thankfully confirmed.</p>

<p>The first major issue I encountered was the lack of four of the
required screws for assembly. Undaunted, I took a quick trip to 
the nearest “home improvement” store, and purchased four
M4-.70 x 12 bolts with phillips heads (in packs of two), which
worked like a charm.</p>

<p>The second slightly annoying issue was that one of the included
30cm 15mm rods was completely unthreaded, so it wouldn’t be
possible to attach it to any other rods, should it need to be
extended. The inclusion of the rods was a bit of a plus, so I
can’t really be too upset about that.</p>

<p>The build quality, once assembled, is quite good. The CAME-06
cage is machined properly, and does not interfere with the
operation of the BMPC4K unit at all, and has enough mount points
to allow me to put handles, arms, and other accessories on it,
which was the secondary purpose of purchasing the cage, after
being able to properly mount the camera on a decent QR plate.</p>

<p>Additionally, it has a set of Hirth joints on either side,
ostensibly for attaching handle mounts. I have no use for them
at the moment, but they seem to be workable.</p>

<p>As the next step up in price is another 70$, and this unit
arrived from China in less than four business days from my
initial order, the annoyance of a $1.00 bolt purchase seems
miniscule, considering the usability of the cage itself. It
isn’t a full system, like the Tilta, Lanparte, and others,
but can be built into a system incrementally.</p>

<p>Verdict: Know what you’re getting yourself into. If you want
a pre-assembled unit, next day shipping, and would rather pay
more money for the lack of inconvenience, you should avoid the
CAME-06. It’s a good deal for the price, however.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

<p><em>Postscript: The manufacturer offered to reimburse me for the
missing screws within a day of me writing to them, so they do
seem to be relatively responsive whenever there is a mixup.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First look at the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T11:17:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was lucky enough to be one of the early people on the waiting list for
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/">Blackmagic Design</a>’s new 4K “Production
Camera” body, which I received last week. It boasts a global shutter, Ultra
4K resolution, ProRes/RAW recording at 1080p/4K resolutions, a super 35mm
sensor, EF mount, and around 12 stops of dynamic range – among other
features. I took it out for a test spin with a fellow cinematographer, just
to see how far I could push the image.</p>

<p>After a test run of “horror” shots with both a Canon EF IS lens and a
manual Rokinon Cine lens, I’ve been learning about the benefits and caveats
of the BMPC body. I’m going to enumerate some of those here.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p><strong>Dynamic Range</strong>. This cooks the hell out of the H.264 image that I’ve been
getting out of the 5D mark III. I can see a full gamut of sky color without losing my subjects – and that’s without additional or reflected light.</p>

<p><strong>Cinematic Quality</strong>. This might have something to do with the depth of the
image, or the amazing amount of data that the body is storing for each frame,
but it is definitely capable of breathtaking quality. I haven’t seen any
artifacts from the footage I’ve taken so far, at either HD or 4K resolution.</p>

<p><strong>Metadata</strong>. The touch screen allows some metadata to be stored for each
clip, including the name of the project, scene number, etc, and allows it to
be edited on the camera body afterwards. It also has a numeric unique numbering
system, with customizable body IDs, which beats the MVI_xxxx.MOV or
MM1Axxxx.MOV scheme from Canon.</p>

<p><strong>Resolve</strong>. The body comes with a <em>full</em> copy of DaVinci Resolve 10. The
only way to truly appreciate it is to actually use it. It essentially puts
Fast Color Corrector and Colorista to shame. The only downside is that it
does take quite a bit longer to run than most of the plugin-based correction
and grading tools, unless you’re willing to invest in either a Red Rocket
card or a bunch of fairly powerful GPU units for your machine. Either way,
it is well worth the time and effort to learn how to use it.</p>

<p><strong>Baked in Zebras and Focus Peaking</strong>. This is less of a revelation for me,
coming from using Magic Lantern, but users of stock Canon bodies don’t know
what they’re missing. You can also acquire these via EVF features – but it
can’t be a bad thing to have those features in the body, as well.</p>

<p><strong>Crop Factor</strong>. It’s about the same crop factor as an APS-C crop, for you
7D and Rebel users, so it’s only a big deal to acclimate if you’re coming
from a full-frame body, like the 5D or 6D. The upshot is that you’re not
going to have to blow a lot of money on extremely wide glass, as would be
required by the BMPCC.</p>

<p><strong>Global Shutter</strong>. If you have a lot of fast motion or quick pans, the lack
of the “jello” effect from rolling shutter is very, very noticeable. This is
one of the prime reasons I purchased this body – and it works as well as
promised.</p>

<p><strong>RAW and ProRes</strong>. (Yes, I know “RAW” isn’t an acronym – I just like it enough to shout it…) No firmware hacks, no playing around, you get ProRes
and RAW footage out of this camera body. As of the time of writing, RAW has
been disabled in the firmware, but I’m expecting an update “any day now”
which will re-enable it. This makes me think twice about having usde H.264
as a codec for so long. And the logarithmic data collection means that all
of that nice dynamic range is intact through the coloring process, so you’re
not losing out there.</p>

<p><strong>EF Mount</strong>. This is a big deal for me, as it keeps me from having to rebuy
all of my glass. All of my M42, EF, and Nikon mount glass will be fine with
this. And as an added bonus, the FD mount glass I have (using the Lens
Doctor EF-FD mount adapter) works fine, and without the vignette I have on
the full-frame sensor.</p>

<h2 id="caveats">Caveats</h2>

<p><strong>Mounting</strong>. The standard 1/4” mount on the bottom of the camera is more
or less useless; the mount plates either shift or scratch the bottom of the
camera – so I ended up using the aluminum handles for my tests. They’re not
particularly useful, considering the weighting of the camera, so I’m waiting
for a cage to arrive. I only considered cages with upper and lower 15mm
rod mounts (for options, of course). These are the ones I found to be the
best choices:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">CAME-06 BMCC Cage</a> - $198 -
The cheapest of the non-ePhoto bunch. It’s just a cage with two 30cm
15mm rods included, so you have to kit the rest of it out, but it’s
potentially the best deal, considering the price jump to the
Wooden Camera or Tilta rigs.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ginirigs-usa.com/bmcc-rigs-and-cages/207-the-bmcc-box-cage.html">Gini Box Cage for BMPC</a> - $269 -
This is a slightly more well-known version of the CAME-06. I don’t know
the difference in build quality, but you’re getting similar type kitting.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/NkeVCv">Wooden Camera Base Kit</a> - $939 -
A well designed, modular kit. Expensive, but potentially worth it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/1lGfAud">Tilta TT-BMC-05</a> - $1570 -
Not necessarily the most affordable, but very well designed. Expect to
pay a hefty markup for their branded accessories. Note that this is an
<em>entire</em> rig, rather than just a base kit, so the extra money is probably
worth it, if you have it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Glossy Screen</strong>. The screen is <em>very</em> reflective. I completely understand
the virtual need for an EVF, otherwise you’re in daguerreotype shade cloth
territory. Because it has SDI outputs, rather than HDMI, it’s probably a
good idea to go with one of the SDI EVFs. Unfortunately, they’re not cheap.
You more or less have the pick of these:</p>

<ul>
  <li><del><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/827800-REG/Cineroid_EVF4MSS_EVF_Metal_with_HD_SDI.html">Cineroid EVF4MSS</a> - $699 - 
The least expensive of the set.</del></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/982065-REG/cineroid_evf4css_electronic_viewfinder.html">Cineroid EVF4CSS</a> - $599 -
I realized that you can’t really use the EVF4MSS, despite its metal
materials, because it only supports up to 1080i, whereas the BMPC4k
requires 1080p.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/894123-REG/Cineroid_EVF4RVW_with_Retina_Display.html">Cineroid EVF4RVW</a> - $995 -
Retina display version of the EVF4CSS. Higher resolution, higher price.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/852192-REG/Alphatron_Broadcast_Electronics_EVF_035W_3G_EVF_035W_3G_Electronic_View_Finder.html">Alphatron EVF-035W-3G</a> - $1395 -
The most expensive, but also most highly reviewed SDI EVF. Shane Hurlbut,
A.S.C., endorsed this particular EVF for use with the BMPC body.</li>
</ul>

<p>Otherwise, you’re in the market for both an EVF and an HDMI-to-SDI converter,
which will tack on an addition few hundred dollars. The temporary budget
solution, in my case, is to use a cloth until the EVF arrives …</p>

<p><strong>Battery Life</strong>. The internal battery isn’t supposed to provide much shoot
time ; virtually everyone using the camera has pointed out that it’s meant
to be a sort of “buffer” between battery changes with an external battery.
I bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9XDal">Switronix PB-70</a> for the body, which
sports a RED-style <a href="http://www.red.com/store/products/accessory-v-mount">V-mount</a>,
as well as a traditional 1/4”-20 mount. It can power the camera alone for
at least four hours, and can additionally power other devices, like EVFs,
HDMI-SDI converters, monitors, follow focus devices, et cetera, by the
extensible power connectors. I have to buy an extra one, so I can have one
charging and one plugged in, but it seems to be a decent solution.</p>

<p>Additionally, it helps to have the battery mounted on the camera assembly,
otherwise it is moderately unweildy. The cheapest mounting solution for
15mm rods I found was the <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9YGao">Ikan BMC-PBK-1-S</a> mount,
which has a small distribution center built into it. It’s slightly redundant,
as the adapter that came with the PB-70 isn’t used, but for the money, it’s
a good buy. It may make sense to buy the slightly more expensive
<a href="http://amzn.to/1hcVO4P">Lanparte plate</a>, which has a number of additional
power outputs.</p>

<p><strong>The Sun</strong>. Besides the glossy screen, the sun tends to blow out the fairly
sensitive BMPC4k sensor. The solution is to use ND filters to reduce the
amount of light coming into the sensor. You might be tempted to increase the
f-stop, but you’ll also be increasing the depth of field to be more
un-cinematic, so the ND filter is a must-have if you find yourself shooting in 
the direct sun, and don’t want to start using high shutter speeds. The
downside is going to come in the “price” category; if you buy cheap ND filters,
it will destroy the quality of the image, so you’re best off sticking with
Tiffen or other brand-name high quality filters. They don’t come particularly
cheap, however.</p>

<p>My recommendation to get started would be the 
<a href="http://amzn.to/1qINli9">Tiffen 77VND</a> 77mm variable neutral density
filter. It handles most of the reduction you’ll need, and at about $150, it’s
far less expensive than a set of 4x4 filter glass.</p>

<h2 id="overall">Overall</h2>

<p>I’m glad I didn’t wait for the Panasonic GH4. I know that’s going to come
off as a little odd, but for the smaller sensor, M4/3 mount and its relatively
insane crop factor, expensive add-on cinema kit, even <em>odder</em> form factor,
H.264 codec, limited dynamic range, and rolling shutter – I feel that the
BMPC4k body is going to do just fine. After all, no camera body makes you
film better, or makes you a better cinematographer. All it can do is allow
you the ability to increase your output quality – if you work for it.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I haven’t posted any video clips yet due to the stabilization issues
I had encountered using the handles alone. I may update the post to include
some stills and short clips with the IS lens.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
