<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-11T12:23:04-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CAME-06 Blackmagic Cage Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T21:52:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/18/came-06-blackmagic-cage-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of setting up the <a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/products/blackmagicproductioncamera4k">Blackmagic Production Camera 4K</a>,
I have been trying to put together a solid, fairly low-cost set of
accessories for the camera body.</p>

<p>I became aware of a low-cost Chinese cage for the BMCC/BMPC4K
bodies manufactured by an outfit called
“<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/">Xiamen Came Photographic Equipment Co., Ltd.</a>”,
which are available sporting both top and bottom 15mm rail mounts, 
along with the normal mounting options and handles present with
most cage designs. The cage in question is available for
<a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">$198, shipping included, from the manufacturer</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/came-06.jpg" width="289" height="400" title="“CAME-06 Cage”" ></p>

<p>My unit arrived today, via DHL, in a box which seemed almost
Ikea-esque in its packing. First thing to note, which is not
indicated either on the website or the packaging: “some assembly
required”. Secondly – no instructions. Thankfully, the entire
assembly procedure seemed pretty obvious with the provided
Allen wrenches. I noticed that there is a 5/8” mount on the
bottom of the unit (as well as a 1/4”-20 mount) for attaching to
the fluid head or quick-release plate of your choosing. This wasn’t
indicated on the website, but I had my suspicions, which were
thankfully confirmed.</p>

<p>The first major issue I encountered was the lack of four of the
required screws for assembly. Undaunted, I took a quick trip to 
the nearest “home improvement” store, and purchased four
M4-.70 x 12 bolts with phillips heads (in packs of two), which
worked like a charm.</p>

<p>The second slightly annoying issue was that one of the included
30cm 15mm rods was completely unthreaded, so it wouldn’t be
possible to attach it to any other rods, should it need to be
extended. The inclusion of the rods was a bit of a plus, so I
can’t really be too upset about that.</p>

<p>The build quality, once assembled, is quite good. The CAME-06
cage is machined properly, and does not interfere with the
operation of the BMPC4K unit at all, and has enough mount points
to allow me to put handles, arms, and other accessories on it,
which was the secondary purpose of purchasing the cage, after
being able to properly mount the camera on a decent QR plate.</p>

<p>Additionally, it has a set of Hirth joints on either side,
ostensibly for attaching handle mounts. I have no use for them
at the moment, but they seem to be workable.</p>

<p>As the next step up in price is another 70$, and this unit
arrived from China in less than four business days from my
initial order, the annoyance of a $1.00 bolt purchase seems
miniscule, considering the usability of the cage itself. It
isn’t a full system, like the Tilta, Lanparte, and others,
but can be built into a system incrementally.</p>

<p>Verdict: Know what you’re getting yourself into. If you want
a pre-assembled unit, next day shipping, and would rather pay
more money for the lack of inconvenience, you should avoid the
CAME-06. It’s a good deal for the price, however.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>

<p><em>Postscript: The manufacturer offered to reimburse me for the
missing screws within a day of me writing to them, so they do
seem to be relatively responsive whenever there is a mixup.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First look at the Blackmagic Production Camera 4K]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T11:17:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/03/16/first-look-at-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was lucky enough to be one of the early people on the waiting list for
<a href="http://www.blackmagicdesign.com/">Blackmagic Design</a>’s new 4K “Production
Camera” body, which I received last week. It boasts a global shutter, Ultra
4K resolution, ProRes/RAW recording at 1080p/4K resolutions, a super 35mm
sensor, EF mount, and around 12 stops of dynamic range – among other
features. I took it out for a test spin with a fellow cinematographer, just
to see how far I could push the image.</p>

<p>After a test run of “horror” shots with both a Canon EF IS lens and a
manual Rokinon Cine lens, I’ve been learning about the benefits and caveats
of the BMPC body. I’m going to enumerate some of those here.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p><strong>Dynamic Range</strong>. This cooks the hell out of the H.264 image that I’ve been
getting out of the 5D mark III. I can see a full gamut of sky color without losing my subjects – and that’s without additional or reflected light.</p>

<p><strong>Cinematic Quality</strong>. This might have something to do with the depth of the
image, or the amazing amount of data that the body is storing for each frame,
but it is definitely capable of breathtaking quality. I haven’t seen any
artifacts from the footage I’ve taken so far, at either HD or 4K resolution.</p>

<p><strong>Metadata</strong>. The touch screen allows some metadata to be stored for each
clip, including the name of the project, scene number, etc, and allows it to
be edited on the camera body afterwards. It also has a numeric unique numbering
system, with customizable body IDs, which beats the MVI_xxxx.MOV or
MM1Axxxx.MOV scheme from Canon.</p>

<p><strong>Resolve</strong>. The body comes with a <em>full</em> copy of DaVinci Resolve 10. The
only way to truly appreciate it is to actually use it. It essentially puts
Fast Color Corrector and Colorista to shame. The only downside is that it
does take quite a bit longer to run than most of the plugin-based correction
and grading tools, unless you’re willing to invest in either a Red Rocket
card or a bunch of fairly powerful GPU units for your machine. Either way,
it is well worth the time and effort to learn how to use it.</p>

<p><strong>Baked in Zebras and Focus Peaking</strong>. This is less of a revelation for me,
coming from using Magic Lantern, but users of stock Canon bodies don’t know
what they’re missing. You can also acquire these via EVF features – but it
can’t be a bad thing to have those features in the body, as well.</p>

<p><strong>Crop Factor</strong>. It’s about the same crop factor as an APS-C crop, for you
7D and Rebel users, so it’s only a big deal to acclimate if you’re coming
from a full-frame body, like the 5D or 6D. The upshot is that you’re not
going to have to blow a lot of money on extremely wide glass, as would be
required by the BMPCC.</p>

<p><strong>Global Shutter</strong>. If you have a lot of fast motion or quick pans, the lack
of the “jello” effect from rolling shutter is very, very noticeable. This is
one of the prime reasons I purchased this body – and it works as well as
promised.</p>

<p><strong>RAW and ProRes</strong>. (Yes, I know “RAW” isn’t an acronym – I just like it enough to shout it…) No firmware hacks, no playing around, you get ProRes
and RAW footage out of this camera body. As of the time of writing, RAW has
been disabled in the firmware, but I’m expecting an update “any day now”
which will re-enable it. This makes me think twice about having usde H.264
as a codec for so long. And the logarithmic data collection means that all
of that nice dynamic range is intact through the coloring process, so you’re
not losing out there.</p>

<p><strong>EF Mount</strong>. This is a big deal for me, as it keeps me from having to rebuy
all of my glass. All of my M42, EF, and Nikon mount glass will be fine with
this. And as an added bonus, the FD mount glass I have (using the Lens
Doctor EF-FD mount adapter) works fine, and without the vignette I have on
the full-frame sensor.</p>

<h2 id="caveats">Caveats</h2>

<p><strong>Mounting</strong>. The standard 1/4” mount on the bottom of the camera is more
or less useless; the mount plates either shift or scratch the bottom of the
camera – so I ended up using the aluminum handles for my tests. They’re not
particularly useful, considering the weighting of the camera, so I’m waiting
for a cage to arrive. I only considered cages with upper and lower 15mm
rod mounts (for options, of course). These are the ones I found to be the
best choices:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.came-tv.com/came06-bmcc-cage-for-blackmagic-design-cinema-camera-15mm-rail-p-477.html">CAME-06 BMCC Cage</a> - $198 -
The cheapest of the non-ePhoto bunch. It’s just a cage with two 30cm
15mm rods included, so you have to kit the rest of it out, but it’s
potentially the best deal, considering the price jump to the
Wooden Camera or Tilta rigs.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ginirigs-usa.com/bmcc-rigs-and-cages/207-the-bmcc-box-cage.html">Gini Box Cage for BMPC</a> - $269 -
This is a slightly more well-known version of the CAME-06. I don’t know
the difference in build quality, but you’re getting similar type kitting.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/NkeVCv">Wooden Camera Base Kit</a> - $939 -
A well designed, modular kit. Expensive, but potentially worth it.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/1lGfAud">Tilta TT-BMC-05</a> - $1570 -
Not necessarily the most affordable, but very well designed. Expect to
pay a hefty markup for their branded accessories. Note that this is an
<em>entire</em> rig, rather than just a base kit, so the extra money is probably
worth it, if you have it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Glossy Screen</strong>. The screen is <em>very</em> reflective. I completely understand
the virtual need for an EVF, otherwise you’re in daguerreotype shade cloth
territory. Because it has SDI outputs, rather than HDMI, it’s probably a
good idea to go with one of the SDI EVFs. Unfortunately, they’re not cheap.
You more or less have the pick of these:</p>

<ul>
  <li><del><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/827800-REG/Cineroid_EVF4MSS_EVF_Metal_with_HD_SDI.html">Cineroid EVF4MSS</a> - $699 - 
The least expensive of the set.</del></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/982065-REG/cineroid_evf4css_electronic_viewfinder.html">Cineroid EVF4CSS</a> - $599 -
I realized that you can’t really use the EVF4MSS, despite its metal
materials, because it only supports up to 1080i, whereas the BMPC4k
requires 1080p.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/894123-REG/Cineroid_EVF4RVW_with_Retina_Display.html">Cineroid EVF4RVW</a> - $995 -
Retina display version of the EVF4CSS. Higher resolution, higher price.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bhphotovideo.com/c/product/852192-REG/Alphatron_Broadcast_Electronics_EVF_035W_3G_EVF_035W_3G_Electronic_View_Finder.html">Alphatron EVF-035W-3G</a> - $1395 -
The most expensive, but also most highly reviewed SDI EVF. Shane Hurlbut,
A.S.C., endorsed this particular EVF for use with the BMPC body.</li>
</ul>

<p>Otherwise, you’re in the market for both an EVF and an HDMI-to-SDI converter,
which will tack on an addition few hundred dollars. The temporary budget
solution, in my case, is to use a cloth until the EVF arrives …</p>

<p><strong>Battery Life</strong>. The internal battery isn’t supposed to provide much shoot
time ; virtually everyone using the camera has pointed out that it’s meant
to be a sort of “buffer” between battery changes with an external battery.
I bought a <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9XDal">Switronix PB-70</a> for the body, which
sports a RED-style <a href="http://www.red.com/store/products/accessory-v-mount">V-mount</a>,
as well as a traditional 1/4”-20 mount. It can power the camera alone for
at least four hours, and can additionally power other devices, like EVFs,
HDMI-SDI converters, monitors, follow focus devices, et cetera, by the
extensible power connectors. I have to buy an extra one, so I can have one
charging and one plugged in, but it seems to be a decent solution.</p>

<p>Additionally, it helps to have the battery mounted on the camera assembly,
otherwise it is moderately unweildy. The cheapest mounting solution for
15mm rods I found was the <a href="http://amzn.to/1m9YGao">Ikan BMC-PBK-1-S</a> mount,
which has a small distribution center built into it. It’s slightly redundant,
as the adapter that came with the PB-70 isn’t used, but for the money, it’s
a good buy. It may make sense to buy the slightly more expensive
<a href="http://amzn.to/1hcVO4P">Lanparte plate</a>, which has a number of additional
power outputs.</p>

<p><strong>The Sun</strong>. Besides the glossy screen, the sun tends to blow out the fairly
sensitive BMPC4k sensor. The solution is to use ND filters to reduce the
amount of light coming into the sensor. You might be tempted to increase the
f-stop, but you’ll also be increasing the depth of field to be more
un-cinematic, so the ND filter is a must-have if you find yourself shooting in 
the direct sun, and don’t want to start using high shutter speeds. The
downside is going to come in the “price” category; if you buy cheap ND filters,
it will destroy the quality of the image, so you’re best off sticking with
Tiffen or other brand-name high quality filters. They don’t come particularly
cheap, however.</p>

<p>My recommendation to get started would be the 
<a href="http://amzn.to/1qINli9">Tiffen 77VND</a> 77mm variable neutral density
filter. It handles most of the reduction you’ll need, and at about $150, it’s
far less expensive than a set of 4x4 filter glass.</p>

<h2 id="overall">Overall</h2>

<p>I’m glad I didn’t wait for the Panasonic GH4. I know that’s going to come
off as a little odd, but for the smaller sensor, M4/3 mount and its relatively
insane crop factor, expensive add-on cinema kit, even <em>odder</em> form factor,
H.264 codec, limited dynamic range, and rolling shutter – I feel that the
BMPC4k body is going to do just fine. After all, no camera body makes you
film better, or makes you a better cinematographer. All it can do is allow
you the ability to increase your output quality – if you work for it.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I haven’t posted any video clips yet due to the stabilization issues
I had encountered using the handles alone. I may update the post to include
some stills and short clips with the IS lens.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lens Selection for Cinematography]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/12/21/lens-selection-for-cinematography/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-21T19:48:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/12/21/lens-selection-for-cinematography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The lens of your camera is arguably one of the most important parts of the
camera ; it has the job of controlling light, adjusting focus (and focal
length in variable focal length lenses), controlling depth-of-field
through the aperture, and adding character to the shots you have lovingly
framed. <em>(It should be noted that the sensor of a digital video camera
body is also very important, in terms of sensitivity, resolution, size,
and other factors, but it is out of the scope of this article.)</em></p>

<p>There are quite a few factors to consider when choosing the lens you will
use for a shot, as well as the lenses you will pack for a shoot. Do you
pack one or two variable focal-length lenses, or do you pack a series of
strategic length prime lenses? Do you stay with your native lens mount?
Do you use vintage lenses? Do you need super-fast lenses?</p>

<p>As of the writing of this, I’ve been known to primarily use three or four
prime lenses (24mm, 35mm, 50mm, and 85mm), while packing a 105mm or 135mm
with a set of extension tubes for extreme macro usage. This setup will
<strong>not</strong> work for everyone, as I will explain.</p>

<h2 id="lens-mount">Lens Mount</h2>

<p>There are several types of lens mounts, and depending on the type of camera
body you use, one (or two) will be a “native” mount. For example, if you
shoot using a Canon EOS camera (T3i, 7D, 5D mk3, C100, etc), you will most
likely be using primarily EF mount lenses (and/or EF-S lenses if you aren’t
shooting with a full-frame sensor). These native lenses have the advantage
of having auto-focus / focus-confirmation electronics, as well as being able
to mount with no additional hardware required. Auto-focus isn’t really an
issue with cinematography, and focus-confirmation isn’t a <em>huge</em> advantage,
especially if your camera has focus peaking – but these lenses were
<em>designed</em> to work with your camera body.</p>

<p>Other lens mounts can be accommodated with adapter rings, which can usually
be purchased for varying amounts from online retailers. I have a few
M42 adapter rings for using old Pentax screw-mount lenses with the EF mount
on my camera, and they work flawlessly for me. Some of the more expensive
ones even have focus confirmation capabilities.</p>

<p>Photographers might give some pause to the idea of not having focus
confirmation or auto focus, but cinematographers should be fine with it.
Lens mount should only factor into your decision to use a lens by whether
or not you have the appropriate adapter ring configuration to use that
lens, in my opinion.</p>

<h2 id="prime-or-variable-focal-length-zoom">Prime or Variable Focal Length (Zoom)</h2>

<p>A great deal of the answer to this question depends on the primary type
of cinematography in which you tend to engage. A variable focal length
lens is essentially a single lens which offers an “infinite number of
focal lengths between its two bounds”, but there are other factors to be
considered when using one. For example, many lower-cost variable focal
length lenses will tend to have variable maximum apertures, depending on
the target focal length.</p>

<p>If you’re engaged in documentary cinematography or non-planned shoots
(such as many modern “web series” shoots), you may want to stick with
the widest range of variable focal length lens you can accommodate. A
24-70mm lens will usually handle most shots which would be required by
those mediums, and will mostly eliminate the hassle of changing lenses
during critical (and possibly situationally-limited) shoot times.</p>

<p>A serious trade-off is that most variable focal length lenses are not
“fast” (i.e. do not have a very low f-stop number for their maximum
aperture size), and therefore tend to require more light. The faster
lenses among that class tend to increase in cost greatly.</p>

<p>Prime lenses usually do one thing, and try to do it very well. They
range down (and below) f/1.2, and are far more cost effective for a
single focal length. If you have the time to change lenses in between
shots, and tend away from smash zooms (which I tend to find are a bit
over-used) and dolly/zoom combination shots, you might want to tend
towards a collection of primes.</p>

<h2 id="how-fast-is-fast">How fast is fast?</h2>

<p>The majority of consumer-grade lenses tend to have smaller maximum aperture
sizes than f/2.8, but there are a fair number of inexpensive primes which
can be had with an f/2.8 maximum aperture size, and relatively inexpensive
(compared to some) lenses can be had down to f/1.4 or so, depending on the
relative concessions you’re willing to make regarding the lens quality,
mount, manufacturer, et cetera.</p>

<p>As the aperture size increases, the depth of field decreases in size, but
the amount of light hitting the sensor increases. Low light cinematography
has historically relied on “fast” lenses rather than increased sensor
sensitivity, primarily due to the increasing role that sensor “noise” 
plays at high ISO levels. This tradeoff means that you may have to decide
whether depth of field or light sensitivity will be the primary determining
factor in the maximum aperture rating of the lenses you’re using.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: Another thing to note is that lenses tend not to be their sharpest
or best when fully open, so you may have to shoot slightly further shut
than the maximum aperture rating.</em></p>

<h2 id="vintage-lenses">Vintage Lenses</h2>

<p>Some cinematographers (and photographers) will <em>swear</em> by vintage glass.
Optics from lenses like old Carl Zeiss lenses are still amazing, and some
of these lenses are sold for less than the comparable modern lenses for
them. It can be a potentially <em>expensive</em> habit, however, since
cinematographers have been driving up the cost of purchasing these lenses,
as their lack of focus controls is far less bothersome than it would be
to photographers.</p>

<p>If you can purchase vintage lenses (or happen upon a cache of them), it’s
something to seriously consider. They have their own character, and when
used thoughtfully, can add much to your footage.</p>

<h2 id="focal-length">Focal length</h2>

<p><em>NOTE: If you’re going with variable focal length lenses exclusively, 
you may be able to safely skip this section. It deals mostly with the
reasoning behind using certain focal length lenses.</em></p>

<p>Selection of focal length depends on a number of factors. Entire chapters,
and even whole <em>books</em> have been written about selecting focal lengths
for cinematography and photography. A great deal of it has to do with
the type of shot you are working with, as well as the framing, etc. I’m
going to hit some of the considerations, but I suggest further reading.</p>

<p>When considering focal lengths on cameras, I tend to consider them using
the standard of a “full frame” sensor, since my camera has one. This means
that the written focal length of a lens corresponds directly to the
<em>effective</em> focal length of that lens. A larger “crop factor” (which is
the case for smaller sensor sizes, like the Canon APS-C sensor and the
Micro 4/3 sensors) means that a lens’s effective focal length is longer
for those sensors. You can figure out the effective focal length by
multiplying the stated focal length by the crop factor. For example,
an APS-C crop factor is 1.5x, so a 35mm lens would have an effective
focal length of 52.5mm, and a 50mm lens would have an effective focal
length of 75mm.</p>

<p>“Wide angle” shots, which are usually used for establishing shots in
cinema, generally tend to rely on very “wide” lenses, which are lenses
with short focal lengths. As you move further away from 35mm effective
focal length, the field of view present in your frame increases, which
increases geometric distortion towards the edges of the frame. This has
been referred to as a “fish eye” effect, when present in more than
moderate amounts.</p>

<p>As an aside, I have seen cinematographers use extremely wide lenses
(18mm and shorter) to shoot closeup shots of actors and actresses in
tight quarters – and I must warn against it, unless you are 
<strong>acutely aware</strong> of the geometric distortion which you are introducing
into the frame. This has very unpleasant effects on the faces of actors
when used for close shots, and I know few actors who take kindly to being
represented in a grossly distorted manner.</p>

<p>A 50mm effective focal length is essentially what your eye sees; at least,
that’s the way I’ve come to think of it. It’s a very neutral lens to use
for most shots. I recommend that this length be a standard part of any
lens kit you’re putting together.</p>

<p>50mm lenses have been popular with the Canon DSLR cinematography crowd,
primarily due to the inexpensive nature of the “nifty fifty”, a 50mm
f/1.8 prime which clocks in at a little over 100 USD new. Its optics aren’t
that fantastic, but its point of entry is so low in the cost department
that many people will own one. If you do, consider buying an f/1.4 version
of the same lens (or the f/1.2 L, if you’re successful, or have some sort
of trust fund laying around), as the optical and build quality is far
superior to the 50mm f/1.8 lens. It’s a “midway” focal length, but very
usable for a variety of shots.</p>

<p>Greater than 50mm effective focal lengh lenses are considered “long”
lenses. They tend to “compress” the space they capture, much as wide angle
lenses tend to expand and distort it. One must be careful with using long
lenses for handheld and steadicam work, as camera shake tends to be
magnified with longer lenses. </p>

<p>Long lenses can also be used for closeup and extreme closeup shots by using
“extension tubes” – what my brother used to refer to as “expensive air”.
They increase the amount of light required, and are not as easy or compact
as most macro lenses, but they’re relatively cheap, and cut down on the
number of lenses you have to carry.</p>

<h2 id="what-the-hell-is-a-bokeh">What the hell is a “bokeh”?</h2>

<p>The term “bokeh” is a recent addition to the vocabulary of the photographer
and cinematographer ; it simply refers to the blur produced by out of
focus objects, particularly lights, by a lens. It is determined largely by
the quality of the optics of the lens, as well as the number of blades in
the lens’s aperture. Higher blade counts generally produce more “pleasing”
bokeh, approaching the cinematic standard of almost circular light blur.</p>

<h2 id="you-havent-told-me-which-lenses">You haven’t told me which lenses!</h2>

<p>This isn’t intended to dictate which lenses a cinematographer <em>must</em> carry,
nor push certain choices over others, but merely to attempt to educate
about sensible lens selection.</p>

<p>Consider buying a Pelican case, or other shock resistant case, for travelling
to shoots. If you’re carrying a lot of glass, you can’t afford to deal
with the downtime of a broken lens.</p>

<p>There are a huge number of lenses, both modern and “ancient”, and you can
equip yourself with any variety of lenses, depending on your particular
idiom and shooting style. Don’t fall into the trap of assuming that lens
selection is unnecessary, or that everything should be shot with a single
lens ; it’s just another aspect of cinematic creativity. Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic range]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-28T11:08:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/28/dynamic-range</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a photographer or cinematographer, I’m sure you’ve come into contact with
limitations in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range">dynamic range</a>.
I have run into limitations with dynamic range in both the visual and audio
field, since anything that involves “real world” signals is going to 
potentially run up against the ability of the digital mediums on which we
rely to properly store the entire gamut of available analog data that we are
able to perceive with our eyes and ears. To combat the loss of data, computer
scientists and electrical engineers developed the process of dynamic range
compression, which is usually referred to as simple “compression”. This
reduces the gamut of presented information to a digitally representable
format. There is, however, something which is lost – and that is the
original dynamic range ; the amount of variance between the strongest and
weakest signal. In small doses, or when done with finesse, this provides the
ability to produce better sounding and better looking content in the digital
realm. When overused, we see results like the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loudness_war">loudness war</a>.</p>

<p>I like to explore the more figurative aspects of many technical concepts, to 
which most avid readers of my work would attest. In that vein of ideas, consider
the derivative concept of dynamics as a function of cinematic tension/resolution
and feeling.</p>

<p>Much like a written work, cinematic works generally tend to follow a
“<a href="http://www.dailywritingtips.com/how-to-structure-a-story-the-eight-point-arc/">plot/story arc</a>”,
which have a number of basic stages, even if the presentation, order, and
presence will vary between works. As cinematographers, one of our jobs is to
attempt to portray the basic plot elements, character interactions, and other
potentially metaphysical aspects of the story through the lensing, lighting,
focal points, composition, and method of stabilization and capture we use.
<em>(I’m aware that there are other control points, but forgive me my omissions
for the sake of some semblence of brevity.)</em> For example, for a more
“cinéma vérité” style for a combat or heavy action sequence, a filmmaker could
choose to shoot with less stabilization, looser composition, and less staged
lighting, which would present the audience with the perception that the scene
is far closer to the work of a documentarian than a staged film scene. In
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120815/">Saving Private Ryan</a>, for example, the
battle scenes have a decreased exposure time, resulting in action appearing
far more caustic and (what we believe is) more realistic. This allows the
relative dynamics of the scenes in question to be raised to allow far more
tension and action to be shown, through simple camera work.</p>

<p>The issue with techniques like this begin to manifest themselves when they
begin to flatten the dynamic of a film work through rampant and flagrant
overuse. At some point, cinematographers realized that they could shoot
<em>entire films</em> with these techniques, ostensibly to raise those tension and
action levels to that same high. By doing this, they have effectively
flattened the dynamic range of their works, producing an effectively and
uniformly “loud” work. The questions that you might be asking are “why is this
a bad thing, and why should I care?”</p>

<p>We view things as deltas, or differences. We understand happiness because we
understand sadness, heat because we experience cold, and comfort and
companionship because we can contrast it with loneliness. If the range we are
give to deal with is only the “best parts”, we begin to lose our ability to
appreciate it, and all of those things which should have made it special and
artistic become mere convention. Think about it – if everyone screamed
everything at the same volume, rather than having varying levels of emphasis
and volume, wouldn’t that screaming have lost its impact and importance?</p>

<p>Every technique that you have as a cinematographer or photographer is another
potential tool in your figurative tool box; but just because you have them
doesn’t mean that you have to use one particular one <em>all the time</em>. Handheld
camerawork has its place, and even though modern technology has provided many
methods of stabilizing camera and lens motion, from the steadicam to image
stabilization/vibration reduction lens to three point shoulder rigs, we still
find many cinematographers intentionally introducing shake into their
footage. I wrote an <a href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/06/03/stabilization/">entire essay</a> 
on the importance of stabilization, so I won’t reiterate my grievances here.</p>

<p>It’s important to understand why you’re doing something rather than
simply doing it for convenience or convention. If you’re using a wide open
aperture, are you doing it because you’re having lighting issues, or simply
because you think that everything should be shot with the thinnest DOF
possible? Is there some sort of artistic reason why you chose to shoot with
a 24mm vs a 35mm lens for a particular shot? Are you using a tripod-based
shot rather than a steadicam for a reason? Asking questions and analyzing
your own work, as well as the work of others, is key to artistic growth, as
well as understanding how to use your skillset as a photographer or
cinematographer.</p>

<p>I am, by no means, at the top of the skill grouping for photography <em>or</em>
cinematography. Many of the entries I have authored here are products of
making mistakes, and they are the attempt I am making to keep others from
having to make some of the very same mistakes I have made. Even films and
other work which we don’t particularly like as a whole may have a few 
setups or shots which provide food for thought. So, watch those films with
a critical eye, and hopefully we can all expand our “toolboxes”, as well
as learn how to use them in a more effective manner. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Signal to noise ratio]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T15:06:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/11/19/signal-to-noise-ratio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To quote the venerable Wikipedia:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Signal-to-noise ratio (often abbreviated SNR or S/N) is a measure used in science and engineering that compares the level of a desired signal to the level of background noise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This has a number of applications in engineering, but it also nicely
encapsulates a basic truth of dealing with equipment, people, and works –
there is always a certain amount of background noise. (For more information
on the concept, check out <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal-to-noise_ratio">this article</a>.)</p>

<p>In an ideal world, all equipment would be flawless and noiseless, everyone
would be wonderful at what they do, and all works would be exceptional 
<em>(don’t mind the inherent logical issue in the statement “all works would be
exceptional”; I was trying to make a point, so please forgive me my
linguistic foibles)</em>. As it so happens, due to a fun little thing called the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">Dunning-Krueger Effect</a>,
we tend to assume that our works are better than they actual are, until we
reach a particular skill level, at which point we start underestimating our
own skill levels. Succinctly put, we’re all terrible at figuring out how good
or bad we are at any particular skill.</p>

<p>This is a real pickle, especially when dealing with other people. With very
few exceptions, we’re going to end up working with other people. This is more
applicable in cinematography than in photography, since there are usually more
people involved with a film production than with a still photo shoot (although
I’m sure there are plenty of instances which would prove me wrong in that
aspect). </p>

<p><em>I’m going to restrict my examples to cinematography projects, to keep
this a bit more manageable and readable.</em></p>

<p>First, look at your potential crew. If you’re dealing with a low-budget indie
shoot, which most of us are, you are either not paying your crew or are paying
them very little money. You’ve already eliminated the possibility of a great
number of highly experienced, educated, and trained people being involved,
simply by eliminating the carrot of a serious payday. It could be additionally
argued that those who do work for a living are not necessarily <em>great</em> at
what they do, but that’s a little tangential to the core of the argument.
Out of those people, you’re generally going to tend to see the talent curve
follow the infamous <a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/NormalDistribution.html">standard/normal distribution curve</a>.
This means some will be utterly atrocious, some will be genius, and the
vast majority will lie somewhere between those two points. The outliers and
bounds will depend on the sample size, but the general concept tends to be
the same, which is that most people are not going to possess genius-level
skills in the vast majority of a sample set.</p>

<p>Second, look at your potential actors/on-screen talent. You’re in the same
boat as you were with the crew – except that a single truly terrible actor
will destroy the illusion you’re trying to create, so you have to hope that
your lower bound is pretty high, otherwise your end product will most likely
suffer. (It should also be said that a really great director has been known
to coax amazing performances out of lackluster talent, but we can’t all be
Stanley Kubrick, Darren Aronofsky, or P.T. Anderson…)</p>

<p>So, what are we to do? We need to start acknowledging that not everything
we’re going to make is going to be the best thing <strong>ever</strong>. It’s an anathema
to the general self-aggrandizing L.A. film culture, but we have to respect
the normal distribution curve – most films will be mediocre, some will be
agonizingly bad, and some will be amazing. The DKE means we’ll always think
that they’re all amazingly wonderful, but we need to be far more critical of
our own works ; at least, if we want to try to produce high-quality output.</p>

<p>We also need to understand that there’s a place for our hubris, as well as
our humility. We cannot grow as filmmakers, photographers, artists, or as
people, until we both appreciate the skill-set we have, while at the same
time understanding the limits of what we have accomplished right now, and
always striving to produce better, become better, and encourage better. We
can’t all be the <strong>best</strong>, but we can all become <strong>better</strong>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
