<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-12T22:01:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Epistemology II]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/06/film-epistemology-ii/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-06T09:12:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/06/film-epistemology-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This continues the analysis from my <a href="/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/">previous article on epistemology in film</a>. It makes more sense in the context of the first part.</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="known-unknowns-and-unknown-unknowns">Known unknowns and unknown unknowns</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say we know there are some things we do not know. But there are also unknown unknowns – the ones we don’t know we don’t know. And if one looks throughout the history of our country and other free countries, it is the latter category that tend to be the difficult ones. - Donald Rumsfeld</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m not a big fan of Donald Rumsfeld, but his attempt to weasel out of a bad PR situation by echoing the sentiments of Nassim Taleb’s “Fooled by Randomness” does have a silver lining of real value in epistemological evaluation – as well as in the analysis of the effects of intentionally incomplete epistemology on film viewing.</p>

<p>There are certain things that are going to fall outside the realm of narrative exposition – our “unknown unknowns”. These can manifest as plot twists, or may simply contain areas of knowledge which are tangential, to a certain degree, to our principal characters or plot.</p>

<p>The “known unknowns” are the principal fodder for epistemic expansion. For example, in the context of Nolan’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0468569/">The Dark Knight</a>, we are treated to a series of false-lead backstories for the Joker, but we’re always aware that we have <em>no idea</em> where he comes from, or anything outside of the explicitly available information in the film epistemology.</p>

<p>The oddest quadrant of the known/unknown delineation is the “unknown known”. In the system of information that we <em>don’t know that we know</em>, there are plenty of subtle hints and pieces of subliminal information which we ingest during the course of viewing the first acts of a film before the potential payoff in the last act. We may not be conscious that we know these things until they are brought to our attention, and the information moves to become a “known known”.</p>

<h2 id="epistemology-as-part-of-a-larger-canon">Epistemology as part of a larger canon</h2>

<p>As part of a response to the first part of this analysis, a friend pointed me to an <a href="http://kotaku.com/why-people-get-so-worked-up-about-canon-1688856413">examination of how we view canon</a> <sup>(<a href="http://www.webcitation.org/6WrSMmtox">cite</a>)</sup>. There are a number of different aspects to the relationship between epistemology and canon.</p>

<p>A television series presents an interesting situation; it poses the question of how to deal with a single work, generally under the care of multiple auteurs, in the form of multiple directors over the course of a single season/series. In traditional multiple episode television works, the story arc writers function as primary auteurs, using a “<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bible_%28writing%29">bible</a>” to attempt to keep epistemic consistency across works. Deviances can (and have been) introduced when interpreted by individual episode directors.</p>

<p>With multi-medium canon, spanning graphic novels, television, film, et al, the potential problems maintaining a single definitive canon multiply. It’s difficult enough to maintain canon between films or television episodes in the same medium, but, as each storytelling medium has its own caveats and rules, there are differences in the way that information is conveyed – not to mention that the presence of multiple auteurs (specific to each medium) would provide a potentially corrupting influence on the epistemology specific to the canon.</p>

<p>An example of this could be seen to be the interactions between large canon works, such as some of the DC comics universe works (i.e. Batman, Superman) and the television and film adaptations of those same works.</p>

<h2 id="altering-canon----and-the-burden-of-appeasing-fandom">Altering canon – and the burden of appeasing fandom</h2>

<p>The auteurs involved in the adaptations will sometimes drastically alter canon – <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0279600/">Smallville</a> and Singer’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0348150/">Superman Returns</a> in the case of the Superman franchise, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3749900/">Gotham</a> and Burton’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096895/">Batman</a> as examples in the case of the Batman franchise. Some of these works override / ignore existing canon, while some of them provide prequel and sequel material; for the moment, the question I’d like to pose is “what does a prequel or sequel <em>owe</em> canonical epistemology?”</p>

<p>There are a few things which I believe should be taken into account when trying to determine the answer to that question.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Intent</strong>. What is the intention of the prequel/sequel? Putting aside the general overriding motive of monetary gain, motivations can generally be split between a primary financial motivation to profit off of the material or an intention to either “re-imagine” the canon (assuming that the auteur can produce a superior outcome) or augment the canon. A primarily financial motive will most likely result in the canonical epistemology being set aside for the sake of increasing or pleasing the target demographic.</li>
  <li><strong>Integrity</strong>. It seems as thought the vast majority of epistemic extension and exploration is done without much consideration for the impact on both the integrity and the closure of the film’s epistemology. Considerate works which are considering attaching themselves to existing epistemology of a larger canon should be considering these factors before altering the epistemology. Any addition to canonical epistemology changes both the perception of prior works and potentially their emotional impact in retrospect.</li>
</ul>

<p>Fandom have devoted time and/or money to a “franchise”, presumably because they identify or sympathize with something espoused in the larger canon. Because of this largely emotional attachment to the larger body of work, fandom can place a great emphasis on preserving the present state of canon and keeping the epistemology intact – or perhaps as close to the state in which they originally found it when they became attached to the canonical works. This temporal attachment goes toward explaining why, for example, fans of <a href="http://tardis.wikia.com/wiki/Doctor_Who">Doctor Who</a> generally tend to view the incarnation of the Doctor which was their first introduction to the series as the subjectively “best” incarnation of that character.</p>

<p>There is another possibility inherent in the relationship between fandom and epistemology, which is that the viewer will (almost obsessively) attempt to seek out any epistemic closure or extension which is offered to them. I posit that it is the result of a deep emotional attachment to the characters and situations present in the canon which cause the viewer to attempt to create the most vivid knowledge-set of the canon and attempt to achieve epistemic closure.</p>

<h2 id="expectations--the-burden-of-context">Expectations ; the burden of context</h2>

<p>The context in which we view the epistemic system of a film, or the subjective epistemology, is almost as important as the objective epistemology given by the subject film.</p>

<p>The emotional and subjective knowledge baggage we bring into a film don’t necessarily have to have been introduced by other works in a canon. They could have come from other films in the same genre, adaptations of written works with similar subject material, earlier attempts at adapting the source material from the film, or even subjective life experiences of the viewer.</p>

<h2 id="reboot----uncorrupting-the-epistemology">Reboot – uncorrupting the epistemology?</h2>

<p>Over time, epistemology of a canon can become corrupted, self-contradictory, or suffer an overall loss in quality. One of the accepted methods for uncorrupting the epistemology of a larger work has been the <em>reboot</em>, another is retroactive continuity, or “retconning”, which has been used extensively in graphic novel and comic works as well as <a href="https://matthewkirshenblatt.wordpress.com/2013/12/24/time-travel-and-retconning-revisionism-and-reconstructionism-in-doctor-who/">television and film</a> <sup>(<a href="http://www.webcitation.org/6WrTwHOTQ">cite</a>)</sup>. There are a number of different successful methodologies which have been used for epistemic resets through reboots:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Complete epistemic do-over</strong>. This involves a disregarding of the entire literal epistemology, perhaps keeping some of the more commonly regarded portions of the canon, most likely to appease the target demographic’s past connection with prior incarnations. Examples of this would include the multiple Batman series reboots (Burton, Nolan), as well as the recent Spiderman reboots.</li>
  <li><strong>Time Travel Adjustment</strong>. This is when a series simply invents a <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/CosmicRetcon">time-travel type retcon or reset</a> in order to change basic principals of the epistemology. This differs from complete epistemic reconfigurations because the original continuity and epistemology is respected and then explained away or altered through the use of a time-travel narrative device. Popular examples of this include Abrams’ <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0796366/">Star Trek</a> reboot, and the <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1340138/">Terminator: Genisys</a> film. Zemeckis’s <a href="">Back to the Future</a> franchise worked almost entirely by turning this concept into a plot device – a concept mirrored by the recent <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3148266/">12 Monkeys</a> television series, but ironically not from its source material, the Gilliam <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114746/">Twelve Monkeys</a> film.</li>
  <li><strong>Hand Wave</strong>. Quite possibly the <em>laziest</em> form of epistemic reset. It generally involves simply ignoring certain aspects of previous epistemology in the canon or offering a glib explanation – usually prior films within a designated series. A general example of this would be the <em>Highlander</em> sequels, although it has also been part of a fairly well known <em>Doctor Who</em> trope for the majority of the run of the show.</li>
  <li><strong>Revisionist Adjustment</strong>. Adjusting portions of an already established epistemology for the purpose of correcting perceived mistakes or inadequacies. An example of this would be the introduction of Darth Vader as Luke Skywalker’s father in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080684/">Empire Strikes Back</a> after it was explained through explicit narrative exposition in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0076759/">A New Hope</a> that Vader had <em>murdered</em> Luke’s father; it was <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/Retcon">retconned</a> during <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086190/">Return of the Jedi</a> through a particularly clumsy dialogue-based hand wave. (This is only one of many, many examples of retroactive continuity in the Star Wars universe.)</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Film Epistemology]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T12:08:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/02/26/film-epistemology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to take a brief look at film epistemology. In order for that to work, I’m going to be positing that for our purposes, each film is its own self-contained universe with its own rules and knowledge both known and unknown.</p>

<p><em>(As a disclaimer, I’m no Scott Eric Kaufmann; I’m not going to be using visual illustrations, and precious few (if any) citations. There are also bound to be spoilers of every variety, so if a film is mentioned, avert your gaze if you don’t want to learn important truths about its ending.)</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="film-as-philosophy-and-self-contained-world">Film as philosophy and self contained world</h2>

<p>As I’ve just mentioned, a singular film can be seen as its own self-contained universe – a universe populated with rules and knowledge which are specific to that universe. Sometimes that world looks much like our own and shares many similar traits, sometimes it shares many visual similarities but a different history, and sometimes it bears little resemblance to the world and universe we know and try to understand.</p>

<p>The important similarity is that there’s a philosophical system underlying each of these film universes, built on the philosophies and mores of the auteurs of each film (writer, director, et al). Some popular films and film franchises have generated series of philosophical works – Star Wars, in particular, comes to mind – as well as compendiums of knowledge and in-universe canon of all varieties. Within the confines of these films, the epistemology has been grown in such a way as to allow a more immersive universe (according to the optimist), and/or wring more money from dedicated fans (according to the pessimist).</p>

<p>One of the things that has tended to irritate my own film sensibilities have been when films violate their own rules. Film is a suspension of disbelief, but there are certain rules explicitly or implicitly set out during the course of the film, which define the epistemology in which I have to be immersed while watching. A film shouldn’t violate its own rules, otherwise I end up setting aside my suspension of disbelief and become very aware that I’m watching a film.</p>

<p>To elaborate, I quote <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/WillingSuspensionOfDisbelief">TV Tropes’ excellent page on this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Any creative endeavor, certainly any written creative endeavor, is only successful to the extent that the audience offers this willing suspension as they read, listen, or watch. It’s part of an unspoken contract: The writer provides the reader/viewer/player with a good story, and in return, they accept the reality of the story as presented, and accept that characters in the fictional universe act on their own accord.
An author’s work, in other words, does not have to be realistic, only believable and internally consistent (see <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/MagicAIsMagicA">Magic A Is Magic A</a>). When the author pushes an audience beyond what they’re willing to accept, the work fails in the eyes of that particular audience. As far as science fiction is concerned, viewers are usually willing to go along with <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/TechnoBabble">creative explanations</a> which is why <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/PhysicsGoof">people don’t criticize your wormhole travel system</a> or <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AppliedPhlebotinum">how a shrinking potion doesn’t violate the laws of matter conservation</a>, but even in the more fantastical genres, suspension of disbelief can be broken when a work breaks its own established laws or asks the audience to put up with too many things that come off as contrived.
A common way of putting this is “You can ask an audience to believe the impossible, but not the improbable.” For example, people will accept that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AWizardDidIt">the Grand Mage can teleport across the world</a>, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/StealthInSpace">the spaceship has technology that makes it completely invisible</a> without rendering its own sensors blind, but they won’t accept that the ferocious carnivore <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/AssPull">just happened to have a heart attack and die</a> right before it attacked the main character, or that <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/HollywoodHacking">the hacker guessed his enemy’s password on the first try just by typing random letters</a>, at least without <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/JustifiedTrope">some prior detail justifying it</a> or one of the Rules listed below coming into play. What is in <a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/RealLife">Real Life</a> impossible just has to be made the norm in the setting and kept consistent.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="epistemological-overlap-and-suspension-of-disbelief">Epistemological overlap and suspension of disbelief</h2>

<p>As much as there is a suspension of disbelief inherent in any viewing of film (it is, after all, a series of quickly presented still frames in an artificial viewing environment), we require a certain epistemological overlap with our own universe / reality.</p>

<p>There is a certain range of deviation from reality which is acceptable in the majority of film. I believe this is because film has to balance a sense of relatability, which is produced by overlapping epistemology with reality, with its own deviations and rules. If a film is <em>too close</em> to reality without matching it exactly, we end up encountering something similar to the “<a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mori_Uncanny_Valley.svg">uncanny valley</a>”, where we become disenfranchised from the reality with which we are presented because it becomes very clear to us that it isn’t real, and suspension of disbelief falls apart.</p>

<p>I believe that resources like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/CinemaSins">CinemaSins</a> are a combination of relevance and irrelevance. In regards to that resource in particular, it shows irrelevance when it posits that film should obey all of the rules of the real world in most of its critiques, but shows relevance when it acknowledges a film’s epistemological separateness and shows how that film breaks its own rules.</p>

<h2 id="narrator-as-deity--narrator-as-liar">Narrator as deity / narrator as liar</h2>

<p>Many films employ an explicit narrator, whether by title scroll (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0076759/">Star Wars: A New Hope</a>), voice-over (Princess Irulan and Paul Atreides’ voiceovers in David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0087182/">Dune</a>), by a narrator telling an inner story (Verbal Kint in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0114814/">The Usual Suspects</a>), by physically narrating a written inner story (The Grandfather in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093779/">The Princess Bride</a>), or even a character’s internal soliloquy (the narrator in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0137523/">Fight Club</a>). This is generally done to augment what could otherwise be clumsy and/or ineffectual exposition through other means in the film – or even to give a certain amount of backstory in order to produce enough in-universe knowledge to allow viewers to be sufficiently immersed in the universe which they are presented.</p>

<p>The narrator has a particular type of power and hold over the viewer ; they are the lens with which the fabricated universe of the film is viewed. Even though we are presented with visual and auditory information through picture and sound, the narrator is the <strong>voice of god</strong> (or at least some sort of prophetic voice, if we’re going with the religious metaphor) as far as this universe is concerned. But what if this omnipresent narrator isn’t telling the truth about this universe?</p>

<p>Two extremely visible cases of this occur in David Fincher’s “Fight Club” and Bryan Singer’s “The Usual Suspects”.</p>

<p>In “Fight Club”, we’re led down a paraprosdokian storyline by a nameless author, who not only tells us a story in his droning monotone, but also shows us his misadventures with a character we know as Tyler Durden. Only at the end of the second act do we learn that our author has been lying to us, much as he has been lying to himself. What we have seen as a fully realistic and discernibly physical part of this universe is a figment of the narrator’s imagination. We’re forced to change our view of this film universe as part of an unsettling experience which helps define a major part of the attraction to that film.</p>

<p>In “The Usual Suspects”, we confront a similar situation – except that the narrator (Verbal Kint) is very much aware that he’s misleading both us and Agent Kujan. Our realization comes right after the perceived climax of the film, as Verbal allows Agent Kujan to apparently convince both himself and the audience that the elusive Keyser Soze is really Dean Keaton. Mere moments later, Kujan comes to the realization at which we are meant to arrive ; he has been lied to. This is shocking to the audience because we implicitly trust the narrator to guide us to the truths of the film universe which he inhabits, yet he betrays us, breaking our knowledge of his universe. Even more troubling is that we’re not sure how much of the last few hours has been real (according to the film universe), and how much was made up by the narrator. A false world, inhabited by a virtual deity who hides the nature of that false world with yet another representation.</p>

<p>Yet another power that on-screen narration (in particular) has is that it can provide the film equivalent to the literary “aside” or footnote. Groucho Marx was known for pioneering this form of soliloquy, which came to be known colloquially as “breaking the fourth wall”. It allows the author to speak through his/her characters directly to the audience without the need for voiceover – but it shows the universe <em>stop</em> around the narrator. What they’re saying is so important that their universe <em>literally stops</em> so that you, the captive audience, can bear witness to it. In Woody Allen’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0075686/">Annie Hall</a>, the narrator’s diatribe (aimed directly at the viewing audience, in spite of the people around him) appears to be breaking the fourth wall – but the subject of his anger is revealed to be able to actually <em>hear what he is saying</em>, in contravention of Groucho Marx’s tradition of film asides. Allen then proceeds to almost literally pull a rabbit out of a hat by magically pulling Marshall McLuhan seemingly out of thin air to make his point for him, then resumes his narrative aside. To Allen, the narrative aside is just another platform on which to base a joke, but it speaks to the unspoken acknowledgement that the narrator is aware at some level that he is part of a film universe; he just bends the rules a little.</p>

<h2 id="epistemic-closure-vs-incomplete-epistemology">Epistemic closure vs incomplete epistemology</h2>

<p>Another supposition I’d like to put forward is that epistemic closure in a film universe essentially eliminates a very specific source of tension. “Settling films” (films which leave the viewer with a feeling of completion) tend not to leave unanswered questions, and if it does leave unanswered questions, they’re generally fairly benign or immaterial to substantial portions of the central plot.</p>

<p>On the other hand, we can look at some of the films of Christopher Nolan as examples of intentionally incomplete epistemology. A number of his films employ missing information or information which can be interpreted in a number of different ways to provide differing conclusions or philosophies to his films.</p>

<p>“Inception”, for example, famously ends with a shot of a spinning top which either will or will not fall down to indicate whether the principal character is trapped within a never-ending dream. Depending on whether you believe that he is awake or asleep, it changes the interpretation of the ending. (Nolan had actually said that fixating on the top essentially missed the point of the ending, as Cobb is happy, which is the important part of the conclusion.)</p>

<p>“The Prestige” offers a number of events which can be interpreted in more than one way. The last shot shows a room full of water tanks full of dead clones – or does it? We see that because we <em>want</em> to see it; we want to believe in the magic of Tesla’s invention, no matter how horrifying the potential consequences. The narrator, being Angier for the expositional sequence about Tesla’s machine, may or may not be telling the truth – he is, after all, a magician who would hide his secrets from everyone including the invisible audience. If there is only one body, it could easily have been Angier’s double. We could puzzle over this at length, which gives us a sense of unsettling non-completion.</p>

<p>Perhaps in a “search for more money” (as a certain purveyor of The Schwartz had been known to say), prequels and origin stories for most major film universes have been veritably exploding into existence. <em>(For the sake of some form of brevity, I’m leaving out film reboots and re-imaginings.)</em> The question which should be asked about these expansions and attempts to bring about some form of epistemic closure should not be “is it good?” but rather “is it necessary or right?”</p>

<p>Sometimes prequel films end up completely destroying a venerable mythology (Star Wars Episodes 1-3), and sometimes prequel works add backstory which is more or less completely unnecessary for the comprehension of a character (the “Gotham” and “Hannibal” television series, for example). I posit that incomplete epistemology inherent in film universes provides a tension which underscores certain themes, and this tension and uncertainty dissolves as soon as every important mystery is taken away by subsequent works. You have to know when to explain and when not to explain.</p>

<h2 id="layered-realities-in-film">Layered realities in film</h2>

<p>A popular motif in film has been the story within a story – from <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0015324/">Sherlock Jr</a>’s cameraman dreaming in the booth to Inception’s dreams within dreams, and many more in between. My supposition is that the popularity of this motif, which stems from sentiments like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All the world’s a stage, and all the men and women merely players - “As You Like It”, William Shakespeare</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are many transpositions of external epistemological ideas in non-“story within a story” contexts as well. Examples of this are films like David Lynch’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0166924/">Mulholland Drive</a>, which uses knowledge about the internal workings of Hollywood to inform and shape the story.</p>

<p>A combination of those methods for transposing epistemology into film are also possible; Inception not only has dreams within dreams, but also has characters who <a href="http://www.theawl.com/2010/07/the-key-to-inception-its-a-movie-about-making-movies">mirror the jobs of the people who make film</a>. David Mamet’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120202/">State and Main</a> tells a story-within-a-story (the film which is being made), but also pulls from the reality of filmmaking and Hollywood politics.</p>

<p>One of my favorite auteurs in the realm of mixing epistemologies and conflating fantasy with reality is Terry Gilliam. As an example, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096764/">The Adventures of Baron Munchausen</a> has a series of overlapping and interweaving stories within stories. The Baron’s life and adventures (which may be pure fantasy, and almost surely represent fantasy and imagination in the context of the larger story) are presented as a matter-of-fact stage play which is being used as a diversion from a larger, terrible reality. As the film progresses, we begin to descend into layers of transitions between what we believe is the “real world” of the film and stories-within-stories. The transitions between them are usually not the typical dream sequence transitions; one of the most genius transitions in the film occurs when the Baron begins narrating his own life, and the stage actor playing the Sultan is pushed out onto the stage, to discover that it is no longer the stage, but rather the Sultan’s palace. Gilliam doesn’t really want there to be a solid delineation between reality and imagination, and it shows. By the end of the film, we’re aware that (at least, within the confines of the film’s epistemology) some of the stories must have been somewhat real, but we don’t know which ones or how much of them. Gilliam denies us epistemological closure, and it does not detract from the film – quite the opposite – it defines the nature of the film.</p>

<h2 id="documentary-and-narrative-fallacies-and-truths">Documentary and narrative fallacies and truths</h2>

<p>Documentary filmmaking is another odd case ; it presents itself as a sort of objective narrative truth, whereas in reality documentarians rely on their own subjective narrative truths and fallacies to underscore themes which they believe to be present in reality. The power of documentary film comes from its ability to expose an external epistemology in the guise of objective observation. The majority of documentary films also possess the omnipresent narrator, using him/her as the lens with which to see the universe of the film – but that universe is <em>our</em> universe.</p>

<p>Rather than creating an artificial world and filling it with narrative and knowledge, documentarians use the real world as the substrate to build their own artificial world, but sell it back to us as being the “real world”. It’s much easier to consume documentary film works when we are aware that they are someone’s subjective view of reality, with all of the epistemological baggage that carries.</p>

<h2 id="the-big-lie">The Big Lie</h2>

<p>The Big Lie is that it’s all fake; documentaries and flights of fantasy alike.</p>

<p>We enter into an unspoken and unwritten agreement with the filmmakers to suspend our ability to differentiate the 24 still frames flying past our eyes as individual discrete images, and instead peek into another world with its own laws, knowledge, and history. We all know, somewhere inside us, that it’s all a Big Lie, but we agree to leave our sense of reality, suspend our disbelief, and share in a small piece of something unlike what we’re used to seeing.</p>

<p>The problems with ignoring the separate epistemology of a film is that it can limit our ability to enjoy that film by removing lingering doubts or questions, or possibly coming a little too close or far away from what we understand to be reasonable deviations from our own local experiences.</p>

<p><em>This is continued in a <a href="/2015/03/06/film-epistemology-ii/">subsequent article on epistemology in film</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exposure]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/24/exposure/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T20:11:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/24/exposure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my workup on effective exposure practices for cinematography. It’s an attempt to provide a fairly effective set of practices for ensuring the best consistent image.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="why">Why</h2>

<p>To keep a consistent feel between shots (and overall), there are a few factors which should generally stay the same between shots:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>ISO Sensitivity</strong>. This generally should remain at the “native ISO” level of your camera’s sensor, which is the level at which the sensor exhibits the maximum amount of dynamic range (levels of difference in luma between lightest and darkest areas representable). I’ve been pretty good about shooting most of my footage at 400 ASA, which matches light levels used with the most common traditional film, but this may vary, depending on the camera body you’re using.</li>
  <li><strong>Shutter Speed</strong>. It’s an amateur mistake to unwittingly vary the shutter speed / exposure time between shots, because the way we perceive motion in film is very particular. The majority of film work tends to use a 180 degree “shutter angle”, which corresponds to <code>1 / 2 x fps</code> – which means that with a frame rate of 24 fps, your exposure time / shutter speed would be 1/48th of a second to correspond to a 180 degree shutter angle. (There are obviously exceptions to this basic rule, but it <em>tends</em> to be consistent within a scene.)</li>
  <li><strong>Aperture</strong>. This may not have to remain constant between shots, but you don’t want your aperture settings to be dictated by the amount of light available to you, alone. It’s better to be able to compose a shot artistically, then deal with the amount of light coming into your lens separately. Not to mention that far too many “independent film” cinematographers have gotten a reputation for jacking the aperture all the way open and leaving it there.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="zones-and-the-zone-system">Zones, and the Zone System</h2>

<p>This is an interesting working understanding of light, and how to properly expose, put together by <a href="http://www.anseladams.com/ansel-adams-information/">Ansel Adams</a> and Fred Archer. I’m not going to go into the specifics of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zone_System">Zone System</a>, but it is important to understand the basic concepts to properly understand the rest of this article.</p>

<h2 id="light-metering">Light metering</h2>

<p>I can’t recommend a traditional light meter enough. It’s completely worth the cost, and will save hours of wasted work and blown shots – and generally will tend to be superior, in terms of accuracy, to cellphone apps.</p>

<p>(My light meter is an old manual light meter, which my father gave to me – just showing that it’s not the bells and whistles, but rather the basics which are important to have.)</p>

<h2 id="nd-filters-vari-and-otherwise">ND filters (vari and otherwise)</h2>

<p>So, if you can’t adjust the ISO sensitivity or shutter speed, and shouldn’t be adjusting via the aperture, how do we control our exposure levels?</p>

<p>Enter the <strong>neutral density filter</strong>; sunglasses for your lens. Depending on your rig (and funding levels), you could either use a “vari ND filter” (which is essentially two circular polarizing filters, mounted in a single assembly), or a series of single ND filter sheets of varying ratings (which can be combined to form particular exposure reduction values). Most indie cinematographers tend not to have 4x4 filter slots, so it may be easier, with the notable exception of lens changes, to go with vari ND filters.</p>

<p>I highly recommend the <a href="http://amzn.to/1B6v40h">Tiffen 77VND filter</a> for vari ND work, assuming a 77mm filter thread – which is common amongst a fair amount of cine lenses. (If you’re working with Cooke primes or similar glass, you’re probably not going to be be worried about any of <em>my</em> recommendations, but you’d also probably have to spring for vari ND filters with a larger filter thread size.)</p>

<p>One caveat about ND filters – they have the potential for introducing slight color casts into the picture, which makes grey cards or other white/color balancing equipment even more necessary.</p>

<p>The trick with ND filters is using them to adjust for your Zone V reading, which means understanding how to reliably adjust them to cut down a certain number of stops of light. This is an entire set of tutorials, and another topic, which is best covered elsewhere.</p>

<h2 id="lighting-for-standard-exposure">Lighting for standard exposure</h2>

<p>Medium-to-light skinned people generally are supposed to be exposed for Zone VI (+1 EV), with darker skinned people exposed for Zone V (0 EV). Zone V is pretty easy to expose for, since it essentially means setting exposure for the metering value, but Zone VI needs to be exposed at +1 EV, which means that it should be twice as bright (or a full stop brighter) than the metering value. Exposing this way may leave certain things blown out or underexposed, based on your lighting setup, but it will produce “ideal” skin lighting for a standard well-balanced exposure.</p>

<h2 id="exposing-to-the-left-right-">Exposing to the left, right …</h2>

<p>ETTR maximizes dynamic range by exposing for highlights, and ETTL maximizes dynamic range by exposing for shadows. The former prevents blown highlights, and the latter prevents details from being lost in the shadows. If you decide to use one of these techniques, it should depend on which portions of your image you’re willing to lose details in.</p>

<p>ETTR is very popular, partly due to its ability to hide one of the primary deficiencies inherent in most DSLR and inexpensive digital sensors – the way that highlights immediately clip, rather than gradually rolling off (as they do with film and more expensive sensors).</p>

<p>There are some mitigating techniques which can be used to avoid over-exposure (blowing highlights). Some of the more common ones are:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Gobos</strong> - A simple “go between”, which can be used to block light. This can be made of any opaque material, and only needs to be clamped or secured between the light source and the target object or person.</li>
  <li><strong>Scrims</strong> - A screen used to soften light. This can disperse a hard light source in to a softer one, and is secured much like a gobo. As it does not decrease the amount of light appreciably, but instead spreads it out, this may not be effective for heavy over-exposure.</li>
  <li><strong>ND Film</strong> - Windows can be covered with neutral density film, effectively reducing their light-transmitting capacity. This technique has been used with great effectiveness in a number of bigger budget productions, but can be a little pricey.</li>
  <li><strong>Fill light</strong> - Matched light temperature fill light or bounced fill light can be used to raise the overall exposure level, which will bring higher zones back to a more manageable level. The disadvantage with this technique is that digital sensors tend to like a certain amount of light level variance, or they may produce a seemingly “flat” image.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="variations">Variations</h2>

<p>These techniques are designed to try to produce the widest dynamic range possible for your camera, as well as the widest possible latitude in post-processing for retaining details and image quality. There are a number of circumstances where the “standard” way of doing things could be eschewed in favor of a particular dynamic or idiom. An example would be intentionally losing the background in black to hide a lack of depth or intentionally blowing highlights around an actor to produce an ethereal quality.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Much like other parts of cinematography, there’s no one right way to do things. You don’t <em>have</em> to maintain ISO, aperture, and shutter angle / exposure time – but it can help, depending on what you’re trying to accomplish.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fine Line Between Confidence and Hubris]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T15:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to make sense of two necessarily contrary positions in regard to skill, art, and aesthetics. This is something of which I’ve been trying to make sense for quite some time.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="aesthetics-technique-and-intent">Aesthetics, Technique, and Intent</h2>

<p>The fundamental balance of aesthetics in any art-form is, in my supposition, the balance between the personal sense and the general public sense. This is somewhat necessitated by a very strange mechanism – that of our inherent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">inability to accurately self-assess</a> our own skills and works. I would secondarily posit that art is effectively a combination of <strong>technique</strong> (skill) and <strong>intent</strong>. (Some have additionally added <strong>context</strong> to that, but I’m going to put that aside as an adjunct of intent for now.)</p>

<p>Technique is teachable. Technique is learnable (depending on the amount of time put in, internal aptitudes, etc). Technique is something which, to one degree or another, is somewhat quantifiable. A great deal of education in the arts is devoted to attempting to teach classical techniques, if only for the sake of eventually learning which ones can be accepted and which ones can be disregarded.</p>

<p>Intent, on the other hand, is a really hairy beast. It is <strong>not</strong> able to be deterministically divined from a work in a vacuum. Even more frustrating is that it can be broken into <strong>perceived intent</strong> (how we internalize what we’ve seen, heard, and experienced), and <strong>original intent</strong> (how the artist actually originally intended the art to be consumed). But wait – the original intent can further be broken into <strong>original intent</strong> and <strong>revisionist intent</strong>, where the artist retro-fits an original intent onto a piece for one reason or another – even though it was not originally present in the design and execution phases. (My personal belief is that this is done primary for reasons dealing with popularity, but I don’t have any data to back this up.)</p>

<p>If art is a combination of these two things, how can art be “judged” by others if the original artist’s intent cannot be accurately determined? Should it be consumed and rated based on the perceived intent, which is completely subjective based on the person consuming it?</p>

<h2 id="coming-back-to-confidence-and-hubris">Coming back to Confidence and Hubris</h2>

<p>The next logical question in the context of this reading would be “what does this have to do with the difference between confidence and hubris?”</p>

<p>Confidence is somewhat necessary in the artistic process, as it helps shape the intent of the work. If we have no belief or confidence in what we are doing, it is very difficult to move forward with doing it.</p>

<p>Technique, however, requires a certain amount of humble nature to learn and master. If we believe that we have nothing else to learn, we stop learning. As the source material from Dunning-Kruger concludes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the miscalibration of the incompetent stems from an error about the self, whereas the miscalibration of the highly competent stems from an error about others</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, hubris is a base requirement for successful intent, as we need to believe that what we are doing has some sort of artistic merit, both to ourselves and for the external validation provided by others. We would need to be able to weather the concerns of others to forge our own artistic path.</p>

<p>But technique requires a humility which contradicts that hubris, for if we do not know our place in the grand spectrum of abilities, how can we ever hope to know when we can improve, or how to improve?</p>

<h2 id="societal-homogenization">Societal Homogenization</h2>

<p>To a degree, all artists who come in contact with other art or other artists will experience a level of homogenization of their work. The Millenial generation, replete with Instagram pictures, <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/doge">Doge-level memes</a>, and an inflated sense of self (unencumbered by a history of perceived failures) seem to experience this effect at a greater magnitude than seen before. I’m not sure if this is due to the replicating effect of social networking, an increased population size (similar to the compounding effect of scientific discoveries with larger populations), or some other ancillary effect with which I’m unfamiliar.</p>

<p>I mention societal homogenization of art-forms because it leads me to the next question…</p>

<h2 id="is-it-me-or-is-it-the-world">Is it me, or is it the world?</h2>

<p>The question that I ask is “Is it me, or is it the world?”</p>

<p>If my aesthetic is different than the vast popular aesthetic, am I wrong, or does society at large just have bad taste? I can’t answer that question. If aesthetics are the domain of popular opinion, I’m wrong, and confidence needs to be cut back in favor of humility and a level of homogenization. If original intent is the important part of the equation, I should be forging ahead, allowing confidence (and eventually hubris) to shape the end-products of artistic labor.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do">What do you do?</h2>

<p>I’ve struggled with this – and due to the paradoxical nature of the problem, the only solution I can offer is to make the decision about how to proceed with your art based on <em>your</em> intent. If you’re trying to make a living from your art, primarily, go for the homogenization – you will see better returns from a more commercially viable product. If you’re trying to make “better art”, go your own way – either you will create something which will transcend you or you won’t, but at least you will have made art which is yours.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The danger of the shortcut mentality]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T13:00:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In “<a href="/2013/06/28/skill-in-the-age-of-instagram/">Skill in the Age of Instagram</a>”, I had opined about the lost value of skill sets, and how the modern approach to skills is to “approximate” them with shortcuts like Instagram, Autotune, and Photoshop.</p>

<p>Even though these tools offer the quickest and shortest “path” to the immediate goal, being your current project, they retard your potential growth by limiting your skills and knowledge about what you’re doing. If the pseudo-magic time-saving software is taken away (or encounters a limitation), how will you continue to be able to function without it?</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="in-cinematography">In cinematography</h2>

<p>Cinematography is rife with this kind of intellectual laziness, as all creative fields have a tendency to be. A few of the places I’ve seen this have been:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Cameras</strong>. If you haven’t met a single cinematographer who has lamented that s/he is being held back by his/her rig, you haven’t gotten out very much. I call crap on that argument, mainly because of fine work like <a href="http://erbpfilm.com/film/upstreamcolor">Shane Carruth’s “Upstream Color”</a>. Learn to use what you’ve got, rather than pining for something better / different.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Color correction and grading</strong>. Virtually every amateur forum on color correction and grading is full of people asking where they can get a “one size fits all” <a href="http://nofilmschool.com/2011/05/what-is-a-look-up-table-lut-anyway">LUT</a> which will make their footage look “like Hollywood”. If there was such a thing, the entire industry of color grading specialists would just be wasting their time and skills. There’s even an “Instagram” of sorts for color grading – Magic Bullet Looks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus</strong>. I’m still surprised at the number of people who complain that cameras do not do the focusing work <em>for</em> them. (It’s easier to remind them that, much like other electronics, more expensive things have fewer bells and whistles – and autofocus is a terrible, terrible idea.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Lighting</strong>. As soon as low light cameras capable of cine work, like the A7s, came out, people came crawling out of the woodwork, happy that they no longer would have to worry about learning to light a scene. Putting aside the relative noisiness of the sensors, low light / no light <em>still</em> does not look like actual lit footage.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Falling into these thought pattern “traps” may seem easier at first, but following this “shortcut mentality” doesn’t may off in the long game.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<p>I’m not sure. I have previously said that I believed intellectual laziness or possibly a culture obsessed with instant gratification could be blamed for attempting to take the easy way out. Upon further observation, I cannot isolate a single cause behind the widespread acceptance of these tools and shortcuts, but I’ll iterate through possible causes.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Illusory superiority</strong>. We aren’t very good at figuring out how good or bad we are at something (the concept of illusory superiority contends that we usually overestimate our skill level, and the Dunning-Kruger effect also stipulates that we will eventually <em>under</em>-estimate our skill level, once we’ve gotten past a certain point). It’s one of the reasons why 90% of drivers believe that they’re in the top 10% of the skill curve – and also could help explain why using some of the aforementioned tools has become so prevalent. If we believe we’re in the top percentiles of a skill set, we’ll also believe that whatever we do (as part of our “process”) is, and must be, inherently correct. This can be seen by the inability of many Instagram filter users to understand why their tool is an “easy way out”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Instant gratification</strong>. Our culture, especially the now-pervasive “<a href="http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2014/03/07/millennials-in-adulthood/">millenial generation</a>”, which has come into cultural power with a shorter-than-ever attention span and a lack of any understanding of their own skill levels, thanks to a society hell-bent on issuing participation awards to everyone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Intellectual laziness</strong>. Increasingly, people seem to be less interested in <em>how</em> something works, and simply interested <em>that</em> it works.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>“Keeping up with the Joneses”</strong>. There is a look and feel “arms race”, which closely parallels the <a href="http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/sep11/articles/loudness.htm">loudness war</a>, in that photographers and cinematographers are pressed to try to replicate the look and feel of their Instagrammified and Photoshopped brethren.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The social disease</strong>. No, not “the herp”; the disease of social networking. A seemingly endless desire for likes, “+1”s, shares, and every other type of social networking accolades, has been a driving force in recent years; “<a href="http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/abs/10.1089/cpb.2009.0003">self-status seeking</a>” is one of the primary goals of those who engage in social networking. In efforts to garner the esteem of “friends” and “contacts” on these social networks, users are adopting the lowest common denominator, in many cases, to attempt to appeal to the greatest number of followers.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-the-solution">What’s the solution?</h2>

<p>This is where I’m at a bit of a loss. I’d like to believe that, given time, those who possess the requisite skills of the trade will advance, simply by virtue of having learned to ply their skills more effectively, and those who use “skill approximation” software will drop off, or will continue to produce mediocre or cookie-cutter output.</p>

<p>That being said, it didn’t happen that way with pitch-correction software. Musical artists no longer have to be able to sing in tune (although, you could point at musicians like Bob Dylan to say “they never had to be able to”, but I digress) to be able to rise to the top of the pop music charts, and photographers don’t have to be able to take a clean picture to be able to produce a cover image for a magazine. The exact opposite, in fact, is expected from professional photographers – knowledge of manipulation tools is <em>expected</em>, and some photographers are becoming well known through their Instagram-filtered images.</p>

<p><em>(As an aside, even though I do have an <a href="http://instagram.com/jbuchbinderphotos">Instagram account</a>, I do tag my photos with <strong>#nofilter</strong> and <strong>#noprocessing</strong> to indicate that I do not manipulate them, apart from the forced square ratio imposed by Instagram.)</em></p>

<p>I can only recommend the long road – and I’m going to end this post with a quote that, while it may seem to be a bit cliché, is perfectly apropos:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Two roads diverged in a wood, and I— /
I took the one less traveled by, /
And that has made all the difference.
- “The Road Not Taken”, Robert Frost</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is even more appropriate that the oft-misconstrued sentiment of Frost’s poem was to lament that he had chosen the more difficult route, not to celebrate that he had taken it.</p>

<p>So please, take the long road of learning and discovery, rather than looking for shortcuts ; you’ll be a better, more skilled person for having done so. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
