<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-22T16:20:42-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Preparing for and recovering from disaster]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/13/preparing-for-and-recovering-from-disaster/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-13T20:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/10/13/preparing-for-and-recovering-from-disaster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the greatest nightmares associated with digital cinematography and
photography is that of the specter of data loss. The very notion that your
carefully planned shots or footage could disappear in a single instant can
be Earth-shattering, since it may not be possible to reshoot (or may be
prohibitively expensive). The best defense is to be prepared, not only for
the possibility that you may lose data, but also to safeguard against that
possibility through preventitive measures.</p>

<h2 id="preparation">Preparation</h2>

<p>There are a number of things you can do to try to protect against data loss,
both before and after shooting has taken place. Here are a few of them:</p>

<p><strong>Don’t use dodgy or off-brand memory cards.</strong> This may seem pretty obvious
to those who have been down this road, but really crappy cards tend to have
dodgy QA processes involved in their manufacture, so although you may get a
good card, you’re just as likely to get a dud – which could end up with your
data. I’ve found that “Amazon Basics” and “KomputerBay” cards have failed me
pretty regularly. Even “Transcend” cards have been pretty dodgy for me, on
occasion. I tend to stick with “SanDisk” branded cards, when I use SD media,
and there are a few decent manufacturers of CF media (Lexar, SanDisk, etc),
which tend to produce quality cards, in my experience.</p>

<p><strong>Storage media doesn’t last forever.</strong> Every piece of flash media has a
certain number of R/W cycles before it becomes unstable and/or unusable.
After a period of time, you might want to start regularly replacing your
media cards to avoid the possibility that errors will begin to occur. It’s
also a good idea to low-level format the cards in between uses, which
supposedly increases their lifespan.</p>

<p><strong>A single physical copy of your product is a bad idea.</strong> If you just move
files off to your laptop harddrive, you’re practically expecting something
to destroy your media. A single SSD or spinning platter in a laptop is a
prime target for an accident to wipe out your data. Ideally, a RAID
(<em>R</em>edundant <em>A</em>rray of <em>I</em>nexpensive <em>D</em>isks) array would provide a
good tradeoff between inexpensive media and redundant storage. I built a
pretty inexpensive one with the following components:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/19EmtYA">Sans Digital MR2UT+ MobileRAID</a>: A two-disk
enclosure, which, when set to RAID-1, gives you a set of mirrored
hard disks, accessible by USB 3.0 or an eSATA interface.</li>
  <li><a href="http://amzn.to/19IlAdp">Seagate Barracuda 2 TB HDD</a>: Two of these
disks will provide you with a total of 2 TB of redundant storage.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>A single physical location is a bad idea.</strong> Consider off-site backup. If
you don’t have the money to store your data in <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">S3</a>
or a similar service, consider using something like
<a href="http://labs.bittorrent.com/experiments/sync.html">Bittorrent Sync</a>, with a
friend or two providing remote backup locations. If this isn’t feasible,
periodically backing up to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Linear_Tape">DLT</a>
or another backup tape, then storing that offsite, may be useful. If you
are questioning “why do I need off-site backup”, just remember that a single
fire or natural disaster can destroy all of your hard work…</p>

<p><strong>Camera-based writing solutions.</strong> Certain cameras (the Canon EOS 5D
Mark III, for example) have multiple media card slots, and have the ability
to write multiple copies of the same media. This can help circumvent the
tragic circumstance (to which I have fallen victim) of a completed shoot
with the inability to read any of the captured data later on. To understand
this, <a href="http://protogtech.com/cameras/canon-5d-mark-iii-record-separately-vs-record-to-multiple-performance-comparison/">read more here</a>.
It should be noted that there are some performance limitations to this,
but if you’re not shooting RAW video and your camera body can handle this,
you might want to seriously consider it.</p>

<h2 id="recovery">Recovery</h2>

<p>There is a pantheon of free and open-source software suites which provide
recovery of lost files, deleted files, destroyed partitions, etc. The true
nightmare scenario would involve a piece of damaged media, from which the
data cannot be extracted – but never assume this unless you have exhausted
all other avenues of recovery.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.cgsecurity.org/wiki/PhotoRec">PhotoRec/Testdisk</a> (Open source,
Linux/Windows/Mac/DOS/etc). This is one of my favorites, although it
may potentially require some fairly in-depth technical expertise to
fully exploit its potential.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.piriform.com/recuva">Recuva</a> (Freeware, Windows). Recovers
deleted files.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.hirensbootcd.org">Hiren’s Boot CD</a> (Freeware, Boot Disc).
Hiren’s is a classic recovery and utility boot disk, which can be
booted on any Intel-based computer. The download is free, and it has
a very comprehensive suite of recovery tools. If you don’t have a copy
of this disc hanging around your studio or house – why not?</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.wondershare.com/disk-utility/cr2-photo-recovery.html">Wondershare Photo Recovery</a> (Freeware, Windows/Mac).
A semi-commercial digital media file recovery suite.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.icare-recovery.com/free/camera-raw-photo-recovery-free.html">iCare Recovery Free</a> (Trialware, Windows).
This has a 2GB maximum data file recovery limit with the trial, otherwise
a license has to be purchased.</li>
  <li><a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~oskin/saveimg.html">saveimg</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
Extracts JPEG images from raw disk devices. Requires some expert
knowledge to use properly.</li>
  <li><a href="http://foremost.sourceforge.net/">Foremost</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
Digital forensic tool to recover files based on headers, footers, and
internal data structures.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.lc-tech.com/pc/sandisk-rescuepro-and-rescuepro-deluxe/">SanDisk RescuePRO</a> (Trialware, Windows).
SanDisk’s recommended recovery software.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/ddrescue/ddrescue.html">ddrescue</a> (Opensource, Linux/Mac).
A data recovery tool. It copies data from one file or block device
(hard disc, cdrom, etc) to another, trying hard to rescue data in case
of read errors.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.stellarphotorecoverysoftware.com/camera-recovery/">Stellar Photo Recovery</a> (Trialware, Windows/Mac).
Another digital photo recovery suite. The trialware shows what can be
recovered, with previews.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.pcinspector.de/default.htm?language=1">PC Inspector</a> (Freeware, Windows).</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.prosofteng.com/products/data_rescue.php">DataRescue</a> (Mac).</li>
  <li><a href="http://subrosasoft.com/OSXSoftware/index.php?main_page=product_info&amp;cPath=1&amp;products_id=3">Camera Salvage</a> (Freeware, Windows).</li>
  <li><a href="http://datarescue.com/">PhotoRescue</a> (Windows/Mac).</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.cfcardrecovery.com/">CF Card Recovery</a> (Trialware, Windows/Mac).</li>
</ul>

<p>Hopefully, this will either make it easier to avoid potential data loss, or
at least help to minimize the impact, if and when you end up losing data.</p>

<p>As always, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Composing for Aspect Ratios]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/30/composing-for-aspect-ratios/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T20:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/30/composing-for-aspect-ratios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Aspect ratios, simply put (for those who are unaware), are the ratios between
the width and height of a single frame of video. Television has had a 4:3
ratio (4 units of width to 3 units of height), until the popularization of
“HD” television, using a “widescreen” ratio of 16:9. I’m not going to go
through the entire history of aspect ratios in cinema, as there is a
<a href="http://vimeo.com/68830569">great retrospective available on vimeo</a>.</p>

<p>{% vimeo 68830569 %}</p>

<p>Most DSLR cinematography is done, by default, with a 16:9 ratio, as the
maximum capture size for their video is generally 1920x1080, abbreviated as
1080p (to additionally indicate progressive, rather than interlaced, scan).
It is relatively easy to enforce a “wider” aspect ratio by dropping lines at
the top and bottom of the frame, which most watch-at-home film viewers will
identify as “black bars” at the top and bottom of the frame. This does,
however, introduce an interesting issue – that of composing inside that
frame. That ends up looking something like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/black-bars-aspect-ratio-16-9-21-9-4-3-cinemawide.png" alt="Black bars for different aspect ratios" title="Black bars for different aspect ratios" /></p>

<p>Standard compositional rules generally make use of the two frame diagonals
(top left to bottom right, and bottom left to top right) and both horizontal
and vertical thirds. Most compositional choices for “balanced” frames have
tended to rely on these invisible divisions to create a pleasing image, even
though the rules are really <em>guidelines</em>, and are not absolute. If you, as
a cinematographer, decide that you’re going to use an alternate aspect ratio,
you cannot properly compose by using the thirds or diagonals indicated by any
common guide or viewfinder in 16:9 ratio, as they will result in a vastly
skewed product, compared to the original on-camera image. I’ve seen a number
of forums on DSLR cinematography which had suggested everything from
using a black marker to denote the frame to using black tape to cover the
segments outside of the final crop. A more “modern” solution for Canon
DSLR owners is using <a href="http://magiclantern.wikia.com/wiki/Cropmarks">Magic Lantern cropmarks</a>.
If you’re shooting with another DSLR brand, you may be at the mercy of the
firmware, or any of the aforementioned hacks.</p>

<p><em>NOTE: I’d like to mention, at this point in this article, that there are
other compositional rules, including <a href="http://photoinf.com/Golden_Mean/Eugene_Ilchenko/GoldenSection.html">golden ratio/mean/spiral/rectangle</a>,
so please don’t take the rule of thirds and diagonals to be the only important
and pleasing ways to frame an image….</em></p>

<p>Besides attempting to find a way to follow common compositional rules, there
is another side to aspect ratio: selecting the appropriate one for the story
you are attempting to tell. Apart from the 16:9 ratio being the “standard
format” for HDTV broadcasts and web-based series, it is much taller (i.e.,
it offers more headroom for shots) than Cinemascope (2.35:1) or some of the
other aspect ratios. Depending on the types of shots which you are using to
compose your film, it may be advantageous to have a wider, yet thinner,
view of the world which comes with “shorter” aspect ratios. Again there is
no “one size fits all” for aspect ratios, and it should be a conscious
decision for the material which you are filming.</p>

<p>An added advantage to using a shorter aspect ratio is that, due to the
camera bodies recording the entire frame, regardless of target aspect
ratio, additional editing and recomposition “wiggle room” is available in
the editing and post-production process. If something isn’t framed in the
exact way it should be, this can be corrected later by adjusting the vertical
positioning of the frame within the crop. Most (if not all) NLE software
has vertical positioning, including
<a href="http://help.adobe.com/en_US/premierepro/cs/using/WSC7A162B6-6EF1-49e1-8622-8127366710BB.html">Adobe Premiere</a>,
<a href="http://vegasaur.com/pan-crop-assistant">Sony Vegas</a>,
and <a href="http://www.peachpit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=1677950&amp;seqNum=8">Final Cut Pro</a>,
so you shouldn’t have any issues doing this. I’m aware that the ideal
cinematographer does everything in-camera (as I have vociferously
advocated in past), and does not rely on post-production to fix mistakes,
this does allow for that possibility.</p>

<p>Aspect ratios additionally carry some subconscious baggage with them, due
to the associations we have made with previous material filmed using them,
much in the same way we associate film grain with high-end Hollywood
pictures, even when, in many cases, that film grain was added back to
the digital footage in post-production.</p>

<p>The quick takeaway is that you shouldn’t embark on a project without having
made a conscious decision regarding the aspect ratio which you are using for
that project, considered the ramifications and technical concerns associated
with that decision (including making sure that you can properly frame and
compose shots in that aspect ratio), and storyboarded and/or prepared your
material considering your chosen aspect ratio. It is yet another variable
which can be tweaked to help make an already good project that much better,
and like all power, it comes with responsibility. So, choose –
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oF2UrYSDb3k">but choose wisely</a>, and as
always, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Documentary Filming]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/19/on-documentary-filming/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T16:58:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/19/on-documentary-filming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had the pleasure of shooting for a documentary down in
Birmingham, AL, about one of the people involved in the 
<a href="http://www.nps.gov/nr/travel/civilrights/al11.htm">16th Street Baptist Church Bombing</a>
in 1963. For those who don’t know, that event was one of the most
important parts of the Civil Rights movement in the 1960s. The
50th anniversary of the bombing was this September (2013), so I had
gone with a small film crew to cover the event, and interview some of
the people involved.</p>

<p>I had never shot documentary footage, apart from some small controlled
one-on-one interviews, so this was an interesting learning experience for
me. I’d like to share some of the more important things which I learned
over the course of my experience down there.</p>

<p><strong>Batteries</strong>. You’re going to run out of them. I ran through four batteries
over the course of a filming day – which I thought would be enough, but
weren’t. If you have one thing which requires a strange and unique battery,
you should have at least one spare, even if it’s new. Someone is invariably
going to leave something on, chew up the battery, and leave you short a
vital piece of equipment. If you’re shooting with a DSLR, try to get a
multi-battery grip, so that you don’t have to change batteries as often.</p>

<p><strong>One Shot</strong>. You only have <em>one shot</em> to get event coverage correctly,
which means that, ideally, you should be covering from more than one angle,
to provide not only options in editing, but some sort of redundancy.
Otherwise, you can easily be left with a serious dearth of footage for
what could be a vital part.</p>

<p><strong>Focus and Calibration</strong>. Get there early, get set up, get everything
metered and working properly <em>before</em> things start moving. You really can’t
easily recalibrate during taping without potentially ruining footage. Did
I forget to mention that you only get <em>one shot</em> with event footage?</p>

<p><strong>Depth of Field: More is Better</strong>. You’re not shooting an art piece, you’re
trying to cover something which probably only happens once, so you shouldn’t
be shooting at f/2.8 or something ridiculous like that. Yes, you can sometimes
take advantage of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperfocal_distance">hyperfocal distance</a>
of a lens to keep far-away objects in focus – but you should, most likely,
find a fairly closed aperture to work with. This can be challenging in low
light scenarios, where you’ll be fighting the specter of sensor noise at
extremely high ISO levels when you close the iris more than a little.</p>

<p><strong>Positivity</strong>. You need to be happy and in a good place when shooting people
and interviews, especially in a one-on-one setting. Other people take certain
cues from your body language and demeanor, and hostility will produce
hostility. If at all possible, try to work on documentary projects which you
like, or identify with.</p>

<p><strong>Lens Changes</strong>. If you can avoid it, don’t. Wear cargo pants or a vest with
lens pockets, much like most photographers, if you absolutely <em>must</em> change
lenses. If you’re shooting a long distance, go with something like the
<a href="http://amzn.to/14nI8Cm">Canon EF 70-200mm f/2.8L IS II USM</a> lens, or if you
are dealing with shorter distances, the
<a href="http://amzn.to/189gQmi">Canon EF 24-70mm f/2.8L II USM</a> lens. Carrying a few
primes around will work well for static interview shots, but they’re going to
be a real pain when you’re dealing with moving targets, no matter how quick
you are with focus peaking assistance. If you’re shooting with a shoulder rig,
you’re going to want an IS/VR lens, if you have one available – it cuts down
on a lot of shudder and shake.</p>

<p><strong>Bring a Spare</strong>. Got one lav mic? You might want to bring a second one.
If there’s a small piece of equipment or accessory which, if missing, could
screw you, it’s going to go missing. Especially when you’re far from home
base and without the benefit of an equipment store.</p>

<p><strong>You’re Going To Mess Up</strong>. This is pretty obvious – no matter how careful
you are, something is going to get messed up. The trick is to try to make
everything redundant enough that it doesn’t matter.</p>

<p><strong>It’s Not About Your Equipment</strong>. Someone there is going to have a better
camera, better lenses, and better <em>everything</em> than you have. Go far enough,
and your rig is going to look bad to someone. Just remember, you’re there for
a reason, so know your equipment, and use it as well as you can.</p>

<p><strong>Rocking Out</strong>. If you’re interviewing someone who is rocking back and forth,
bring it to their attention. It creates massive focusing, framing, and
perspective issues. Don’t be intimidated; they can rock as much as they’d
like, just as soon as you’re done filming.</p>

<p><strong>Network</strong>. If you’re looking for an interview with someone, talking to
some of the people around them may lead you to another interviewee who may
produce even better results. There’s no cost associated with being polite.</p>

<p><strong>Respect the Eyeline</strong>. For static interviews, don’t shoot up or down on
someone’s eye-line unless you are trying to indicate something about that
person. You should be even with their eye-line on initial shot setup. This
is also a good idea when doing non-static interviews, when possible.</p>

<p><strong>Make Two Copies</strong>. When you transfer the data off of your memory cards,
make two copies, and if possible, don’t transport them together. Redundancy
is the name of the game here, since even the best footage means diddly/squat
if no one ever gets to see it.</p>

<p><strong>Bring a Sound Guy</strong>. I know, you don’t think you need one – you’ve got a
lav mic, right? A sound engineer is half of your production, since you’re in
charge of the visuals. Also, boom mic operators generally should be fairly
competent sound engineers, to avoid issues later on in the post-production
process – when possible.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t Go For The Cheaper Chicken</strong>. When booking accommodations, don’t go
for the least expensive hotel – there’s a good chance that it’s in a dodgy
part of town, and that extra 10 dollars a night might buy you not only a
bit of security, but might buy you a better night’s sleep. Protip: the
cheapest hotel is generally right next to a) train tracks with 24-hour train
service, b) an open-air coal mine, c) a condemned house with mysterious
block parties at all hours of the night, or d) all of the above…</p>

<p><strong>Get Stills</strong>. If you’re doing a documentary with a bunch of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ken_Burns_effect">Ken Burns effect</a> style
picture montages, you should try to either take stills yourself, or have
another camera operator capture some for you. If you can, attempt to take
pictures of landmarks or buildings when they are not occupied, unless it
specifically works in your storytelling to have them occupied or surrounded.</p>

<p>There are many, many more things to think about when it comes to filming
documentaries and documentary footage – but hopefully, these bullet points
will help someone else avoid some of the pitfalls I experienced on my first
documentary shoot. Good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Are you a cinematographer or a camera operator?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/are-you-a-cinematographer-or-a-camera-operator/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T21:55:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/are-you-a-cinematographer-or-a-camera-operator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There’s only a slight difference in the textbook definition between a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinematographer">cinematographer</a> and a
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camera_operator">camera operator</a>. Besides the
slight variance in responsibilities (a cinematographer/DP can be responsible
for several camera operators), there are some additional skills and
aptitudes which play into the decision to try to be a cinematographer.</p>

<p>None of this is meant to downplay the skill and experience which make a
great camera operator. Knowing your equipment, being able to choose the
proper lenses and camera settings, being able to operate that equipment,
being able to interpret the direction of both the director and the
cinematographer, and being able to hold together a cohesive shot –
these are all the hallmarks of a great camera operator.</p>

<p>At a much, much more basic level, there’s an <em>art</em> to cinematography, which
transcends the physical manipulations of the equipment involved, and becomes
more about creating a sort of separate reality; that of capturing a little
slice of time and space, motion and stillness, light and dark, vibrant
colors and subtle undertones. That’s the part of this that, to me, offers
the most promising creativity and the most fulfilling, yet burdening, tasks.</p>

<p>It’s very easy to get lost in the minutiae of camera settings adjustments,
equipment acquisition, troubleshooting and stabilization, among other
demons – but the <em>art</em> is the derivative of those functions.</p>

<p>To properly illustrate this, I think of a concert I attended, quite a few
years ago. The guitarist, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/VernonReid">Vernon Reid</a>,
was (and still is), an amazing technical instrumentalist. I watched him dance
over the semi-circle of effects pedals and boxes, his hands moving,
seemingly effortlessly over the six strings on his instrument. It struck me
as astounding. We are all, in some way, capable of recognizing genius and
immense skill, even if we cannot reproduce it, or explain it in purely
quantifiable terms. In that way, the body of his technical skills simply
became a foundation for the <em>art</em> which was made by way of them. I wish I
could explain it better – I only know that I could recognize it when I saw
it. The man himself, whom I had the pleasure of speaking with for a few
brief moments, was very humble and very “zen” about his skill and his art.</p>

<p>Due to my particular circumstances, I’ve been able to pick and choose projects,
more of late, specifically based on their relative merits to me. As such, I
haven’t had much experience acting strictly as a “camera operator”. There
may be some hubris, on my part, which would have come out of getting to
perform the artistic duties of a cinematographer on the vast majority of the
projects on which I’ve been involved. It has given me an affinity for the
creative aspects of the job. For as long as I’ve been involved with
cinematography, I have always assumed that being a “camera operator” has been
a step towards being a cinematographer; a way of honing the technical
foundation of the craft, so that the art can come later. It seemed like an
“apprenticeship”, much as the old focus pullers became second unit
cameramen, to eventually move up to first units, then perhaps aspire to
become a cinematographer one day…</p>

<p>The landscape, mostly due to the explosion of low-cost cinematography
(fueled primarily by DSLR cinematography), has been shifting away from that
old model. Most projects have one, perhaps two camera operators – and the
primary camera operator is usually the cinematographer/DP. Many projects
don’t even <em>have</em> a second camera operator – it simply isn’t required.</p>

<p>Ultimately, it depends what your plans and/or revenue model is.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you want to learn more about how to get your equipment to perform
the way you want it to perform, you may do well working as a camera
operator with a seasoned cinematographer, rather than holding out for
a DP position on a project.</li>
  <li>If you want to make a living behind a camera, you can’t really differentiate
between cinematography and camera operator work – at least as long as
you want to keep a steady revenue stream up. Even the best cinematographers
can moonlight as strict “camera operators” when the pay is right.</li>
  <li>If you want to work in a lower pressure environment, you might want to
be a camera operator. Cinematographers are responsible for everything
visual which goes on in a project, and it can be a lot of stress.</li>
  <li>If you feel passionate enough about a project to want to be involved at
any cost, you might sign on as a camera operator.</li>
</ul>

<p>Even though there’s a lot of competition for certain spots on certain
projects, we’re all on the same team; we all (for the most part) are
interested in shooting great footage, and many of us are concerned about
creating enduring works of art, wherever possible. We all have great
potential for growth, so whatever your career and job choice, good luck!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prime Lenses and Proper Depth of Field]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/prime-lenses-and-proper-depth-of-field/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T13:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2013/09/10/prime-lenses-and-proper-depth-of-field</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Depth of field is a massively misunderstood “side effect” of iris size, and
an ultimately useful storytelling tool (when used properly).</p>

<p>DSLR photography has spawned a large group of cinematographers who are
dealing with largely light-insensitive camera sensors (usually producing
fairly unacceptable noise when used at greater sensitivies than ISO 800).
This has created a need for “fast” lenses, which are lenses which have very
large maximum apertures, featuring maximum f-stop ratings like f/2.0, f/1.8,
and even f/1.4 (there are even some <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/news/2013/08/06/kubrick-s-f-0-7-lenses-now-available-for-rent-but-start-saving-up">f/0.7 lenses</a> out there, but I’m
sticking to the realm of affordable DSLR cinematography, at the moment).
Using firmware like <a href="http://magiclantern.fm/">Magic Lantern</a> allows us to use
focus peaking to exploit manual-focus and non-EF mount lenses (for those
Canon-philes among us), to bring down the effective cost of shooting “fast”
lenses. I have some M42 “Pentax screw-mount” lenses which open to f/2.8 –
acquired for less than 10 USD each, plus a 7 USD <a href="http://amzn.to/1fVPGyf">M42-to-EF adapter ring</a>.
If you’re interested in more information on how to use focus peaking, check
out <a href="http://fstoppers.com/using-magic-lantern-with-focus-peaking-for-free-lensing">how it works</a>.</p>

<p>So, you’ve beaten high-cost DSLR and cinema camera body manufacturers by
using “fast” lenses, right? Well, not so fast, there… You have to consider
the <em>side effect</em> of fast lenses and wide apertures: the shallow depth of
field. It’s both a blessing and a curse; we tend to associate shallow depth
of field images and video with expensive equipment (rightfully so, in most
cases) and a more personal type of image, but those lenses are not
universally usable “wide open”. Many shots come off looking amateurish and
ill-composed, when half of the subjects are out of focus, because they’ve
exceeded the edges of the “sharp” area in the focus range.</p>

<p>(There’s also lack of lens sharpness and chromatic abberation to consider,
which are generally present, to some degree, in the widest aperture settings
available on most lenses. That’s a very intensely technical discussion,
however, and will probably be reserved for a future posting.)</p>

<p>When considering the depth of field you want, consider the subject (or
literal <em>focus</em>) of the shot, and figure out how much of the shot needs to
be in focus to properly tell your story. The depth of field is very
important for exposing the mise-en-scène in the way which best represents
both the explicit visuals and external representation of internal
character development and exposition. If your character needs to “pop”
out of the scenery, a narrow DOF would be perfect – but if they are to
appear as a figurative cog in the machinery of the world, you’re probably
going to be looking for the widest DOF (approaching infinity) as you can
get. When widening the DOF like this, you’ll most likely have to compensate
by boosting the ambient lighting, or adding additional lighting, to
adjust for the decreased light hitting your camera sensor.</p>

<p>There are a number of tools for figuring out the proper DOF for a certain
shot, based on the camera/sensor, lens focal length, and distance to
primary focal point.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/dofjs.html">Web-based DOF calculator</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/android.html">Android calculator</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dofmaster.com/iphone.html">iOS calculator</a></li>
</ul>

<p>There are more of them, but if you specify the variables, you can adjust
the aperture f-stop to the widest setting which properly fits the scene
and visuals which you’re attempting to achieve.</p>

<p>Like anything else, this isn’t strictly an instructional A-to-B guide on
how to achieve stunning visuals; it’s simply an attempt to share some of
what I’ve learned, and to help share the knowledge and tools to exploit
your own inner artistic vision. Good luck shooting!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
