<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cinematography | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/cinematography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-24T23:31:54-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exposure]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/24/exposure/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-24T20:11:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/24/exposure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my workup on effective exposure practices for cinematography. It’s an attempt to provide a fairly effective set of practices for ensuring the best consistent image.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why</h2>

<p>To keep a consistent feel between shots (and overall), there are a few factors which should generally stay the same between shots:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>ISO Sensitivity</strong>. This generally should remain at the “native ISO” level of your camera’s sensor, which is the level at which the sensor exhibits the maximum amount of dynamic range (levels of difference in luma between lightest and darkest areas representable). I’ve been pretty good about shooting most of my footage at 400 ASA, which matches light levels used with the most common traditional film, but this may vary, depending on the camera body you’re using.</li>
  <li><strong>Shutter Speed</strong>. It’s an amateur mistake to unwittingly vary the shutter speed / exposure time between shots, because the way we perceive motion in film is very particular. The majority of film work tends to use a 180 degree “shutter angle”, which corresponds to <code>1 / 2 x fps</code> – which means that with a frame rate of 24 fps, your exposure time / shutter speed would be 1/48th of a second to correspond to a 180 degree shutter angle. (There are obviously exceptions to this basic rule, but it <em>tends</em> to be consistent within a scene.)</li>
  <li><strong>Aperture</strong>. This may not have to remain constant between shots, but you don’t want your aperture settings to be dictated by the amount of light available to you, alone. It’s better to be able to compose a shot artistically, then deal with the amount of light coming into your lens separately. Not to mention that far too many “independent film” cinematographers have gotten a reputation for jacking the aperture all the way open and leaving it there.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="zones-and-the-zone-system">Zones, and the Zone System</h2>

<p>This is an interesting working understanding of light, and how to properly expose, put together by <a href="http://www.anseladams.com/ansel-adams-information/">Ansel Adams</a> and Fred Archer. I’m not going to go into the specifics of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zone_System">Zone System</a>, but it is important to understand the basic concepts to properly understand the rest of this article.</p>

<h2 id="light-metering">Light metering</h2>

<p>I can’t recommend a traditional light meter enough. It’s completely worth the cost, and will save hours of wasted work and blown shots – and generally will tend to be superior, in terms of accuracy, to cellphone apps.</p>

<p>(My light meter is an old manual light meter, which my father gave to me – just showing that it’s not the bells and whistles, but rather the basics which are important to have.)</p>

<h2 id="nd-filters-vari-and-otherwise">ND filters (vari and otherwise)</h2>

<p>So, if you can’t adjust the ISO sensitivity or shutter speed, and shouldn’t be adjusting via the aperture, how do we control our exposure levels?</p>

<p>Enter the <strong>neutral density filter</strong>; sunglasses for your lens. Depending on your rig (and funding levels), you could either use a “vari ND filter” (which is essentially two circular polarizing filters, mounted in a single assembly), or a series of single ND filter sheets of varying ratings (which can be combined to form particular exposure reduction values). Most indie cinematographers tend not to have 4x4 filter slots, so it may be easier, with the notable exception of lens changes, to go with vari ND filters.</p>

<p>I highly recommend the <a href="http://amzn.to/1B6v40h">Tiffen 77VND filter</a> for vari ND work, assuming a 77mm filter thread – which is common amongst a fair amount of cine lenses. (If you’re working with Cooke primes or similar glass, you’re probably not going to be be worried about any of <em>my</em> recommendations, but you’d also probably have to spring for vari ND filters with a larger filter thread size.)</p>

<p>One caveat about ND filters – they have the potential for introducing slight color casts into the picture, which makes grey cards or other white/color balancing equipment even more necessary.</p>

<p>The trick with ND filters is using them to adjust for your Zone V reading, which means understanding how to reliably adjust them to cut down a certain number of stops of light. This is an entire set of tutorials, and another topic, which is best covered elsewhere.</p>

<h2 id="lighting-for-standard-exposure">Lighting for standard exposure</h2>

<p>Medium-to-light skinned people generally are supposed to be exposed for Zone VI (+1 EV), with darker skinned people exposed for Zone V (0 EV). Zone V is pretty easy to expose for, since it essentially means setting exposure for the metering value, but Zone VI needs to be exposed at +1 EV, which means that it should be twice as bright (or a full stop brighter) than the metering value. Exposing this way may leave certain things blown out or underexposed, based on your lighting setup, but it will produce “ideal” skin lighting for a standard well-balanced exposure.</p>

<h2 id="exposing-to-the-left-right-">Exposing to the left, right …</h2>

<p>ETTR maximizes dynamic range by exposing for highlights, and ETTL maximizes dynamic range by exposing for shadows. The former prevents blown highlights, and the latter prevents details from being lost in the shadows. If you decide to use one of these techniques, it should depend on which portions of your image you’re willing to lose details in.</p>

<p>ETTR is very popular, partly due to its ability to hide one of the primary deficiencies inherent in most DSLR and inexpensive digital sensors – the way that highlights immediately clip, rather than gradually rolling off (as they do with film and more expensive sensors).</p>

<p>There are some mitigating techniques which can be used to avoid over-exposure (blowing highlights). Some of the more common ones are:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Gobos</strong> - A simple “go between”, which can be used to block light. This can be made of any opaque material, and only needs to be clamped or secured between the light source and the target object or person.</li>
  <li><strong>Scrims</strong> - A screen used to soften light. This can disperse a hard light source in to a softer one, and is secured much like a gobo. As it does not decrease the amount of light appreciably, but instead spreads it out, this may not be effective for heavy over-exposure.</li>
  <li><strong>ND Film</strong> - Windows can be covered with neutral density film, effectively reducing their light-transmitting capacity. This technique has been used with great effectiveness in a number of bigger budget productions, but can be a little pricey.</li>
  <li><strong>Fill light</strong> - Matched light temperature fill light or bounced fill light can be used to raise the overall exposure level, which will bring higher zones back to a more manageable level. The disadvantage with this technique is that digital sensors tend to like a certain amount of light level variance, or they may produce a seemingly “flat” image.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="variations">Variations</h2>

<p>These techniques are designed to try to produce the widest dynamic range possible for your camera, as well as the widest possible latitude in post-processing for retaining details and image quality. There are a number of circumstances where the “standard” way of doing things could be eschewed in favor of a particular dynamic or idiom. An example would be intentionally losing the background in black to hide a lack of depth or intentionally blowing highlights around an actor to produce an ethereal quality.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Much like other parts of cinematography, there’s no one right way to do things. You don’t <em>have</em> to maintain ISO, aperture, and shutter angle / exposure time – but it can help, depending on what you’re trying to accomplish.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Fine Line Between Confidence and Hubris]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T15:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/01/15/the-fine-line-between-confidence-and-hubris</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been trying to make sense of two necessarily contrary positions in regard to skill, art, and aesthetics. This is something of which I’ve been trying to make sense for quite some time.</p>

<h2 id="aesthetics-technique-and-intent">Aesthetics, Technique, and Intent</h2>

<p>The fundamental balance of aesthetics in any art-form is, in my supposition, the balance between the personal sense and the general public sense. This is somewhat necessitated by a very strange mechanism – that of our inherent <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect">inability to accurately self-assess</a> our own skills and works. I would secondarily posit that art is effectively a combination of <strong>technique</strong> (skill) and <strong>intent</strong>. (Some have additionally added <strong>context</strong> to that, but I’m going to put that aside as an adjunct of intent for now.)</p>

<p>Technique is teachable. Technique is learnable (depending on the amount of time put in, internal aptitudes, etc). Technique is something which, to one degree or another, is somewhat quantifiable. A great deal of education in the arts is devoted to attempting to teach classical techniques, if only for the sake of eventually learning which ones can be accepted and which ones can be disregarded.</p>

<p>Intent, on the other hand, is a really hairy beast. It is <strong>not</strong> able to be deterministically divined from a work in a vacuum. Even more frustrating is that it can be broken into <strong>perceived intent</strong> (how we internalize what we’ve seen, heard, and experienced), and <strong>original intent</strong> (how the artist actually originally intended the art to be consumed). But wait – the original intent can further be broken into <strong>original intent</strong> and <strong>revisionist intent</strong>, where the artist retro-fits an original intent onto a piece for one reason or another – even though it was not originally present in the design and execution phases. (My personal belief is that this is done primary for reasons dealing with popularity, but I don’t have any data to back this up.)</p>

<p>If art is a combination of these two things, how can art be “judged” by others if the original artist’s intent cannot be accurately determined? Should it be consumed and rated based on the perceived intent, which is completely subjective based on the person consuming it?</p>

<h2 id="coming-back-to-confidence-and-hubris">Coming back to Confidence and Hubris</h2>

<p>The next logical question in the context of this reading would be “what does this have to do with the difference between confidence and hubris?”</p>

<p>Confidence is somewhat necessary in the artistic process, as it helps shape the intent of the work. If we have no belief or confidence in what we are doing, it is very difficult to move forward with doing it.</p>

<p>Technique, however, requires a certain amount of humble nature to learn and master. If we believe that we have nothing else to learn, we stop learning. As the source material from Dunning-Kruger concludes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>the miscalibration of the incompetent stems from an error about the self, whereas the miscalibration of the highly competent stems from an error about others</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, hubris is a base requirement for successful intent, as we need to believe that what we are doing has some sort of artistic merit, both to ourselves and for the external validation provided by others. We would need to be able to weather the concerns of others to forge our own artistic path.</p>

<p>But technique requires a humility which contradicts that hubris, for if we do not know our place in the grand spectrum of abilities, how can we ever hope to know when we can improve, or how to improve?</p>

<h2 id="societal-homogenization">Societal Homogenization</h2>

<p>To a degree, all artists who come in contact with other art or other artists will experience a level of homogenization of their work. The Millenial generation, replete with Instagram pictures, <a href="http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/doge">Doge-level memes</a>, and an inflated sense of self (unencumbered by a history of perceived failures) seem to experience this effect at a greater magnitude than seen before. I’m not sure if this is due to the replicating effect of social networking, an increased population size (similar to the compounding effect of scientific discoveries with larger populations), or some other ancillary effect with which I’m unfamiliar.</p>

<p>I mention societal homogenization of art-forms because it leads me to the next question…</p>

<h2 id="is-it-me-or-is-it-the-world">Is it me, or is it the world?</h2>

<p>The question that I ask is “Is it me, or is it the world?”</p>

<p>If my aesthetic is different than the vast popular aesthetic, am I wrong, or does society at large just have bad taste? I can’t answer that question. If aesthetics are the domain of popular opinion, I’m wrong, and confidence needs to be cut back in favor of humility and a level of homogenization. If original intent is the important part of the equation, I should be forging ahead, allowing confidence (and eventually hubris) to shape the end-products of artistic labor.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do">What do you do?</h2>

<p>I’ve struggled with this – and due to the paradoxical nature of the problem, the only solution I can offer is to make the decision about how to proceed with your art based on <em>your</em> intent. If you’re trying to make a living from your art, primarily, go for the homogenization – you will see better returns from a more commercially viable product. If you’re trying to make “better art”, go your own way – either you will create something which will transcend you or you won’t, but at least you will have made art which is yours.</p>

<p>Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The danger of the shortcut mentality]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T13:00:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/16/the-danger-of-the-shortcut-mentality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In “<a href="/2013/06/28/skill-in-the-age-of-instagram/">Skill in the Age of Instagram</a>”, I had opined about the lost value of skill sets, and how the modern approach to skills is to “approximate” them with shortcuts like Instagram, Autotune, and Photoshop.</p>

<p>Even though these tools offer the quickest and shortest “path” to the immediate goal, being your current project, they retard your potential growth by limiting your skills and knowledge about what you’re doing. If the pseudo-magic time-saving software is taken away (or encounters a limitation), how will you continue to be able to function without it?</p>

<h2 id="in-cinematography">In cinematography</h2>

<p>Cinematography is rife with this kind of intellectual laziness, as all creative fields have a tendency to be. A few of the places I’ve seen this have been:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Cameras</strong>. If you haven’t met a single cinematographer who has lamented that s/he is being held back by his/her rig, you haven’t gotten out very much. I call crap on that argument, mainly because of fine work like <a href="http://erbpfilm.com/film/upstreamcolor">Shane Carruth’s “Upstream Color”</a>. Learn to use what you’ve got, rather than pining for something better / different.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Color correction and grading</strong>. Virtually every amateur forum on color correction and grading is full of people asking where they can get a “one size fits all” <a href="http://nofilmschool.com/2011/05/what-is-a-look-up-table-lut-anyway">LUT</a> which will make their footage look “like Hollywood”. If there was such a thing, the entire industry of color grading specialists would just be wasting their time and skills. There’s even an “Instagram” of sorts for color grading – Magic Bullet Looks.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus</strong>. I’m still surprised at the number of people who complain that cameras do not do the focusing work <em>for</em> them. (It’s easier to remind them that, much like other electronics, more expensive things have fewer bells and whistles – and autofocus is a terrible, terrible idea.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Lighting</strong>. As soon as low light cameras capable of cine work, like the A7s, came out, people came crawling out of the woodwork, happy that they no longer would have to worry about learning to light a scene. Putting aside the relative noisiness of the sensors, low light / no light <em>still</em> does not look like actual lit footage.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Falling into these thought pattern “traps” may seem easier at first, but following this “shortcut mentality” doesn’t may off in the long game.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<p>I’m not sure. I have previously said that I believed intellectual laziness or possibly a culture obsessed with instant gratification could be blamed for attempting to take the easy way out. Upon further observation, I cannot isolate a single cause behind the widespread acceptance of these tools and shortcuts, but I’ll iterate through possible causes.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Illusory superiority</strong>. We aren’t very good at figuring out how good or bad we are at something (the concept of illusory superiority contends that we usually overestimate our skill level, and the Dunning-Kruger effect also stipulates that we will eventually <em>under</em>-estimate our skill level, once we’ve gotten past a certain point). It’s one of the reasons why 90% of drivers believe that they’re in the top 10% of the skill curve – and also could help explain why using some of the aforementioned tools has become so prevalent. If we believe we’re in the top percentiles of a skill set, we’ll also believe that whatever we do (as part of our “process”) is, and must be, inherently correct. This can be seen by the inability of many Instagram filter users to understand why their tool is an “easy way out”.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Instant gratification</strong>. Our culture, especially the now-pervasive “<a href="http://www.pewsocialtrends.org/2014/03/07/millennials-in-adulthood/">millenial generation</a>”, which has come into cultural power with a shorter-than-ever attention span and a lack of any understanding of their own skill levels, thanks to a society hell-bent on issuing participation awards to everyone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Intellectual laziness</strong>. Increasingly, people seem to be less interested in <em>how</em> something works, and simply interested <em>that</em> it works.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>“Keeping up with the Joneses”</strong>. There is a look and feel “arms race”, which closely parallels the <a href="http://www.soundonsound.com/sos/sep11/articles/loudness.htm">loudness war</a>, in that photographers and cinematographers are pressed to try to replicate the look and feel of their Instagrammified and Photoshopped brethren.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The social disease</strong>. No, not “the herp”; the disease of social networking. A seemingly endless desire for likes, “+1”s, shares, and every other type of social networking accolades, has been a driving force in recent years; “<a href="http://online.liebertpub.com/doi/abs/10.1089/cpb.2009.0003">self-status seeking</a>” is one of the primary goals of those who engage in social networking. In efforts to garner the esteem of “friends” and “contacts” on these social networks, users are adopting the lowest common denominator, in many cases, to attempt to appeal to the greatest number of followers.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-the-solution">What’s the solution?</h2>

<p>This is where I’m at a bit of a loss. I’d like to believe that, given time, those who possess the requisite skills of the trade will advance, simply by virtue of having learned to ply their skills more effectively, and those who use “skill approximation” software will drop off, or will continue to produce mediocre or cookie-cutter output.</p>

<p>That being said, it didn’t happen that way with pitch-correction software. Musical artists no longer have to be able to sing in tune (although, you could point at musicians like Bob Dylan to say “they never had to be able to”, but I digress) to be able to rise to the top of the pop music charts, and photographers don’t have to be able to take a clean picture to be able to produce a cover image for a magazine. The exact opposite, in fact, is expected from professional photographers – knowledge of manipulation tools is <em>expected</em>, and some photographers are becoming well known through their Instagram-filtered images.</p>

<p><em>(As an aside, even though I do have an <a href="http://instagram.com/jbuchbinderphotos">Instagram account</a>, I do tag my photos with <strong>#nofilter</strong> and <strong>#noprocessing</strong> to indicate that I do not manipulate them, apart from the forced square ratio imposed by Instagram.)</em></p>

<p>I can only recommend the long road – and I’m going to end this post with a quote that, while it may seem to be a bit cliché, is perfectly apropos:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Two roads diverged in a wood, and I— /
I took the one less traveled by, /
And that has made all the difference.
- “The Road Not Taken”, Robert Frost</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is even more appropriate that the oft-misconstrued sentiment of Frost’s poem was to lament that he had chosen the more difficult route, not to celebrate that he had taken it.</p>

<p>So please, take the long road of learning and discovery, rather than looking for shortcuts ; you’ll be a better, more skilled person for having done so. Good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Importance of Failure]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/11/the-importance-of-failure/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T20:04:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/12/11/the-importance-of-failure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Failing is a terrible thing, we are taught. As a result of inherent cognitive biases and our own illusory superiority (look up the <a href="http://www.spring.org.uk/2012/06/the-dunning-kruger-effect-why-the-incompetent-dont-know-theyre-incompetent.php">Dunning-Kruger effect</a>, if you’re curious about this), we believe that we are right the majority of times, that we are more skilled than those around us, and that we have nothing of import to learn from not succeeding.</p>

<p>I’m going to uncharacteristically detour into a quick anecdote. I was attending a film festival a little while ago, and had ended up talking to one of the festival’s organizers. She had asked me about how I got into film, and talked a little bit about some of her own projects. After a while, I mentioned how I learned more from my failures than I did from my successes. She stopped the line of conversion, and said that she didn’t, because she “always” succeeded.</p>

<p>There’s a lesson to be learned from her. If you never fail (or never allow yourself to be put in a situation when you fail, or never accept that you have failed), you aren’t going to be able to examine your process to figure out how you can improve. If we’re at the height of our skill set at the present moment, I view that assessment as a dismal failure; we should always expect that, given time and effort, we should continue to improve as time goes on.</p>

<p>I don’t necessarily <em>hate</em> everything I’ve done in past projects, but can instead view my previous work as evolutionary improvement. Every project I do should be the best work I’ve done <em>so far</em>, and if it isn’t, I should be taking steps to make sure that the next one is.</p>

<h2 id="understanding-failure-and-criticism">Understanding Failure and Criticism</h2>

<p>We do not accept criticism well – especially not as artists. Most of our work is, to some degree, very personal. We then view attacks on our work as attacks on some part of ourselves, and become much more defensive than we should be.</p>

<p><strong>Cognitive bias</strong> is a serious issue with us accepting criticism, or any differing points of view from our own. Without getting into too much detail about the mechanics of cognitive bias, it is important to emphasize the importance of recognizing that we all possess it, to one degree or another.</p>

<p><strong>High expectations</strong> tends to result in a feeling of having failed at a much deeper level than the project at hand. A very insightful person had written (about film festival contests, in particular) that you had to be committed to making the best thing you could, not winning. It may not sound like a lot of inherent difference, but stripping your expectations for a project can allow you to be much more free in your ability to execute that project.</p>

<p><strong>People who criticize or critique can help you.</strong> Every failure which is left without analysis is a missed opportunity. You cannot learn from your missteps and mistakes without looking at them with a critical eye. A third party with less vested interest in you and your project can give you the perspective you need to improve.</p>

<h2 id="post-mortem-analyses">Post Mortem Analyses</h2>

<p>I come from a pretty heavy information technology background, and one of the favorite “failure analysis” tools we tend to use after something breaks is something called a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postmortem_documentation">post mortem</a>, which is short for “post mortem documentation”. It involves a rigorous process of analyzing key elements which were responsible for both successful and unsuccessful aspects of a project or event.</p>

<p>For example, I performed both a post mortem on our <a href="/2014/05/07/48-hours-with-the-blackmagic-production-camera-4k/">2014 48 Hour Boston Festival project</a>, which documented some of the things I learned about working with a new camera body, as well as working under tight time constraints, and a post mortem on our <a href="/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project/">2014 48 Hour Providence Horror Festival project</a>, which took home a number of awards, including “Best Film”. Even the analysis of our <strong>successful</strong> project found issues which needed to be addressed before our next project.</p>

<h2 id="your-worst-critic">Your Worst Critic</h2>

<p>… is you (or at least, it should be). You need to be the harshest critic you have.</p>

<p>The rationale I give for this is that you cannot rely on those intrinsically involved in either your professional or personal life, who all have some sort of stake in how well you do something, to be critical enough of what you do. If you can’t expect complete, harsh honesty from those around you – then <em>you</em> are going to have to try to be as harsh as possible with what you’re putting out.</p>

<p><em>(Yes, I’m aware that the younger generation has been indoctrinated, to a certain point, with the notion that everything they do is the best, most awesome, most <strong>EPIC</strong> thing that any human being has ever done – but if you want to succeed artistically, you’ve got to overcome that.)</em></p>

<h2 id="avoid-negativity">Avoid Negativity</h2>

<p>Failure doesn’t have to be a negative thing. Any experience from which we learn a valuable lesson or draw potential improvement from should not be a negative experience. Much like the rest of life, this isn’t the end product of what you’re capable of. It isn’t the last, greatest thing you do – unless, of course, you become disheartened and stop producing things.</p>

<p>Stay positive, learn from your successes <strong>and</strong> your failures – and good luck!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winning a 48 Hour Film Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T15:37:26-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2014/11/07/winning-a-48-hour-film-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My team, <a href="http://www.shootthemoonfilms.com/">Shoot the Moon Films</a>, won the
2014 Providence Horror Film Project’s “Best Picture” award, as well as scoring
a “Best Actor” award for <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">Nicholas Magrey</a>, a “Best Writing” award for
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm5720821/">Natasha Darius</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm3895408/">Nicholas Magrey</a>, and a “Best Sound Design” award for
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm6854894/">Aaron Theodore Berton</a> for our short film
“<a href="http://www.facebook.com/TheCarving">The Carving</a>” (<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4131910/">IMDb</a>).</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/l4OQm1J0F0w "></iframe></div></p>

<p>I’m used to doing post-mortem analyses on failures, so this is a fairly
unusual task ; why did “The Carving” win against other films – especially
against some very strong contenders?</p>

<h2 id="its-all-about-the-story">It’s all about the story.</h2>

<p>As usual, we didn’t base our story off of any pre-existing concepts, scripts,
etc. Although it is expressly forbidden in the rules of the 48 hour film
projects, it is common knowledge that many teams engage in this practice,
presumably because of the difficulty of producing a good screenplay in the
alloted time.</p>

<p>I’m always proud of our writers, and this was no exception. When you’re
writing a story which has to come out as a four to seven minute short, you
can’t write an over-complicated concept, or take a half hour concept and
cut it down to a few minutes of film. We had used a fairly complicated
concept for our last 48 hour effort, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3713362/">Desire</a>,
and it did not fare very well.</p>

<p>It helps to have writers who know basic tenets of writing, and there are
a ton of online courses, books, and general help to improve scripts. Without
the screenwriters, we would not have won.</p>

<h2 id="sound-is-important-too">Sound is important, too.</h2>

<p>We spend an inordinate amount of post production time on ADR-ing, Foley-ing,
and otherwise enjoying the hard work of our sound engineer, which resulted
in the best <strong>sounding</strong> audio track of any of the films in the festival.
(Don’t take my word for it – it won an award specifically for that.)</p>

<p>Your boom operator has to be paying attention, and your audio setup has to
be… something. Don’t rely on a single source of audio, either. We had an
issue with a cable which resulted in having to use on-camera audio for a
closeup shot. This wouldn’t have been possible without a backup.</p>

<p>(It’s worth noting that in editing, I ended up doing as much audio replacement
as I could before handing off to our sound engineer, to cut down on the
amount of time which he’d have to burn finding the nicest audio for a certain
take.)</p>

<h2 id="take-footage-of-only-what-you-need-to-survive">Take (footage of) only what you need to survive.</h2>

<p>Overly fancy cinematography, while fun to execute (and great for winning
Cinematography awards), is nothing if it doesn’t help propel your story
forward. If you’re trying desperately to find a way to put a quadcopter
shot into your film, you may have lost already.</p>

<p>I’m a huge fan of indulgent, long, complicated shots – but they have to
fit your idiom. If you’re making a four to seven minute long short, you
probably shouldn’t do things just for the sake of doing them. A quick
example was that I had originally planned a jib/crane shot for a particular
piece of exposition, but ended up going with a snorricam rigged shot
instead. The snorricam doesn’t add as much “value” to the end product, but
it told the story <em>better</em>.</p>

<h2 id="on-the-other-hand-think-about-your-video-quality-a-bit">On the other hand, think about your video quality a bit.</h2>

<p>If you’re shooting on a handicam, why? Entry level DSLRs are cheap and
easy to come by, and with the right set of eyes behind the camera, they
can produce great footage.</p>

<p>If you’re not color correcting or grading your footage, why? The walls
behind your characters shouldn’t be changing between shots unless you
intend for them to be doing so. White balancing doesn’t cost any money.</p>

<p>If you’re not lighting your footage, why? A guy with a decent eye and
a few clamp lights can add immeasurable depth and character to your
shots. I know that “low light cinematography” is making the rounds as
the new fad, but you’re not going to get the same type of picture. It
doesn’t cost much (or anything if you already have the equipment at
home), so what’s the harm?</p>

<h2 id="if-you-cant-do-something-find-someone-who-can">If you can’t do something, find someone who can.</h2>

<p>Unless you’re a one person shop, consider finding other people to handle
tasks – especially if they’re better at something than you are. Get
someone with a good eye to handle the cinematography, someone who can
write well to pen your piece, and people who are good with audio to handle
your post production.</p>

<h2 id="dont-try-to-win-try-to-put-out-the-best-film-you-can">Don’t try to win, try to put out the best film you can.</h2>

<p>This is advice I had received right before the 48 started, and it’s some
of the best I’ve had. Because we specifically tried to make the best film
we could make in 48 hours (within the constraints outlined by the 48), we
have a film for our own promotion and uses after the festival ended.</p>

<p>Good luck to you in all of your cinematographic adventures!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
