<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: film | /home/jeff/blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/categories/film/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-28T23:36:48-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[jeff]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mother Night: You Must Be Careful What You Pretend To Be]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/28/mother-night-you-must-be-careful-what-you-pretend-to-be/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-28T21:54:28-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/28/mother-night-you-must-be-careful-what-you-pretend-to-be</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>I suppose the moral here is: You must be careful what you pretend to be… because in the end you are what you pretend to be. - Howard W Campbell, Jr</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are many interesting facets of the film adaptation of Kurt Vonnegut’s novel about the fictional Howard W. Campbell, Jr, a self-described American spy who functioned as a Nazi propagandist during World War II; I’m going to focus on one particular series of scenes during the third act of the film.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Mother Night</em> sets us up with a very particular visual paradigm regarding events in the past and present; much like <em>The Wizard of Oz</em>, present day (or in the case of <em>Wizard</em>, “real life”) events are portrayed in black and white, while narrative events are portrayed in color. This is interestingly subverted in this first scene.</p>

<p>Campbell has just met August Krapptauer, who proceeds to die moments after meeting him. He is asked by the Reverend Dr. Lionel Jones, D.D.S., D.D., to speak at a Neo-Nazi rally – but as he is a wanted man, he instead leaves Jones with a note laced with a sardonic double entendre…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0001.jpg" alt="mother-night-0001" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The truth of your leader, August Krapptauer, and those like him
will be with mankind forever, as long as there are men and women who listen to their guts, instead of their minds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>… which uses Campbell’s literary wit to undermine the very cause his literary wit used to serve.</p>

<p>Even the stoic Nazis are shown to tear up at the passing of their leader, oddly showing emotion for a single loss as they contemplate the extermination of an entire group of people</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0003.jpg" alt="mother-night-0003" /></p>

<p>Jones offers a “special treat”, and we cut to Campbell, who is writing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0011.jpg" alt="mother-night-0011" /></p>

<p>He gets up, and begins following his voice. We see him pass, as a shadow, in front of a poster of Hitler …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0013.jpg" alt="mother-night-0013" /></p>

<p>… and becomes a shadow against the visage of the enormous Nazi flag. The visual contrasts the shadow of a man he has become with the reason <em>why</em> he has become this – the Nazis have taken everything from him, unwittingly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0014.jpg" alt="mother-night-0014" /></p>

<p>Campbell walks out behind the projection screen, which is semi-translucent – he can see the image and the projector light, but the audience cannot see him – and our entire visual paradigm shifts:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0016.jpg" alt="mother-night-0016" /></p>

<p>Campbell is, by virtue of the light casted on him of the recording of his past sins, now represented in the same dichromatic idiom used to represent the present – that same present in which he is both physically and mentally imprisoned for <em>these</em> sins. Campbell occupies a sliver of the frame, compared to the enormous legacy splashed across the screen.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0017.jpg" alt="mother-night-0017" /></p>

<p>We reverse shot to see the pale translucent image projected on his face, and for a moment, we see him through this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0019.jpg" alt="mother-night-0019" /><br />
<img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0020.jpg" alt="mother-night-0020" /></p>

<p>A shadowy figure hands Campbell a note.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0021.jpg" alt="mother-night-0021" /></p>

<p>We look down to see that he is being warned about an impending danger:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0023.jpg" alt="mother-night-0023" /></p>

<p>… and we come back to the same shot of Campbell’s face with the projection overlaid on it, with the ominous words “the last free American”. They are the sign-off that Campbell used during his broadcasts for the Nazis, and again we are treated to an ironic twist to that meaning, for Campbell is effectively a prisoner of his past actions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0024.jpg" alt="mother-night-0024" /></p>

<p>Campbell leaves, and we’re left with a ghostly image of his past repeating the mantra of the Nazi: “Heil Hitler.” This is the lasting image of him – what the world sees when they see him. It isn’t him; it’s an apparition, and we know from the rest of the expositional elements in the story that it doesn’t represent who he is as a person – or does it? Regardless of what kind of a person he believes he is, it’s what he pretended to be that will matter.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0025.jpg" alt="mother-night-0025" /></p>

<p>He leaves, in accordance with the warning note, and enters a building via a side entrance. Campbell is, again, masked in darkness.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0028.jpg" alt="mother-night-0028" /></p>

<p>As he moves down the unmarked hallway, his face becomes illuminated, and as he is finally bathed in light, he steps out…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0031.jpg" alt="mother-night-0031" /></p>

<p>… and we are confronted with what looks like a series of paintings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0032.jpg" alt="mother-night-0032" /></p>

<p>We pan down …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0033.jpg" alt="mother-night-0033" /></p>

<p>… to reveal a rising curtain, with a lone figure in the audience. We instinctually know who it is; it is Frank Wirtanen, Howard’s “blue fairy godmother”.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0034.jpg" alt="mother-night-0034" /></p>

<p>The curtain rises, and Wirtanen claps. Campbell’s entire life is, for a moment, lampooned as the sort of play about selfless heroism which he used to write in his pre-Nazi writing days.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0035.jpg" alt="mother-night-0035" /><br />
<img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0036.jpg" alt="mother-night-0036" /></p>

<p>After Wirtanen tells him that his entire world is a lie, and that his friends are actually conspiring to turn him in, we return to Campbell, slumped over his typewriter, defeated:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/mother-night-0037.jpg" alt="mother-night-0037" /></p>

<p>His reality is the stark black and white of his prison cell, the black and white of the typewriter ink on the blank page, the black and white of the celluloid record of his sins. There is no room for what he perceives to be the nuanced core of his inner being and inherent goodness – he has become what he has pretended to be: a monster, portrayed in the stark contrast of black and white.</p>

<p><em>(All images are presented under <a href="http://libguides.mit.edu/usingimages">fair use guidelines</a> – all frame grabs are property of <strong>Fine Line Features, New Line Cinema, Whyaduck Productions</strong>, or any other entities who hold copyright on this film. They are presented for exclusively educational purposes.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Departed: Introducing Costello and Life in the Shadows]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/26/the-departed-introducing-costello-and-life-in-the-shadows/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-26T18:07:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/26/the-departed-introducing-costello-and-life-in-the-shadows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Scorsese’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0407887/">The Departed</a> netted the venerable director his second “Best Director” Academy Award and only his first “Best Picture” Academy Award in his entire 20+ year career, despite being a remake of another film.</p>

<p>Many film critics and scholars have examined the film’s themes and visuals, but I would like to concentrate on a single character’s introduction and early visualization on the screen: Nicholson’s <em>Frank Costello</em>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We first encounter Frank Costello as a disembodied voice, expounding on existential topics over vintage news footage.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0001.jpg" alt="departed-0001.jpg" /></p>

<p>The first time we actually <em>see</em> him is when he starts a slow walk, in the shadow of a shop with open car bays, from the right to left side of the frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0002.jpg" alt="departed-0002.jpg" /></p>

<p>He appears almost exclusively as a silhouette, with virtually no color present in his face or clothing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0003.jpg" alt="departed-0003.jpg" /></p>

<p>As the shot progresses, the camera dollies from right to left, along with him, but we only catch slight reflections of his glasses. There should be <em>some</em> light hitting him, but there isn’t. This is the midpoint of the shot, where he hits center frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0005.jpg" alt="departed-0005.jpg" /></p>

<p>He delivers his final line of the shot as he begins to drop off the left side of the frame, and out of our purview.</p>

<p>Already we know a few things about the character through his basic exposition and accent (as well as the “Boston” placard in the introductory sequence), but the director’s choice in keeping this character completely shadowed during his introduction speaks more to his nature than another thirty seconds or minute of monologue could. The right-to-left motion of both the camera and Costello offer  subtext to indicate that he is not a good person, and is moving against the natural order of things. We generally expect logical progressions on screen to occur from left to right, which indicate progress, but Scorsese is subverting this by having his character purposefully walk <em>against</em> that directionality.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0006.jpg" alt="departed-0006.jpg" /></p>

<p>The next shot is a wide shot of the exterior of a small store / bodega, and the camera sweeps in to show us the store clerk working behind the counter. There’s nothing special to see here, right?</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0008.jpg" alt="departed-0008.jpg" /></p>

<p>Wrong. We pan back to the left (notice that subtle directionality again), and Costello is there. He isn’t fully shadowed, but his back is to the camera, so we can’t see his face at all.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0009.jpg" alt="departed-0009.jpg" /></p>

<p>The most detail we get of him is his hands in a closeup, exchanging money with the cashier. It’s not immediately apparent when we first see the cashier going for the drawer that Costello is <em>extorting</em> him until the dialogue backs it up …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0010.jpg" alt="departed-0010.jpg" /></p>

<p>… in the wider two-shot. The cashier is almost exactly on the rightmost thirds line in the frame, but Costello is skewed off to the left of the frame, and inexplicably masked in darkness. We can see his face – somewhat – but it’s not clear.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0011.jpg" alt="departed-0011.jpg" /></p>

<p>Even the medium shot of Costello doesn’t offer us much in terms of detail. He’s still mostly locked off in the left third of the frame, with only his arm and a sliver of his face making it into the rest.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0012.jpg" alt="departed-0012.jpg" /></p>

<p>When Sullivan’s younger self is revealed, sitting down, Costello and Sullivan are represented at thirds, and we can see that there’s light everywhere …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0016.jpg" alt="departed-0016.jpg" /></p>

<p>… but not on Costello. Even up close:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0017.jpg" alt="departed-0017.jpg" /></p>

<p>Sullivan, as he starts out on his path with Costello, heads off <em>to the left</em>. He’s even seen leaving Costello behind, in the shadows, on the right.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0019.jpg" alt="departed-0019.jpg" /></p>

<p>We’ve just been given a window into the hierarchy of good and evil in <em>The Departed</em>, even if we might not consciously know it upon first viewing. When we pick back up with Sullivan and Costello, the protégé occupies center frame as Costello paces in the shadows, elucidating his views on the roles of good and evil in society.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0020.jpg" alt="departed-0020.jpg" /></p>

<p>Costello is, again, the only one in the shadows. He’s almost <em>supernaturally</em> shadowed, as everyone else seems plainly visible.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0021.jpg" alt="departed-0021.jpg" /></p>

<p>Even in the middle of a sunny day, in the first of the film’s pertinent flashback sequences, Frank has little to no light on his face. He’s also still occupying the left side of the frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0025.jpg" alt="departed-0025.jpg" /></p>

<p>Cut back to a wider shot, and he’s <em>still on the left</em>, even if only by a very small amount. His face is turned away from us, so we’re denied a full-on glimpse of his visage during this flashback.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0026.jpg" alt="departed-0026.jpg" /></p>

<p>Back to the garage, we see Sullivan’s face over Costello’s shoulder as he literally <em>looks up</em> to this man.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0028.jpg" alt="departed-0028.jpg" /></p>

<p>But, for the final act of his introduction – comprising the most salient point of his long monologue – he starts in the shadows …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0029.jpg" alt="departed-0029.jpg" /></p>

<p>… begins to come out as he sets up his point …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0030.jpg" alt="departed-0030.jpg" /></p>

<p>… and is revealed when he asks “what’s the difference” between being a cop or being a criminal.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/departed-0031.jpg" alt="departed-0031.jpg" /></p>

<p>The gravity of this reveal is absolutely intrinsic to the plot of the film, as Costello is more or less <em>both</em>, being an FBI informant (revealed much later in the film), as well as being one of the most violent and wanted criminals in Boston. He doesn’t see a difference because, for him, there is none, as his true self is revealed.</p>

<p>It is also key in the dual plot threads of criminal pretending to be cop (Sullivan) and cop pretending to be criminal (Costigan) which make up the majority of the film.</p>

<p>One important take-away is that what you don’t see and don’t know can be as important, if not more important, than what you do see and do know. Withholding Costello from us fully for about <em>five minutes</em> means that his introduction is going to mean much more to us, both in <em>how</em> it is done (emerging from the shadows) and <em>when</em> it is done (the context of his speech).</p>

<p><em>(All images are presented under <a href="http://libguides.mit.edu/usingimages">fair use guidelines</a> – all frame grabs are property of <strong>Warner Brothers, Plan B Entertainment, Initial Entertainment Group (IEG)</strong>, or any other entities who hold copyright on this film. They are presented for exclusively educational purposes.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Adventures of Baron Munchausen: Gilliam and the Art of the Reveal Part III]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/25/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal-part-iii/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T09:20:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/25/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal-part-iii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the third (and final) part of a series examining the “reveal” shots in “The Adventures of Baron Munchausen”.</p>

<p>Previous installments of this series are available <a href="/2015/03/22/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal/">here</a> and <a href="/2015/03/23/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal-part-ii/">here</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>For this installment, I’d like to start by reviewing a series of shots ending in a reveal. The Baron and his companions are in the belly of a sea monster, and they are approaching a group of people who were already there. It starts with a POV shot from our protagonists, but probably specifically from Sally’s point of view. We can distantly see the members at the table, but can’t specifically make any of them out.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-01.jpg" alt="E-01" /></p>

<p>The shot is reversed, and we can see our protagonists between two unfamiliar-looking people.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-02.jpg" alt="E-02" /></p>

<p>We move in a little closer to watch Sally, Albrecht, Berthold, and The Baron try to see the occupants of the card game.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-03.jpg" alt="E-03" /></p>

<p>… but the card game is still too far away to make out anything.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-04.jpg" alt="E-04" /></p>

<p>Closer to Sally, so we can really get into her head.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-05.jpg" alt="E-05" /></p>

<p>Gilliam finally gives us a full view of the table so that we can see all of the five clearly visible card players.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-06.jpg" alt="E-06" /></p>

<p>Next up, we get a closeup of the two semi-familiar characters (Gustavus and Adolphus) – The Baron has finally found the last of his lost companions. But that’s not the <em>actual</em> reveal; not yet.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-07.jpg" alt="E-07" /></p>

<p>The Baron and company approach the table…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-08.jpg" alt="E-08" /></p>

<p>… and join the group of misfits (and lost friends) already seated there. Gilliam has set the stage for a reunion between the characters, and that sets our expectations for the following shots much lower.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-09.jpg" alt="E-09" /></p>

<p>Sally is trying to convince The Baron to go back to trying to save the town, but he is despondent, insisting that the town is in no immediate danger. We then see a few quick cuts of the Turks attacking the town, to downplay The Baron’s tenuous grasp on the gravity of the situation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-11.jpg" alt="E-11" /></p>

<p>We’re then treated to a very odd closeup shot of a strange set of hands dealing cards…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-12.jpg" alt="E-12" /></p>

<p>The conversation continues, and Sally circles The Baron, trying to convince him to continue on as he picks up the cards and examines his hand.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-13.jpg" alt="E-13" /></p>

<p>The next thing we see is the payoff of all of this build up – we now know that Gilliam has been dancing around the table position occupied by the embodiment of Death by carefully avoiding allowing us to see him sitting there. All of the characters, including Sally, <em>should</em> be able to see him, but no one seems alarmed or aware of this at all yet. This reverse shot is for <em>us</em>, the audience.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-14.jpg" alt="E-14" /></p>

<p>Sally realizes <em>something</em> is wrong …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-15.jpg" alt="E-15" /></p>

<p>… then does a violent double-take.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-16.jpg" alt="E-16" /></p>

<p>We can now see exactly where Death is, in relation to everyone else – and he’s been hiding in plain sight this entire time.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-E-17.jpg" alt="E-17" /></p>

<p>The next reveal shot that I’d like to examine is probably the most well known. This shot has been somewhat duplicated, allegedly as homage, in Raimi’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0106308/">Army of Darkness</a>, during the scene where Ash is about to be thrown into the monster pit.</p>

<p>We start with a low-angle medium shot of the large golden hand which is meant to catch The Baron’s head.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-01.jpg" alt="F-01" /></p>

<p>We naturally expect a cut to The Baron, the executioner, the Sultan, or maybe others – but instead we start dollying back to reveal The Baron, standing in the precarious position above the execution platform.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-02.jpg" alt="F-02" /></p>

<p>Pull back, and the scribe and executioner move in to fill the negative space on either side of The Baron, as the lower level of the camera becomes less severe in relation to the position of The Baron, and he moves into the dead center of the frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-03.jpg" alt="F-03" /></p>

<p>Further back. We don’t know what’s in front of the platform, and at least for the moment, it seems as though there are a few sparse soldiers.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-04.jpg" alt="F-04" /></p>

<p>But wait – as we move back, they move back into the center, occupying the space where the camera was. In the epistemological system that is the film, outer <em>or</em> inner story, these characters are unaware of a camera or moving observer. Their movement is strictly a function of allowing us to view their numbers.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-05.jpg" alt="F-05" /></p>

<p>Further back. The Baron is still dead center frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-06.jpg" alt="F-06" /></p>

<p>Even further back – the scale has reduced The Baron to a mere pinpoint in the center of the frame, and now we’re seeing flags and banners begin to occupy the space allowing us to see him. The soldiers and troops we’re seeing now <em>can’t actually see</em> the execution, but are here specifically to represent the massive scale of the shot, or maybe were ordered by the power of the Sultan?</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-07.jpg" alt="F-07" /></p>

<p>We now <em>really</em> can’t see The Baron, or the platform, or anything else that is the subject of this shot, but we continue to move backwards. The scale increases, letting us subconsciously understand that this is a massively important moment simply by the virtue of the number of people standing at attention.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-08.jpg" alt="F-08" /></p>

<p>We’re at the end of the shot, with two cannons facing each other – a subtle call-back to the first interaction in this layer of the film which The Baron had with the Turks (grabbing on to a mortar shell as it flew over their encampments and a cannonball on the way back).</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-F-10.jpg" alt="F-10" /></p>

<p>The scale completely sells this shot. We need to see the massive number of extras, props, and scenery so that we can feel that there is an entire army waiting patiently for the death of this symbol – The Baron.</p>

<p>The last sequence I’d like to examine, as part of this series, is the sequence where The Baron leads the “outer film/story” versions of the characters – the actors in the theater, Sally, and the townspeople who have been ostensibly watching him tell these stories on stage – to emphatically “open the gates!”</p>

<p>Skip forward to the confrontation between the city troops, led by The Right Ordinary Horatio Jackson, and the townspeople, led by The Baron. A wide high-angle shot on The Baron, implying disadvantage at the same time it exposes scale …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-01.jpg" alt="G-01" /></p>

<p>… is followed by a closer reverse shot on Jackson, surrounded by his troops. It’s not a direct reverse shot, however. Gilliam has it positioned as though we are standing directly between the two men, at a lower angle – perhaps that of a child? These are, after all, the metaphoric ranks of imagination (The Baron) against reality (Jackson).</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-02.jpg" alt="G-02" /></p>

<p>The Baron plows through the rank and file of reality’s troops like a ship through water.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-03.jpg" alt="G-03" /></p>

<p>Jackson screams at the forces of imagination as they effortlessly glide past him.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-04.jpg" alt="G-04" /></p>

<p>We’re back to The Baron, who is still moving forward, even as Jackson is stuck in place.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-05.jpg" alt="G-05" /></p>

<p>Back to the previous shot of Jackson, who removes his glasses, incredulously.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-06.jpg" alt="G-06" /></p>

<p>We pull back to reveal that Jackson is, more or less, alone and the subject of mockery. A child kicks him in the shin to put the proverbial icing on his humiliation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-07.jpg" alt="G-07" /></p>

<p>Another high shot, to give us the scale of the tide of townspeople surging toward the city gate.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-08.jpg" alt="G-08" /></p>

<p>The logical reverse shot, but with the gate standing between us and the crowd. Gilliam <em>could</em> have shown us more, but purposefully does not allow us to see what’s going on <em>outside</em> of the gates. There’s still some suspense to be had.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-09.jpg" alt="G-09" /></p>

<p>We cut in closer on the motion of the gate to the Baron’s face. There isn’t a definitive reaction on his face; everyone just looks outwards in bewilderment.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-10.jpg" alt="G-10" /></p>

<p>We dolly to the right and pan to the left, to stretch out the palpable tension. Everyone looks out in wonderment, but we are denied a view of the outside of the town.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-11.jpg" alt="G-11" /></p>

<p>Cut to the smoking remains of the battle <em>we just saw</em> in a inner layer of the film. The implication is that the story we were just told wasn’t just a story – Sally literally says this in a few moments – but that means that The Baron may have been telling the truth. In the epistemological system of the outer film/story, this presents a few problems, including that Sally couldn’t have conceivably gone on the journey that The Baron describes, as she was <em>in the theater the whole time</em>. The Baron, as imagination, resembles reality, but does not accurately portray it at all times. Our narrator is a liar, but not entirely.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-12.jpg" alt="G-12" /></p>

<p>I only include the last shot as part of the sequence is necessary for us to internalize what we’re seeing. The townspeople are theoretically objective in the outer layer of the story/film, and seeing them react to this helps us confirm internally that what we’re seeing is <em>real</em> in relation to the reality of the outer layer.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-G-13.jpg" alt="G-13" /></p>

<p>The denouement of the film is the triumph and realization of fantasy / imagination, through The Baron and his companions, over the forces of reality, through The Right Ordinary Horatio Jackson and the endless and pointless “logical” war. It hasn’t just been a battle for the city, but specifically for the youth and innocence represented by Sally. The Baron, when tempted to give his always-present rose (from the Hammerspace in his coat), gives it to Sally after she realizes that this wasn’t just a story.</p>

<p>It’s interesting to note that we never see any other “inner film/story” versions of Adolphus, Gustavus, Albrecht, or Berthold. In the outer layer, we only see them as the actors <em>playing</em> those characters – yet the ending would not be possible without the story in the way that The Baron told it, including his supernatural companions. All of these things have to be hand-waved away by the notion that you have to have imagination (and believe in it) to understand the world of The Baron.</p>

<p><em>(All images are presented under <a href="http://libguides.mit.edu/usingimages">fair use guidelines</a> – all frame grabs are property of <strong>Columbia/Tristar</strong>, or any other entities who hold copyright on this film. They are presented for exclusively educational purposes.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Adventures of Baron Munchausen: Gilliam and the Art of the Reveal Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/23/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal-part-ii/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-23T09:00:19-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/23/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the second part of a series examining the “reveal” shots in “The Adventures of Baron Munchausen”.</p>

<p>The <a href="/2015/03/22/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal/">previous installment of this series</a> is also available.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Sometimes a reveal shot can be as simple as forcing a change in perspective. In the second scene where Sally and The Baron meet with the King of the Moon, we are treated to a perfectly ordinary scene. Gilliam gives us a wall, adorned with pictures, small tables table covered with candleholders, surrounded by chairs … and our protagonists in the middle.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-C-01.jpg" alt="C-01" /></p>

<p>Notice that Gilliam isn’t showing us anything other than the contents of this room and the two walls we can see as part of the frame. We’re led to assume that there are four walls – or at least, at a minimum, that the building continues on in the directions which we cannot see. Sally, looking up at the walls we can see, begins to walk towards the left wall while looking up.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-C-02.jpg" alt="C-02" /></p>

<p>We see her look at a place where there <em>should</em> be a wall, as she continues to walk forward…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-C-03.jpg" alt="C-03" /></p>

<p>… and she stumbles as we begin to see the reality of their situation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-C-04.jpg" alt="C-04" /></p>

<p>Gilliam cuts to a much wider view, and we can see that there never were any walls other than the two we could see, with a large empty space between the floor and the walls.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-C-05.jpg" alt="C-05" /></p>

<p>It’s interesting to note that this should not have been a surprise for Sally – she and the Baron <em>should</em> have been able to see that there were only two walls. Or were there, subjective to the characters? In a way, it doesn’t really matter; we share the surprise of the characters when we are treated to a full scale representation of the insanity of the King. Everything he presents bears some resemblance to reality, but as soon as some perspective is gained, it becomes grotesque and unlike anything we would consider real.</p>

<p>In a later scene, the Baron, his servant Berthold, and Sally fall from the moon into a volcano, to land miraculously unharmed. We are introduced to the god Vulcan (god of war) as he throws flaming chunks of volcanic rock at his underlings.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-01.jpg" alt="D-01" /></p>

<p>Our heroes find themselves in a crater in the volcano. We have no idea what is around them.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-02.jpg" alt="D-02" /></p>

<p>The camera draws back to show us what must be <em>giants</em>. We gather this based on the size of these creatures and their relationship to our protagonists (who are normal-sized people):</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-03.jpg" alt="D-03" /></p>

<p>Gilliam gives us the reverse shot of two of the giants …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-04.jpg" alt="D-04" /></p>

<p>… but only so Vulcan can inject himself into our frame of reference. We know how big these creatures are, in comparison to The Baron, because of the previous pulling back shot.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-05.jpg" alt="D-05" /></p>

<p>To confirm this, The Baron speaks (and is seen) in the reverse shot, still maintaining the known scale of the shot. These creatures are seen to tower over our protagonists, and are quite literally looking down on them, for they are gods and demi-gods.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-06.jpg" alt="D-06" /></p>

<p>We go back to Vulcan, who has decided that he will bring this “tiny mortal” to face him.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-08.jpg" alt="D-08" /></p>

<p>Vulcan’s hand comes down to grab The Baron. This is done so quickly that we are only aware that <em>a hand</em> has entered the frame as we see Vulcan lunge forward, so we don’t immediately assimilate the information about the scale of the hand which we see enter the frame and grab The Baron.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-09.jpg" alt="D-09" /></p>

<p>Gilliam wisely gives us an interstitial shot of The Baron’s companions to break this sequence up. We see his boots and his shadow pass over them to continue the established scale and perceived danger in the scenario. By focusing on their expressions, the suspense of the confrontation with Vulcan can continue to build, and the scale can be built up even more.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-10.jpg" alt="D-10" /></p>

<p>The Baron lands on the same vertical plane as Vulcan. This, again, is done very quickly, so we can see that Vulcan has grabbed him, but not any more information than the basic kinetics of the motion.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-11.jpg" alt="D-11" /></p>

<p>The Baron at rest. We now see that his eyeline is significantly higher than Vulcan’s – how is this possible?</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-12.jpg" alt="D-12" /></p>

<p>In the denouement of this particular farcical reveal, we are given the reverse of the last semi over-the-shoulder shot, and Vulcan looks him up and down. The reality of the difference in sizes is now apparent …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-D-13.jpg" alt="D-13" /></p>

<p>… and the god who was shown to be a giant in comparison to The Baron is actually shorter than him, as Vulcan comically assesses the difference in size between the two characters. There are a number of other comparative references between the two of them, including The Baron’s romantic prowess with Vulcan’s wife and his greater value in the epistemological system that is the reality of the film. We could have been immediately privvy to this information, but through the use of a reveal shot setup, Gilliam is able to not only set up the relationship between the two characters, but also to fool us briefly with a very clever sight gag.</p>

<p><em>(All images are presented under <a href="http://libguides.mit.edu/usingimages">fair use guidelines</a> – all frame grabs are property of <strong>Columbia/Tristar</strong>, or any other entities who hold copyright on this film. They are presented for exclusively educational purposes.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Adventures of Baron Munchausen: Gilliam and the Art of the Reveal]]></title>
    <link href="http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/22/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T15:50:57-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jbuchbinder.com/2015/03/22/the-adventures-of-baron-munchausen-gilliam-and-the-art-of-the-reveal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Terry Gilliam is, in my opinion, one of the great distinctive film directors of the latter part of the 20th century. Books have been written – literally – about his techniques and his rather unique style of filmmaking. I’m going to focus on one of my favorite films of his, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0096764/">The Adventures of Baron Munchausen</a>, to study Gilliam’s artful reveal shots.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>A <em>reveal shot</em> is a shot where one or more visual element(s) are revealed to the viewer through either camera movement, movement in the mise-en-scène, or a combination of the two; the element(s) usually have some sort of significant relevance to the overall plot, as the reveal shot is usually regarded as a fairly powerful shot in a filmmaker’s arsenal.</p>

<p><em>Munchausen</em> is a <a href="/2015/03/08/layers/">layered film</a>, and Gilliam transitions between the different layers of story and relative reality in relatively unusual ways, which I posit is to maintain the tenuous separation between these layers.</p>

<p>One of my favorite reveal shots in the film comes in the first act on a <em>literal</em> stage. The Baron has decided to elucidate what he considers to be the “real” version of events involving himself, as he stands in the narrator’s position on the stage as the curtain is lifted to reveal a set of the Sultan’s Palace, with all the lack-of-depth that such a stage set would afford:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-01.jpg" alt="A-01" /></p>

<p>As he begins to narrate, “The Grand Turk” (the Sultan) – or at least, the actor <em>playing</em> the Sultan in the Salts’ stage production – is pushed out to center stage, as if to prepare to play out the action being narrated by the Baron.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-02.jpg" alt="A-02" /></p>

<p>Gilliam flips back to The Baron so that he can tell a (relatively) personal anecdote about being granted access to the Sultan’s harem.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-03.jpg" alt="A-03" /></p>

<p>We then flip to a side view – what we can only assume is, more or less, a POV shot from The Baron’s point of view. We see the stage hands and the rest of the cast, urging the actor playing the Sultan to move forward.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-04.jpg" alt="A-04" /></p>

<p>He then begins to move forward. Notice that, right now, we’re completely in the theater, and this character is the <em>actor</em> <strong>playing</strong> the Sultan.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-05.jpg" alt="A-05" /></p>

<p>We move forward a few frames, and we see that, rather than the front of the stage, we’re now seeing something that <em>wasn’t there</em> in the previous shots – guards. This is the image where he crosses what <em>should</em> be the threshold of the stage. To the left is the world of the theatre, to the right is … the palace.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-06.jpg" alt="A-06" /></p>

<p>Forward another second or so, and he has completely left the theater, and the character we see in front of us is no longer the <em>actor</em> playing the Sultan, but now <em>is</em> the Sultan.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-A-07.jpg" alt="A-07" /></p>

<p>Without any cutting during the transition, Gilliam has managed to transport us from one reality to another ; from one layer of film to another nested one. This didn’t require any special effects or camera tricks, but simply duplicating a small piece of the theater set (with lighting) adjacent to the edge of the palace set, allowing the juxtaposition of the two realities in a single seamless shot.</p>

<p>Another stylized reveal comes by way of a repeated shot, as part of three – more minor – reveal shots. When The Baron wins the wager with the Sultan, he’s told that he can have as much gold as “the strongest man can carry”. The treasurer opens a comically sized lock …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-01.jpg" alt="B-01" /></p>

<p>… to reveal what appears to be a few gold coins.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-02.jpg" alt="B-02" /></p>

<p>But which when we pull back …</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-03.jpg" alt="B-03" /></p>

<p>… reveals a ridiculous pile of gold and treasure. The next shot shows a pile of treasure with a ladder.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-04.jpg" alt="B-04" /></p>

<p>We crane down…</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-05.jpg" alt="B-05" /></p>

<p>… to reveal Albrecht holding everything on his shoulders.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-06.jpg" alt="B-06" /></p>

<p>Cut to the Baron, looking very smug. Note that this is the <em>same shot</em> used to show the subjective story about the Sultan’s harem from my earlier example, with the Baron appearing in roughly the same framing, but slightly more to the center of the frame. The Baron is front and center in this reality, as opposed to the off-kilter nature of the “real” world of the theater.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-07.jpg" alt="B-07" /></p>

<p>Then we repeat the earlier dolly-back shot to reveal exactly what the Baron and his minions have done with the Sultan’s treasure:</p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-08.jpg" alt="B-08" /></p>

<p><img src="/images/2015/03/munchausen-reveal-B-09.jpg" alt="B-09" /></p>

<p>The framing and composition are the same, with the exception of Albrecht moving the treasure, which had been in the foreground in the previous shot, out of the comically small exit, and beating a hasty retreat.</p>

<p><em>In the interests of brevity, I’m breaking this post up into multiple parts, so that I can demonstrate more examples of the full range of reveal shots used by Gilliam in this film.</em></p>

<p><em>(All images are presented under <a href="http://libguides.mit.edu/usingimages">fair use guidelines</a> – all frame grabs are property of <strong>Columbia/Tristar</strong>, or any other entities who hold copyright on this film. They are presented for exclusively educational purposes.)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
